<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<!--

Documentation standards for the manual.

-->

<appendix id="app.docstand">
  <title>Documentation Standards for the User Manual</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The entire manual is written using
      <ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook"><application>DocBook
        XML&nbsp;V4.1.2</application></ulink>. This section covers some
      conventions for use of DocBook and for the documentation in general. It
also includes some information for Emacs users
and the psgml package.
</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- Conventions for the document in general -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Style</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
"We" in the document means the persons reading the document and using
&argouml;
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
"I" in the document refers to the author and is only used to denote
the authors personal opinion. 
Avoid using it! 
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Use the active voice.</para>
      </listitem>
  
      <listitem>
        <para>Use plain rather than elegant language.</para>
      </listitem>
  
      <listitem>
        <para>
Use specific and concrete terms rather than vague generalities.
</para>
      </listitem>
  
      <listitem>
        <para>
Break up your writing in short sections.
Each section dealing with one topic.
</para>
      </listitem>
  
      <listitem>
        <para>Use the present tense.</para>
      </listitem>
  
      <listitem>
        <para>Opt for an informal rather than a formal style.</para>
      </listitem>
  
  
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Document Conventions</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
All titles of chapters, sections etc are capitalized throughout.
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
All titles of figures, tables etc have the first word only capitalized.
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
Spelling is US English.
(According to The Webster's Second Unabridged.)
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
Use full URLs throughout this manual!
We allow for the manual being other than as html on the &argouml; web site.
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
Don't include lists of what changes that has been done.
This information is kept by cvs, the version control tool.
This is changed since Jeremy Bennet made the work for 0.9/0.10
so there are still such lists.
Remove them while changing the files!
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
If a problem in the current implementation of &argouml; is mentioned
or perhaps even emphasized using 
<sgmltag>warning</sgmltag>
include the issue number in a sgml-comment in the source 
so that it is easy to know if this problem has been fixed.
</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- Conventions relating to DocBook -->

  <sect1>
    <title>DocBook Conventions</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
The top level document is argouml.xml (actually in argouml.in 
and copied to argouml.xml by the build script). 
Each chapter (or
        preface, glossary, appendix etc) is a separate file, defined as a
        system entity and included from this top level
        file.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>There are some useful entities defined for common terms
        at the top of argouml.xml. Of these, use of
        <sgmltag>argouml</sgmltag> will ensure consistent naming of the
product (ArgoUML) and allow us to change it later (to Argo/UML,
        Argouml or whatever).</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>XML comments are used throughout to explain what various
        sections are trying to achieve.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Cross-referencing requires use of <literal>id.</literal>
        attributes. To avoid confusion, use a prefix of <literal>ch.</literal>
        for <sgmltag>chapter</sgmltag>, <literal>app.</literal> for
        <sgmltag>appendix</sgmltag>, <literal>s1.</literal> through
        <literal>s5.</literal> for <sgmltag>sect1</sgmltag> through
        <sgmltag>sect5</sgmltag>, <literal>fig.</literal> for
        <sgmltag>figure</sgmltag>, <literal>tab.</literal> for
        <sgmltag>table</sgmltag> and <literal>gl</literal> for
        <sgmltag>glossentry</sgmltag>.</para>

        <para>A second prefix of <literal>tut.</literal> or
          <literal>ref.</literal> is used to distinguish tutorial and reference
          material. The remainder of the tag should be descriptive, but concise
          with words separate by underscore. Where a graphic is involved this
          remainder should correspond to the file name. For example
          <literal>fig.ref.navigation_pane</literal> for a figure showing the
          explorer, with the diagram in
          <literal>navigation_pane.gif</literal></para>

	<para>
There is one exception to this and that is the critics.
Each paragraph about a critic is instead marked with
<literal>critics.</literal> followed by the classname
implementing that critic.
The reason for this is that the intention is to have the manual
accessable when pressing the Help button on that critic.
Generating a link to the correct place in the manual is easier
if the classname need not undergo some kind of textual
transformation and the implementation doesn't
care if a a specific critic is described in a 
<sgmltag>sect1</sgmltag>, 
<sgmltag>sect2</sgmltag>,
<sgmltag>sect3</sgmltag>, or
<sgmltag>sect4</sgmltag>.
Reorganizing the manual would otherwise affect also the
java code.
The conversion to the correct tagname or really the correct URL
is currently implemented in the 
<literal>defaultMoreInfoURL()</literal>
method in the
<literal>org.argouml.cognitive.critics.Critic</literal>
class.
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Only use <sgmltag>glossterm</sgmltag> (for the term
        <emphasis>or</emphasis> its abbreviation/acronym),
        <sgmltag>glossdef</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>glossseealso</sgmltag>
        within <sgmltag>glossentry</sgmltag>. Other entries are not
        implemented in the style sheets and so do not appear in the
        glossary!</para></listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
Use spaces rather than tabs. 
Tabs are generally set so large the text moves over to the right of the page,
and are not set the same everywhere (emacs uses 8 spaces, some MS
editors use 6 spaces), making documents unreadable between users.
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
Indent only the tags, not the text.
The Docbook source is kept in cvs that is a line-oriented tool. 
This means that reindentation will be a major thing in cvs making
it hard to see if there were other things done to the code.
Especielly if reindentation caused the paragraphs to be broken
in a different way.
Not indenting the text means that the text will be unchanged even
if the heading level was changed.
The contributions that Jeremy Bennet did for 0.10 
are not indented like this.
Change it while changing the paragraphs.
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
Make a new line after each sentence or before expressions.
The Docbook source is source that is handled by cvs.
When structuring the text the parts are paragraphs, sentences and words.
By having each sentence on a line of its own it is easier to see
what sentences has been changed and what has not in the diff reports
from cvs.
The contributions that Jeremy Bennet did 
are not written like this.
Change it while changing the paragraphs.
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>All block graphics should be encapsulated within
        <sgmltag>figure</sgmltag>, allowing reference from around the
        text. Set attribute <sgmltag>float</sgmltag> to 1 to allow the figure
        to float (makes life easier for printed version).</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>All block graphics should be provided through
        <sgmltag>mediaobject</sgmltag> and provided with both an
        <sgmltag>imageobject</sgmltag> and comprehensive description in a
        <sgmltag>textobject</sgmltag>. This gives the potential of meaningful
        content where a diagram cannot be displayed for any
        reason. Where appropriate the <sgmltag>mediaobject</sgmltag> should be
        wrapped by <sgmltag>screenshot</sgmltag>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Inline graphics can be done through
        <sgmltag>inlinegraphic</sgmltag>, rather
        <sgmltag>inlinemediaobject</sgmltag>. A textual alternative is of
        little value in these circumstances. Where appropriate the
        <sgmltag>mediaobject</sgmltag> should be wrapped by
        <sgmltag>guiicon</sgmltag></para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>In general use <sgmltag>literal</sgmltag> for computer
        related text (input and output). There are a huge number of possible
        specialist tags, but I suggest restriction to the following list:
        <sgmltag>filename</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>application</sgmltag>.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- Conventions relating to use of emacs -->

  <sect1>
    <title>For Emacs Users</title>

    <para>If you use the psgml library within emacs, then editing and
      verifying XML gets easier. Information on using this facility is
      inluded with psgml.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Emacs' local variables appear in a few lines of 
comment at the bottom of each XML file. 
Please don't delete these!
</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Adding
        <literal>(setq&nbsp;sgml-set-face&nbsp;t)</literal> to your
        <filename>.emacs</filename> file will cause all tags and entities to
        appear in boldface.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Adding
        <literal>(setq&nbsp;sgml-auto-activate-dtd&nbsp;t)</literal> to your
        <filename>.emacs</filename> file will ensure the DocBook DTD is
        parsed as soon as the file is loaded.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
        
</appendix>

<!-- Local stuff for Emacs - please do not delete

Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-doctype: "argomanual.xml"
sgml-parent-document: ("argomanual.xml" "appendix" nil)
sgml-validate-command: "nsgmls -wxml -sv ../docbook-setup/xml.dcl \
  argomanual.xml"
indent-tabs-mode: nil
End:

-->
