<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--

The overall introduction to the book. Sections are:

1. Origins and overview of &argouml;

2. Scope of this User Manual

3. Overview of the User Manual

4. Assumptions

-->
 
<chapter>

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <!-- This section takes us through the history of Argo/UML -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Origins and Overview of &argouml;</title>

    <!-- The origins of OOA&D and its rise to prominence -->

    <sect2 id="s2.ooad">
      <title>Object Oriented Analysis and Design</title>

      <para>Over the past decade, Object Oriented Analysis and Design (&ooad;)
        has become <emphasis>the</emphasis> dominant software development
        paradigm. With it has come a major shift in the thought processes of
        all involved in the software development life cycle.</para>

      <para>Programming language support for objects began with Simula&nbsp;67,
        but it was the emergence in the 1980's of hybrid languages, such as
        C++, Ada and Object Pascal that allowed &ooad; to take off. These
        languages provided support for both OO and procedural
        programming. Object Oriented <emphasis>programming</emphasis> became
        mainstream.</para>

      <para>An OO system is designed and implemented as a
        <emphasis>simulation</emphasis> of the real world using software
        artifacts. This premise is as powerful as it is simple. By using an OO
        approach to <emphasis>design</emphasis> a system can be designed and
        tested (or more correctly simulated) without having to actually build
        the system first.</para>

      <para>It is the development during the 1990's of tools to support Object
        Oriented <emphasis>analysis</emphasis> and <emphasis>design</emphasis>
        that moved this approach into the mainstream. When coupled with the
        ability to design systems at a very high level, a tool based &ooad;
        approach has enabled the implementation of more complex systems than
        previously possible.</para>

     <para>The final driver that has propelled &ooad; has been its suitability
        for modeling graphical user interfaces. The popularity of object based
        and object oriented graphical languages such as Visual Basic and Java
        reflect the effectiveness of this approach.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Why Argo/UML was developed and why it is different -->

    <sect2>
      <title>The Development of &argouml;</title>

      <para>During the 1980's a number of &ooad; process methodologies and
        notations were developed by different research teams. It became clear
        there were many common themes and, during the 1990's, a unified
        approach for &ooad; notation was developed under the auspices of the
        <ulink url="http://www.omg.org">Object Management Group</ulink>. This
        standard became known as the Unified Modeling Language (UML), and is
        now the standard language for communicating OO concepts.</para>

      <para>&argouml; was conceived as a tool and environment for use in the
        analysis and design of object-oriented software systems. In this sense
        it is similar to many of the commercial CASE tools that are sold as
        tools for modeling software systems. &argouml; has a number of very
        important distinctions from many of these tools.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>&argouml; draws on research in cognitive psychology to
          provide novel features that increase productivity by supporting the
          cognitive needs of object-oriented software designers and
          architects.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>&argouml; supports open standards
          extensively&mdash;UML, XMI, SVG, OCL and others. In this respect,
          &argouml; is still ahead of many commercial tools.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>&argouml; is a 100% pure Java application. This allows
          &argouml; to run on all platforms for which a reliable port of the
          Java2 platform is available.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>&argouml; is an open source project. The availability
          of the source ensures that a new generation of software
          designers and researchers now have a proven framework from which they
          can drive the development and evolution of CASE tool
          technologies.</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>UML is the most prevalent OO modeling language and Java is one of
        the most productive OO development platforms. Jason Robbins and the
        rest of his research team at the University of California, Irvine
        leveraged these benefits in creating the &argouml;. The result is a
        solid development tool and environment for OO systems design. Further,
        it provides a test bed for the evolution of object oriented CASE tools
        development and research.</para>

      <para>A first release of &argouml; was available in 1998 and more than
        100,000 downloads by mid-2001 show the impact that this project has
        made, being popular in educational and commercial fields.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- A bit more on the status of the project. Taken from Andreas. -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Finding Out More About the &argouml; Project</title>

      <!-- The Argo/UML process and infrastructure -->

      <sect3>
        <title>How &argouml; is Developed</title> 

	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Jason Robbins</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Robbins, Jason</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Mailing lists</primary>
	</indexterm>

        <para>Jason Elliot Robbins founded the Argo Project and provided early
          project leadership.  While Jason remains active in the project, he
          has handed off project leadership.  The project continues to move
          forward strongly.  There are more than 300 members on the developer
          mailing list (see <ulink
          url="http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList">
          http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList</ulink>),
          with a couple of dozen of those forming the core development
          group.</para>

        <para>This is the place where all the discussion on the latest tasks
          takes place, and developers discuss the directions the project should
          take. Although controversial at times, these discussions are always
          kept nice and friendly (no flame-wars and such), so newbies should
          not hesitate and participate in them. You'll always get a warm
          welcome there.</para>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Contributing</primary>
	  <secondary>to &argouml;</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Cookbook</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Developers' Cookbook, The</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Developer Zone</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
If you want to learn some details about how the project is run and
how you should go about to contribute go the the 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/dev.html">&argouml;
Web Site Developer Zone</ulink>
and read through the documentation there.
The Cookbook is an important document.
</para>
      </sect3>

      <!-- More on the infrastructure -->

      <sect3>
        <title>More on Infrastructure</title>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Mailing lists</primary>
	</indexterm>

        <para>
Besides the developer mailing list, there's also a mailing for users
(see <ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList">
The &argouml; Mailing List List</ulink>),
where we can discuss problems from a user perspective.
Developers also read this list, so there's a good chance to get
qualified help.
</para>

	<indexterm>
	  <primary>FAQ</primary>
	</indexterm>
        <para>Before posting to this list, you should take a look at the
          <ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/faqs/users.html">
            user FAQ</ulink> maintained by Ewan R. Grantham.</para>

        <para>
More information on ArgoUML and other UML related topics is also
available on the 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org">ArgoUML website</ulink>,
maintained by Linus Tolke.
</para>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- What we do and don't do in this document. Includes target audience and
       limitations of the current version, with links to other documents. -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Scope of This User Manual</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Target Audience</title>

      <para>The current release of this document is aimed at experienced users
        of UML in &ooad; (perhaps with other tools) who wish to transfer to
        &argouml;.</para>

      <para>Future releases will support designers who know &ooad;, and wish to
        adopt UML notation within their development process.</para>

      <para>A long term goal is to support i) those who are learning design and
        wish to start with an &ooad; process that uses UML notation, and ii)
        people interested in modularized code design with a GUI.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Scope</title>

      <para>The intention is that this document will provide a comprehensive
        guide, enabling designers to use &argouml; to its full extent. It is in
        two parts.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>A tutorial manual, showing how to work with
          &argouml;</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>A complete reference manual, recording everything you
          can do with &argouml;.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The current version of the document has achieved the second of
        these.</para>

      <para>In this guide there are some things you will not find, because they
        are covered elsewhere.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Descriptions of how &argouml; works on the
          inside.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>How to improve &argouml; with new features and
          functions.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>A trouble shooting guide.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>A summary quick reference to using
          &argouml;.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>These are covered in 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/documentation/defaulthtml/cookbook/">
the Developers Cookbook</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/faqs/users.html">the FAQ</ulink>, 
and
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/documentation/defaulthtml/quickguide/">
the Quick Guide</ulink>.
</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- Let the reader know how the manual is structured. -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview of the User Manual</title>

    <!-- Tutorial chapters structure -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Tutorial Manual Structure</title>

      <para><xref linkend="ch.tut.uml"/> provides an overview of UML based
        &ooad;, including a guide to getting &argouml; up and running.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="ch.tut.reqs"/> through <xref linkend="ch.tut.build"/>
        then step through each part of the design process from initial
        requirements capture through to final project build and
        deployment.</para>

      <para>As each UML concept is encountered, its use is explained. Its use
        within &argouml; is then described. Finally the a study is used to
        give examples of the concepts in use.</para>
    </sect2>         


    <!-- Reference material, which includes glossary, appendixes, index
         etc. -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Reference Manual Structure</title>

      <para><xref linkend="ch.ref.ui"/> is an overview of the user interface
        and provides a summary of the support for the various UML diagram types
        in &argouml;. Separate chapters <xref linkend="ch.ref.navpane"/>
        through <xref linkend="ch.ref.menu"/> describe each of the sub-windows
        of the user interface, known as <emphasis>Panes</emphasis>, and the
        menu bar.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="ch.ref.critics"/> gives details of all the cognitive
        critics within the system. Eventually &argouml; will link directly to
        this manual when giving advice on critics.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="ch.ref.entities"/> is an overview of the artifacts
        (i.e. the UML entities that can be placed on diagrams) within
        &argouml;. The following chapters (<xref linkend="ch.ref.entusecase"/>
        through <xref linkend="ch.ref.entbuiltin"/>) describe, the artifacts
        that can be created through each &argouml; diagram, and their
        properties, as well as some standard artifacts provided with the
        system.</para>

      <para>A complete <xref linkend="glossary"/> is provided.  <xref
          linkend="app.casestudy"/> provides material to supplement the case
        study used throughout the document. <xref linkend="app.umlres"/> and
        <xref linkend="app.umlcase"/> identify background information on UML
        and UML CASE tools. <xref linkend="app.docplan"/> describes the plan
        for creation of this manual. <xref linkend="app.docstand"/> gives
        some guidelines for those writing this manual. <xref
          linkend="app.legal"/> is a copy of the GNU Free Documentation
        License.</para>

      <para>A future ambition is to provide a comprehensive index</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Make it easy to get feedback. This section also appears in the
         preface. -->

    <sect2>
      <title>User Feedback</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>Feedback</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>User Feedback</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Contributing</primary>
	<secondary>to the User Manual</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Please tell us what you think about this User Manual. Your
        comments will help us make improvements. Email your thoughts to the
        <ulink url="mailto:users@argouml.tigris.org">&argouml; Users Mailing
          List</ulink>.
In case you would like to add to the missing chapters 
you should contact the 
<ulink url="mailto:dev@argouml.tigris.org">&argouml; 
Developer Mailing List</ulink> 
to check whether noone else is working on this part. 
You can subscribe to either of the mailinglists via 
the <ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org">&argouml; web site</ulink>.
</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- We have a dream for a manual that will be all things to all people. This
       explains how we currently fall short.

       In the current version, we assume familiarity with UML, and the case
       study is very limited. -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Assumptions</title>

    <para>This release of the manual assumes the reader is very familiar
      with UML already. This is reflected in the sparseness of the description
      of UML concepts in the tutorial.</para>

    <para>The case study is described, but not yet fully realized throughout
      the tutorial. This will be achieved in future releases of the
      manual.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<!-- Local stuff for Emacs - please do not delete

Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-doctype: "argomanual.xml"
sgml-parent-document: ("argomanual.xml" "chapter" nil)
sgml-validate-command: "nsgmls -wxml -sv ../docbook-setup/xml.dcl \
  argomanual.xml"
End:

-->
