<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--

This is the top level reference to the User Interface. To keep things
manageable, the description of each of the panes and the menu bar have their
own chapters.

Modifications
=============

 5 Dec 2001:  Jeremy Bennett. Broken out as a separate section from the
              original manual by Alejandro, Phillipe and Andreas.

23 Jan 2002:  Jeremy Bennett. Moved all discussion of menu buttons in to this
              section to avoid duplication and completed the chapter.

-->

<chapter id="ch.ref.ui">
  <title>User Interface Reference</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This chapter describes the overall behavior of the user
      interface. Description of the various component parts&mdash;the menu bar,
      panes and various diagrams&mdash; is in separate chapters.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- An overview of the window as a whole -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview of the Window</title>

    <para><xref linkend="fig.ref.guioverview"/> shows the main &argouml;
      window.</para>

    <!-- A big diagram with all the bits pointed out. At the moment its just a
         plane screenshot, but it would be nice to float in some bubbles
         pointing out things. -->

    <figure id="fig.ref.guioverview" float="1">
      <title>Overview of the &argouml; window</title>

      <screenshot><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="GIF" align="center"
                     fileref="images/reference/guioverview.gif"/>
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <para>A display of the &argouml; window, showing at the top the menu
            bar, in the main area four sub-windows and at the bottom a status
            bar. The four sub-windows are arranged two by two, and named,
            clockwise from top left as: navigator pane, editing pane, details
            pane and to-do pane. at the top of the editing pane is a horizontal
            tool bar.</para>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject></screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>At the top of screen is a <emphasis>menu bar</emphasis> described in
      <xref linkend="ch.ref.menu"/>. The bulk of the window comprises four
      sub-windows or <emphasis>panes</emphasis>. Clockwise from top left these
      are the <emphasis>navigator pane</emphasis> (see <xref
      linkend="ch.ref.navpane"/>), <emphasis>editing pane</emphasis> (see <xref
      linkend="ch.ref.editpane"/>), <emphasis>details pane</emphasis> (see
      <xref linkend="ch.ref.navpane"/>) and <emphasis>to-do pane</emphasis>
      (see <xref linkend="ch.ref.navpane"/>). At the top of the editing pane is
      a <emphasis>tool bar</emphasis>. An overview of the panes is given in
      <xref linkend="s1.ref.panes"/>. Finally at the bottom of the window is a
      <emphasis>status bar</emphasis> described in <xref
      linkend="s1.ref.status"/>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- The central explanation of how the mouse behaves -->

  <sect1>
    <title>General Mouse Behavior in &argouml;</title>

    <para>&argouml; assumes a two button mouse. We will refer to the buttons as
      <quote>&button1;</quote> and <quote>&button2;</quote>. &Button1; is the
      leftmost button on a right-handed mouse, and sometimes referred to as the
      <emphasis>select</emphasis> button. &Button2; is the rightmost button on
      a right-handed mouse, and is sometimes referred to as the
      <emphasis>adjust</emphasis> button.</para>

    <!-- Button1 click -->

    <sect2>
      <title>&Button1; Click</title>

      <para>This action is generally used to select an item for subsequent
        operations. If the item is an artifact in the navigation pane or the
        editing pane it will be highlighted.</para>

      <!-- Within the navigation pane -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within the Navigation Pane</title>

        <para>Within the hierarchical display elements which have
        sub-hierarchies are indicated by
        <guiicon><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
          format="GIF" align="center"
          fileref="images/icons/hierarchy_closed.gif"/>
        </imageobject></inlinemediaobject></guiicon> when the hierarchy is
        hidden and 
        <guiicon><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
          format="GIF" align="center"
          fileref="images/icons/hierarchy_open.gif"/>
        </imageobject></inlinemediaobject></guiicon> when the hierarchy is
        open.</para>

        <para>&Button1; click over the name of any diagram artifact will cause
          the diagram to be selected and displayed in the editing pane. Its
          details will also be displayed in the details pane.</para>

        <para>&Button1; click over the name of any artifact other than a
          diagram in the main area of the navigation pane will cause it to be
          selected, and its details shown in the details pane. If the artifact
          is part of a diagram currently displayed in the editing pane, it will
          be highlighted there.</para>

        <note><para>If the artifact is part of a diagram other than that
          currently displayed in the Editing Pane, there will be
          <emphasis>no</emphasis> change of diagram in the Editing
          Pane.</para></note>
      </sect3>

      <!-- Within the editing pane -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within the Editing Pane</title>

        <para>In the tool bar of the editing pane, &button1; click is used to
          select the next tool for adding artifacts to the diagram (but only
          once&mdash;see double clicking for adding multiple artifacts).
          Adding to the diagram is achieved by moving the mouse to the editing
          area and clicking again.</para>

        <para>There are various more detailed effects, which are discussed
          under the descriptions of the various tools (see
          <xref linkend="s1.ref.edit_pane_tool_bar"/>).</para>
      </sect3>

      <!-- Behavior within menus -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within the Menu Bar</title>

        <para>Over a top level drop down menu this will expose the menu.</para>

        <para>Over a menu entry this will invoke the action of the menu.</para>

        <para>Within menu dialog boxes this will generally select a text item,
          and invoke a button action.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Button1 double click -->

    <sect2>
      <title>&Button1; Double Click</title>

      <para>In general this action is identical to a single click
        <emphasis>except</emphasis>, when it is used with the editing pane
        tool bar, in the to-do pane, or in dialog boxes (which are mostly
        associated with menu actions).</para>

      <!-- Behavior within the editing pane -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within the Editing Pane</title>

        <para>When used on the tool bar with a tool to add an artifact, the
        selected artifact will be added multiple times to the drawing area,
        once for each further button click, until the tool is again selected or
        another tool chosen.</para>
      </sect3>

      <!-- Behavior within the to-do pane -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within the To-Do Pane</title>

        <para>Within the to-do pane this will select the diagram for the
          associated artifact in the editing pane and highlight the artifact
          that is affected using an appropriate clarifier (the artifact may be
          highlighted, underlined with a wavy line or surrounded by a colored
          box as appropriate).</para>
      </sect3>

      <!-- Behavior within dialogs -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within Dialog Boxes</title>

        <para>Within dialog boxes this will cause an action associated
          with a text item to be invoked. For example double clicking on a
          filename during the <literal>Open&nbsp;Project&hellip;</literal>
          dialog will cause the file to be selected and opened.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Button1 Motion -->

    <sect2>
      <title>&Button1; Motion</title>

      <!-- Within the editing pane -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within the Editing Pane</title>

        <para>When adding an artifact using the toolbar, &button1; motion can
          generally be used to define the size of the new artifact. Its
          dimensions (line ends, diagonal corners of a rectangular artifact
          etc) are defined by &button1; down and &button1; up.</para>

        <para>Over graphical artifacts &button1; motion will move the artifact
          to a new position. Graphical artifacts that are selected show
          handles, and these can be used for re-sizing.</para>

        <para>Some artifacts (e.g. actor, class) show special handles at the
          sides, top and bottom, which can be dragged to form types of
          relationship with other artifacts.</para>

        <para>Where the artifact is some form of connector between other items,
          &button1; motion other than at a handle will cause a new handle to be
          created, allowing the connector to be articulated at that point. Such
          new handles can be removed by moving them to the end of the
          connector.</para>

        <para>There are various more detailed effects, which are discussed
          under the descriptions of the various tools (see
          <xref linkend="s1.ref.edit_pane_tool_bar"/>).</para>
      </sect3>

      <!-- Behavior within menus -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within the Menu Bar</title>

        <para>Moving over a top level menu, or a sub-menu will cause that menu
          to be exposed.</para>

        <para>If the button is released (thereby completing a click) over a
          menu entry that entry will be invoked.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Button2 click -->

    <sect2>
      <title>&Button2; Actions</title>

      <para>When used over text items in the the navigation or details panes,
        or graphical artifacts in the editing pane, this will display a context
        dependent pop-up menu.</para>

      <para>If the item or artifact has not yet been selected it will also be
        selected.</para>

      <para>In general there are no &button2; actions associated with
        menus.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Button2 double click -->

    <sect2>
      <title>&Button2; Double Click</title>

      <para>This has no effect other than that of &button2; single
        click.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Button2 Motion -->

    <sect2>
      <title>&Button2; Motion</title>

      <para>This is used to select items in a context sensitive menu popped up
        by use of &button2; click.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- Shift and control keys -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Shift and Control with &Button1;</title>

      <!-- Where there is a list of things -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within Lists</title>

        <para>This behavior applies where there is a list of things that may
          be selected. This includes various dialog boxes, and the to-do pane,
          where there is a list of to-do items to be selected.</para>

        <para>Where selections are to be made, the SHIFT key is used to with
          &button1; to <emphasis>extend</emphasis> from the original &button1;
          selection to the current position.</para>

        <para>Similarly the CONTROL key with &button1; is used to add
          individual items to the current selection. Where Ctrl-&button1; is
          used on an item already selected, that item is removed from the
          selection.</para>
      </sect3>

      <!-- Within diagrams -->

      <sect3>
        <title>Within Diagrams</title>

        <para>This behavior applies to diagrams within the editing
          pane.</para>

        <para>Where selections are to be made, the SHIFT key is used to with
          &button1; to <emphasis>add</emphasis> unselected artifacts to the
          current selection. Where an artifact is already selected, it is
          removed from the current selection.</para>

        <para>The CONTROL key is effective where selected artifacts are being
          moved. Using the CONTROL key will cause them to be moved with the
          broom (see <xref linkend="ch.ref.editpane"/>).</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- General information about Panes -->

  <sect1 id="s1.ref.panes">
    <title>General Information About Panes</title>

    <para>The four sub-windows of the main &argouml; window are called
      <emphasis>panes</emphasis>. Clockwise from top left these are the
      <emphasis>navigator pane</emphasis> (see <xref
      linkend="ch.ref.navpane"/>), <emphasis>editing pane</emphasis> (see <xref
      linkend="ch.ref.editpane"/>), <emphasis>details pane</emphasis> (see
      <xref linkend="ch.ref.navpane"/>) and <emphasis>to-do pane</emphasis>
      (see <xref linkend="ch.ref.navpane"/>). At the top the editing pane is a
      <emphasis>tool bar</emphasis>.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Re-sizing Panes</title>

      <para>You can re-size panes by dragging on the divider bars between
        them.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="s2.ref.spawn">
      <title>Looking at Different Diagrams Simultaneously</title>

      <para>You can <quote>spawn</quote> a copy of the editing pane by
        double-clicking on the <literal>As Diagram</literal> tab at the bottom
        of the pane. It will then show as an individual window and you can put
        it where you will on the screen.</para>

      <para>The same effect is achievable with the tabs of the details
        pane.</para>

      <note><para>There is no equivalent function for the navigation or to-do
        panes.</para></note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Reducing the Number of Panes Visible</title>

      <para>This function is not implemented directly. However you can spawn
        a pane (see <xref linkend="s2.ref.spawn"/>) and maximize this to be the
        whole window, which achieves the same thing.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- All about the status bar -->

  <sect1 id="s1.ref.status">
    <title>The status bar</title>

    <para>The status bar is at the very bottom of the &argouml; window and is
      used to display short advisory messages.</para>

    <para>In the current release of &argouml; the only messages are those
      associated with &button1; motion in the editing pane. Where &button1; is
      held down over a 2-D artifact, the message
      <literal>Move&nbsp;object(s)</literal> will appear. Where &button1; is
      held down over a connector, the message
      <literal>Add&nbsp;a&nbsp;point</literal> will appear.</para>

    <note><para>&argouml; is a system in development, and occasionally other
      messages will appear. In particular clicking on the background on the
      editing pane will cause a message of the form
      <literal>[&lt;n&gt;]</literal> to appear where &lt;n&gt; is a small
      integer.</para></note>
  </sect1>

</chapter>

<!-- Local stuff for Emacs - please do not delete

Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-doctype: "argomanual.xml"
sgml-parent-document: ("argomanual.xml" "chapter" nil)
sgml-validate-command: "nsgmls -wxml -sv ../docbook-setup/xml.dcl \
argomanual.xml"
End:

-->
