<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"  "../docbook-setup/docbookx/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ArgoUM and Poseidon for UML Documentation -->
<book>
	<title>ArgoUML and Poseidon for UML</title>
	<chapter>
		<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
		<qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
			<qandadiv>
				<title>General Questions</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
							What is Java Web Start?
						</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
							JWS = Java Webstart, some Sun technology which allows you start Java
							Applications via the web. You can start ArgoUML as well as Poseidon for
							UML Community Edition from www.argouml.org
							and www.gentleware, respecitvely. Just click on the provided link (after
							installing JWS).
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
							What are the names of the various work screens?
						</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
							The different screens are called panes. They all have an individual
							name, Navigation Pane, Diagram Pane, ToDo Pane and Details Pane, as
							shown in the following table.
							<table frame="all">
								<title>Table title</title>
								<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
									<tbody>
										<row>
											<entry>Navigation Pane</entry>
											<entry>Diagram Pane</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry>ToDo Pane</entry>
											<entry>Details Pane</entry>
										</row>
									</tbody>
								</tgroup>
							</table>
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
							Where do I get the code for ArgoUML?
						</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
							You can download the latest release of Argo in source from
							www.argouml.org. Or you can get the must current code from CVS. You can
							reach it via normal cvs command (either in a tool or on the
							command line). The server is the same as for ARGOUML (try
							:pserver:guest@cvs.tigris.org:/cvs) and the name of the repository is
							gef/src. This is the GEF repository. The Argo rep (for 0.9.x versions)
							is argouml/src_new.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
							Is there commercial support for ARGO?
						</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
							Yes there is, Gentleware provides enhanced versions of Argo as well as
							support. It was founded by some to the core developers of ArgoUML.
							See http://www.gentleware.com.
					</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
			<qandadiv>
				<title>Diagrams</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
							How do I arrange my diagram elements?
						</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
							There are several ways to easily and elegantly move diagram elements.
						</para>
						<para>
							Select the elements you want to move. By holding down the
							controll key you can select several.
							Now hit your arrow keys. Your elements move a little with every key
							stroke. If you also hold down the shift key, they move a bit faster.
						</para>
						<para>
							Or click on the broom button, move your mouse to the diagram
							pane, right click and hold. Now moving your mouse side ways (or up and
							down)
							will allign elements.
						</para>
						<para>
							There also is the menu item arrage where you can allign, group or nodge
							(move a little bit) elements.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
How can I look at different diagrams at the same time?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
You can 'spawn' a panel by
double-clicking on the tab. It will then show as individual window and
you can put it next to another.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
			<qandadiv>
					<title>Class Diagrams</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
						</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
			<qandadiv>
				<title>Activity Diagrams</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
How do I create an activity diagram?
						</para>
						</question>
						<answer>
							<para>
Select a use case or class, then you can create an activity
diagram.
</para>
						</answer>
					</qandaentry>
				</qandadiv>
				<qandadiv>
					<title>State Diagrams</title>
					<qandaentry>
						<question>
							<para>
How do I create a state diagram?
</para>
						</question>
						<answer>
							<para>
Select a class, then you can create a state
diagram.
</para>
						</answer>
					</qandaentry>
				</qandadiv>
				<qandadiv>
					<title>Loading and Saving</title>
					<qandaentry>
						<question>
						<para>
Do Argo and Poseidon save .xmi files?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
Yes! They save the model information in an .xmi-file, the diagram
information in a .pgml-file and information about the project in a .argo
file. All of these are
then
zipped  to a .zargo-file. You can easily extract the .xmi from the
.zargo file
using any old generic ZIP application. Give it a try and look into the
magic of ARGO!
Be aware that double clicking will launch a ZIP utility, if one is
installed, and NOT ARGO.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
How do I import an .xmi into ARGO and what formats are known to be
supported?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
Because of the variety of .xmi formats being generated you will
encounter problems using other .xmis generated from other applications.
ARGOUML's native storage format is another implementation of XMI (Curt
Arnold believes that it has been hacked so it can also read the Unisys
variant).  He recommends that if you are comfortable with XSLT, you can
typically transform one variant of UML + XMI to another, plus
MetaIntegrations (http://www.metaintegrations.net) makes a version of
their Bridge product available to transform between XMI flavors.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
If i design a model by using ARGO UML how I can generate XMI format?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
Check out the .zargo file. Open it and Voila! It's tucked inside...
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
			<qandadiv>
				<title>Code Generation</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
Is the generated code meant to be able to compile?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
Yes, it is possible to compile your generated code from Poseidon. You
still need to implement method bodies, though, to get usable results.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
			<qandadiv>
				<title>Reverse Engineering</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
What reverse engineering functionality is available?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
Since version 0.9.3 Argo supports reverse engineering. The menu item to
import sources is in Files->Import.  There are various
weaknesses in the layout and parsing algorithms so if you track down a
bug please submit a bug report.  Also, you should not expect ARGO to
reverse engineer non-compiling code.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
Can I reverse engineer a .jar file with ARGO .9.3?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
Currently, ArgoUML as well as Poseidon cannot RE .jar Files. When we
talk about traditional jar files,
which are but a collection of class files (*.class). Reverse engineering
relies on Source
Files (*.java), which should be syntactically correct, i.e. they can be
compiled.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
			<qandadiv>
				<title>Roundtrip Engineering</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
						</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
			<qandadiv>
				<title>Grafics and Printing</title>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
What does GEF mean?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
GEF = Graph Editing Framework - the thing which is hidden in gef.jar and
is responsible for displaying the graphs and which gives you the the
ability to move things around. GEF used to be closely interwoven with
Argo, but is now more or less seperate as far as I know. The sources are
also available via www.tigris.org
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
What is PGML?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
PGML is the saving format for diagram information used in Argo and
Poseidon. Although this is outdated a little,
it shows why we chose PGML in the first place. In the future, PGML
will be replaced by an extended XMI format which will include graphical
representation.
PGML is shortcut for Precision Graphics Markup Language. In April 1998
Adobe
Systems proposed a new Standard for Vector Graphics to the World Wide
Web Consortium (W3C), which should faciliate the creation and usage of
image material in the World Wide Web. It will be replaced by SVG. We
will support SVG by generating it from the XMI in the future.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
What applications open PGML?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
PGML is a predecessor of SVG. It was droped by the W3C Consortium.
Currently
there are no other tools that we know of working on PGML. We will move
to SVG
soon. And THAT will be read by many tools.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
What does SVG stand for?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
A super cool vector graphics format (like MM Flash) that is totally open
and is gaining enormous ground in the graphics world. Find out more at
the www.W3C.org
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<para>
How can I print my diagrams?
</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<para>
Select a diagram, then go to File->Export Diagrams. You can generate
gif, postscript, eps or svg format.
</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandadiv>
		</qandaset>
	</chapter>
</book>
