<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "../docbook-setup/docbookx/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY cookbookmodules SYSTEM "cookbook_modules.xml">
<!ENTITY cookbooklogging SYSTEM "cookbook_logging.xml">
]>

<!-- THIS IS THE ARGO/UML DEVELOPER COOKBOOK 
     - PLEASE FEEL FREE TO ADD TO THE CONTENT AND INSERT YOUR 
     NAME IN THE AUTHOR GROUP.
     - IMAGES SHOULD BE LOCATED IN THE GENERAL IMAGES SECTION OF THE 
     DOCUMENTATION MODULE UNDER THE DIRECTORY COOKBOOK
     - PLEASE VERIFY THAT YOUR CHANGES COMPILE CORRECTLY BEFORE COMMITING THEM
-->
     
<book>
     <bookinfo>
         <date>2001-11-10
         </date>
         <title>Cookbook for Developers of ArgoUML</title>
         <subtitle>An introduction to ArgoUML Programming</subtitle>
         <authorgroup>
             <author>
                 <firstname>Markus</firstname>
                 <surname>Klink</surname>
             </author>
             <author>
                 <firstname>Linus</firstname>
                 <surname>Tolke</surname>
             </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <legalnotice>
             <para>
 Copyright (c) 1996-2002 The Regents of the University of California. All
 Rights Reserved. Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this
 software and its documentation without fee, and without a written
 agreement is hereby granted, provided that the above copyright notice
 and this paragraph appear in all copies.  This software program and
 documentation are copyrighted by The Regents of the University of
 California. The software program and documentation are supplied "AS
 IS", without any accompanying services from The Regents. The Regents
 does not warrant that the operation of the program will be
 uninterrupted or error-free. The end-user understands that the program
 was developed for research purposes and is advised not to rely
 exclusively on the program for any reason.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
 UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BE LIABLE TO ANY PARTY FOR DIRECT, INDIRECT,
 SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, INCLUDING LOST PROFITS,
 ARISING OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE AND ITS DOCUMENTATION, EVEN IF
 THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
 SUCH DAMAGE. THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIMS ANY
 WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
 MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. THE SOFTWARE
 PROVIDED HEREUNDER IS ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, AND THE UNIVERSITY OF
 CALIFORNIA HAS NO OBLIGATIONS TO PROVIDE MAINTENANCE, SUPPORT,
 UPDATES, ENHANCEMENTS, OR MODIFICATIONS.
             </para>
         </legalnotice>
     </bookinfo>
     <toc/>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <sect1 id="thanks">
      <title>Thanks</title>
      <para>
We, the authors would like to take the opportunity to thank everyone
involved in the creation of this documentation, and especially the
people behind setting up the DocBook environment. In particular thanks
go out to Alejandro Ramirez, Phillipe Vanpeperstraete and Andreas
Rueckert.  Thank you!
</para>
    </sect1>
  
    <sect1 id="project">
      <title>About the project</title>
      <para>
ArgoUML is an open source project, so it depends on
people that volunteer to work on it. Especially in the
area of development there is still so much to do!
This Cookbook is dedicated to everyone interested in taking part
in the ArgoUML project as such and
should help to transfer the knowledge from the old experts to them.
Please feel free to send more questions and/or answers to the 
<ulink url="mailto:dev@argouml.tigris.org">dev mailing list</ulink>!
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>How to contribute</title>
      <para>
You can help, there are big tasks and small tasks waiting for you.
</para>
      <para>
Here is a suggestion on how you could become
part of the ArgoUML Project.
This could be perceived as a ladder to climb but remember
that if so it is firstly a ladder of levels of commitment
and time spent by you.
You get no price for climbing higher, you just get more 
responsibility in the project and more work.
</para>
      <para>
	  <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Use the tool.</para>
	  </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Subscribe to the dev list.</para>
	      <para>
Follow the discussions and as soon as you see some issue discussed
where you know the answer or solution, jump right in!
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Apply for an Observer role.</para>
	      <para>
This shows that you are commited to the project and also
allows you to enter and comment on issues etc.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Familiarize yourself with the project and how we work.
</para>
	      <para>
Suggestion on how to go about this:
		<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Read through most of the User manual and install and run 
the latest version of ArgoUML.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Read the process part of the Developers Cookbook at
<xref linkend="processes"/>.
</para>
		    <para>
This will give you the idea of how the ArgoUML project
attempts to release with good quality and especially
how Issuezilla works.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>Get the Observer role granted.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
From this on you can report bugs yourself directly in Issuezilla.
</para>
		    <para>
You can also verify issues according to the
verification process (see <xref linkend="verify_resolved_fixed"/>).
</para>
		    <para>
This will help you understand the terminology used in the project
and also gives you an idea of the current quality of ArgoUML and
what needs to be done in the future.
</para>
		    <para>
This is also a very low-commitment level task that
could be completed in a couple of minutes
(depending on your choice of issue).
</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>Read the rest of the Developers Cookbook.</para>
		    <para>
There is a lot of stuff discussed in here that is interesting 
for your understanding of the project and the code.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>Check out the source from cvs and build.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Familiarize yourself with the code.</para>
	      <para>
For this a good knowledge of Java is more or less a prerequisite.
</para>
	      <para>
Suggestion on how to go about this:
		<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Take active part in the discussions on the dev-list.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Solve issues registered in Issuezilla.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Convince someone to commit your changes.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Repeat.
</para>
		    <para>
This can go on until you find that your main problem is the to get
someone to actually commit your changes, not because they are hard to
convince but because they don't have time to do commits to keep up with
your pace.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Apply for a Developer role.</para>
	      <para>
This allows you to do commits on your own and you can now increase
the pace in which you are working.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Focus your work in a specific area.</para>
	      <para>
Everybody has different interests and the best contribution is made
when someone is allowed to pursue his own interests.
Hopefully ArgoUML provides you with interesting challanges to
your taste.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Accept responsibility for a specific area.</para>
	      <para>
With this you are part of the core team developing ArgoUML.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>About this Cookbook</title>
      <para>
This document, the Cookbook for Developers of ArgoUML, is provided
with the hopes of being helpful for the developers of ArgoUML when
it comes to learning and understanding how ArgoUML work in order
to improve on its functions and features. 

It can also be of interest for persons that wish to analyse the
ArgoUML project for whatever purpose that may be.
</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>In this Cookbook, you will find...</title>
	<para>
Information on how you can compile ArgoUML.
</para>
	<para>
Information on how different features of ArgoUML are implemented.
</para>
	<para>
Information on how you should add modules and Plug-ins to ArgoUML.
</para>
	<para>
Information that you, as a developer of ArgoUML,
needs to know about how the project is organised and
how to contribute.
</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>In this Cookbook, you will not find...</title>
	<para>
You will not find information on how to install and use ArgoUML.
</para>
	<para>
You will not find information on what UML is and if or how you should
use it in your project.
</para>
	<para>
You will not find information on how to convince your project to use
ArgoUML as a modelling tool.
</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="mailing_lists">
      <title>Mailing Lists</title>
      <indexterm><primary>Mailing lists</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>Developers' Mailing List</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
All developers <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> subscribe to the mailinglist
for developers. Please find the details at: 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList">http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList</ulink>
</para>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>CVS</primary>
	<secondary>Mailing list</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Mailing list</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
It is also recommended to join the CVS and Issues mailing lists.
Both give you a good idea of what is going on.
Developers should also work with Issuezilla registering or fixing 
problems found by themselves and others.
     </para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>

     <chapter id="buildingandtools">
    <title>Building from source</title>
    <para>
If you are in a hurry:
<programlisting>
C:\Work>set CVSROOT=:pserver:guest@cvs.tigris.org:/cvs
C:\Work>cvs login   (use guest as password)
C:\Work>cvs checkout argouml_src
C:\Work>set JAVA_HOME=<replaceable>C:\Programs\jdkwhatever</replaceable>
C:\Work>cd argouml\src_new
C:\Work\argouml\src_new>build run
</programlisting>
A window from the newly compiled ArgoUML opens after a while!
</para>
    <para>
That was the compact version for Windows + JDK.
(Note: jdk cannot be installed in a directory that contains space in its 
name.)
</para>
    <para>
If you don't understand this or it doesn't work read the rest of 
the chapter that describes all the nitty details about why and
how.
</para>
     <sect1 id="starting">
     <title>Getting started</title>
      <para>
In order to develop with ArgoUML it is absolutely mandatory to get get
the CVS version of ArgoUML.
How this is done is described in 
<xref endterm="cvs_checkout_term" linkend="cvs_checkout"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
Notice that the CVS contents is not only a set of source files but
instead it is the complete development environment for
all work within the ArgoUML project.
</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>Which tools do I need to build ArgoUML?</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Building</primary>
	  <secondary>tools</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Tools</primary>
	  <secondary>needed for building</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
These are the tools not included in the cvs repository that
you need to work with ArgoUML.
</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
A computer with a free disk space for your work.
</para>
	    <para>
Linus' guess is that you need at least 200MB to build it all 
(javadocs, documentation, classes, packages, ...).
If you just build the classes and packages 40MB will do.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
CVS for getting the files
and committing source code updates.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
JDK, at least version 1.3 (includes the java compiler)
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>
Which tools are part of the ArgoUML development environment?
</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Tools</primary>
	  <secondary>used</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
These tools are provided by the development environment that you
get when you check out from CVS.
</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>ANT</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
ANT, the tool to manage compiling and packaging.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>ANTLR</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
ANTLR, for regenerating the built-in parser.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>JUnit</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
JUnit, for running the JUnit test cases.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>jdepend</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
JDepend, for examining the code.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
For building the documentation from docbook format, 
these tools are also provided with the development environment that
you get when you check out from CVS.
</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
saxon for building documentation from docbook format.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Docbook</primary>
	      <secondary>XSL stylesheets</secondary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
Docbook XSL stylesheets.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>fop</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
fop for generating pdf versions of the docbook format.
</para>
	    <para>
To build a pdf file with the pictures included you 
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>What libraries are needed and used by ArgoUML?</title>
	<para>
These libraries are provided in the development environment that
you get when you check out CVS.
They are checked by the java compiler when compiling, 
needed for running ArgoUML and therefore distributed with ArgoUML.
</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>NSUML</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
nsuml, the Novosoft UML library.
</para>
	    <para>
ArgoUML project doesn't include the developing of Java classes for 
the purpose of storing, saving and loading an UML Model.
That work is done by NSUML and is used by ArgoUML.
</para>
<!--
	    <para>
See <xref linkend="nsuml"/> for some reading tips on how to learn
the insides of NSUML.
</para>
-->
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>GEF</primary>
	    </indexterm>

	    <para>
GEF graph editing framework, available from 
<ulink url="http://gef.tigris.org">gef.tigris.org</ulink>.
</para>
	    <para>
It is also recommended that you check out GEF at the same time as you
check out ArgoUML because many things in Argo relate to GEF and it is
quite handy to have the source code available.
GEF is also residing at tigris so you can do a simple
<command>cvs <replaceable>-d :user@cvs.tigris.org:/cvs</replaceable> co gef</command>
(with the same checkout arguments you had when you checked out ArgoUML)
to get it.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
The ocl package to parse and run the Object Constraint Language things.
</para>
	    <para>
Details about the package are available from sourceforge
<ulink url="http://dresden-ocl.sourceforge.net/">OCL Compiler</ulink>.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>log4j</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
log4j, a library with infrastructure for logs.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
antlrall, the run-time part of the antlr tool.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

 </sect1>
    <sect1 id="cvs_checkout">
      <title id="cvs_checkout_term">Download from the CVS repository</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>CVS</primary>
	<secondary>checking out from</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Checking out from CVS</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
The CVS repository at Tigris is accessable using the pserver protocol.
The CVS root is <filename>/cvs</filename> at cvs.tigris.org.
You use your Tigris login and Tigris password.
</para>
      <para>
This means that you will set the <varname>CVSROOT</varname>-variable to
<parameter>:pserver:<replaceable>login</replaceable>@cvs.tigris.org:/cvs</parameter>
where <replaceable>login</replaceable> is you Tigris login.
This needs to be done for the first checkout.
After that the root will be remembered by the checked out copy.
</para>
      <para>
The next thing to do is to login. It is done using the command:
<command>cvs login</command>.
This only needs to be done once and then the account on your machine
remembers this.
</para>
      <para>
Then you do the actual checking out.
<command>cvs checkout <replaceable>modulename</replaceable></command>.
</para>
      <para>
The CVS module you need to check out to build ArgoUML is
<parameter>argouml_src</parameter>.
This will check out the directories
<filename class="directory">argouml/lib</filename>,
<filename class="directory">argouml/tools</filename>,
<filename class="directory">argouml/src</filename>,
<filename class="directory">argouml/src_new</filename>,
and
<filename class="directory">argouml/tests</filename>.
</para>
      <para>
If you want to build to documentation you check out the module
<parameter>argouml_doc</parameter>.
This will check out the directories
<filename class="directory">argouml/lib</filename>
<filename class="directory">argouml/tools</filename>
and
<filename class="directory">argouml/documentation</filename>.
</para>
      <para>
If you want to work with the web site you check out the directory
<parameter>argouml/www</parameter>.
</para>
      <para>
If you give the argument
<parameter>argouml</parameter> all of ArgoUML is checked out.
That is no problem except for the extra use of bandwidth and disk space
but if you have plenty of both, get it all, and eventually you will
see how everything is used for a purpose in the project.
</para>
      <para>
If you don't want to acquire a tigris login to do this you can use the
"guest" account with the password "guest".
Since the checked out copy remembers the login you used to do the
check out, if you do this, you will have to remember to delete this
copy and start over if you get a developer role in the project and
want to do commits directly.
</para>
    </sect1>
 <sect1 id="Build">
     <title id="Build_term">Build Process</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Building</primary>
	<secondary>ArgoUML</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>ANT</primary>
      </indexterm>
     <para>
The ArgoUML build process is driven by ANT, and it is highly recommend
that you stick to that.
There are people known to build from JBuilder or Netbeans, but always
make sure that your work compile with the plain vanilla build process.
     </para>
      <para>
Ant is a tool written in java developed for Apache that reads an xml-file
with rules telling what to compile to what result and what files to include
in what jar-file.
</para>
      <indexterm>
	<primary><filename>build.xml</filename></primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
The rule file is named <filename>build.xml</filename>.
There is one of those in every separately built directory
(<filename class="directory">src_new</filename>,
<filename class="directory">documentation</filename>, and
<filename class="directory">modules/<replaceable>whatever</replaceable></filename>).
</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>How ANT is run from the ArgoUML development environment</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>ANT</primary>
	  <secondary>how it is used</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
For your convenience the ant tool of the correct version is present in the
CVS repository of ArgoUML in the file 
<filename class="libraryfile">argouml/tools/ant-1.4.1/lib/ant.jar</filename>.
</para>
	<para>
Normally ant is started with the command
<command>../tools/ant-1.4.1/bin/ant <replaceable>arg</replaceable></command>
and in the modules
<command>
../../tools/ant-1.4.1/bin/ant <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
</command>.
On windows the command
<command>..\tools\ant-1.4.1\bin\ant <replaceable>arg</replaceable></command>
runs the program <filename>ant.bat</filename>.
</para>
	<para>
To keep you from having to write this and keeping track if you are
working with a module or not
there are two scripts (one for Unix and one for
Windows) that are called <filename>build.sh</filename> and
<filename>build.bat</filename> respectively present in most
of the directories that contain a <filename>build.xml</filename> file.
These two scripts runs the equivalence of the above paths.
</para>
	<para>
By setting JAVA_HOME to different values you can at different times
build with different versions of jdk and java.
</para>
	<para>
To use different versions of ANT,
you are responsible for installing your own version.
Also, you must execute
<command>/where/ever/you/placed/your/new/ant <replaceable>target</replaceable></command>
rather than
<command>build <replaceable>target</replaceable></command>.
</para>
	<sect3>
	  <title>Compiling for Unix</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Compiling</primary>
	    <secondary>Unix</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Unix</primary>
	    <secondary>compilation</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
Here is what you need to do in order to compile and run 
your checked out copy of ArgoUML under Unix.
</para>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para><command>JAVA_HOME=<replaceable>/where/you/have/installed/jdk</replaceable></command></para>
	      <para><command>export JAVA_HOME</command></para>
	      <para>
This is for sh-style shells like sh, ksh, zsh and bash. If you use
csh-style shells like csh and tcsh you will instead have to write
<command>setenv JAVA_HOME <replaceable>/where/you/have/installed/jdk</replaceable></command>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Change the current directory to the directory you are building
</para>
	      <para>
<command>cd <replaceable>/your/checked/out/copy/of/argouml/src_new</replaceable></command>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Start ant using <command>./build.sh</command></para>
	      <para>This gives you a list of targets with descriptions</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Compile and run Argouml using <command>./build.sh run</command>
</para>
	      <para>
You can do this over and over again when you have modified something
or want to compile and run again.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>Compiling for Windows</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Compiling</primary>
	    <secondary>Windows</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Windows</primary>
	    <secondary>Compilation</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
<command>set JAVA_HOME=<replaceable>/where/you/have/installed/jdk</replaceable></command>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Change the current directory to the directory you are building
</para>
	      <para>
<command>chdir <replaceable>\your\checked\out\copy\of\argouml\src_new</replaceable></command>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Start ant using <command>build</command></para>
	      <para>This gives you a list of targets with descriptions</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Compile and run Argouml using <command>build run</command>
</para>
	      <para>
You can do this over and over again when you have modified something
or want to compile and run again.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>

	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Compiling</primary>
	    <secondary>Cygwin</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Cygwin</primary>
	    <secondary>Compilation</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
If you do this from Cygwin you work just like for Unix.
</para>

	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>Customizing and configuring your build</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Compiling</primary>
	    <secondary>customized</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Compiling</primary>
	    <secondary>build.properties</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Compiling</primary>
	    <secondary>argouml.build.properties</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
It is possible to customize your compilation of ArgoUML.
</para>
	  <para>
If you issue the command
<command>build list-property-files</command>
you can see what files are searched for properties.
</para>
	  <para>
Don't change the
<filename class="libraryfile">argouml/src_new/default.properties</filename>
file (unless you are working with updating the development environment
itself).
Instead create one of the other files locally on you machine.
The properties in these files have precedence over the properties in
<filename class="libraryfile">argouml/src_new/default.properties</filename>.
</para>
	  <para>
Remember that if you do this, you have modified your development
environment.
To be sure that you will not break anything for
anyone else when checking in things 
developed using this modified environment, 
remove these files temporarily for the compiling and testing
you do just before you commit.
	  </para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>Building javadoc</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Javadoc</primary>
	    <secondary>building</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Building</primary>
	    <secondary>javadoc</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
By running ANT again using <command>build prepare-docs</command>
the javadoc documentation is generated and put into
<filename class="directory">argouml/build/javadocs</filename>.
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>How documentation is presented</title>
	<para>
This describes how the documentation arrives on the web site.
</para>
	<sect3 id="how_the_web_site_works">
	  <title>How the ArgoUML web site works</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Web Site</primary>
	    <secondary>maintaining</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
Tigris provides the ArgoUML site to be edited through CVS. Everything
that is checked in under <filename>argouml/www</filename>
becomes immediatly available at the url 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/">http://argouml.tigris.org/</ulink>
with some added decorations.
</para>
	  <para>
Example: The file <filename>argouml/www/project.html</filename> is
available at 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/project.html">http://argouml.tigris.org/project.html</ulink>.
</para>
	  <para>
This is the way the site is maintained and updated.
</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>The ArgoUML documentation</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Documentation</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Web Site</primary>
	    <secondary>documentation</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
For the ArgoUML project the same documenation shall be available in both
html, pdf and javahelp. To this end the documentation is written in
docbook xml and generated into two versions of html 
(one page per chapter and one page for the whole book),
pdf and javahelp.
</para>
	  <para>
We have tools that does the conversion from docbook xml to html and pdf.
The conversion is done whenever you need to look at the result or when 
you want to present the final result on the web site.
</para>
	  <para>
There is currently three different books generated in this way, 
each its own directory. They are cookbook (this document), 
manual and quick-guide. They are all generated and stored in the
exact same way except for the name of the directory that is one
of <filename class="directory">cookbook</filename>,
<filename class="directory">manual</filename> or 
<filename class="directory">quick-guide</filename>.
Below I will reference this directory using 
<filename class="directory"><replaceable>book</replaceable></filename>.
</para>
	  <para>
When a new version of the documentation is to be made available on the
web site the responsible document release person does the following:
</para>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
He checks out everything needed
and a copy of the <filename class="directory">argouml/www</filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
The module <parameter>argouml_docs</parameter> is there for this purpose.
</para>
	      <para>
If wanted, the CVS repository could be tagged and then the tag
can be checked out. This makes it possible to know exactly 
how a certain version of the documentation was generated.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
The documentation is generated using <command>build docs</command>.
</para>
	      <para>
This generates all three books and the result appears in 
<filename class="directory">argouml/build/documentation/defaulthtml/<replaceable>book</replaceable></filename>,
<filename class="directory">argouml/build/documentation/printablehtml/<replaceable>book</replaceable></filename>, and
<filename class="directory">argouml/build/documentation/pdf/<replaceable>book</replaceable></filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
This has been done several times before while preparing the release so
no problems are expected. If there are problems then the preparations
was not good enough and the process is best stopped right here.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
All the old files are removed from the checked out copy of 
<filename class="directory">argouml/www/documentation/defaulthtml/<replaceable>book</replaceable></filename>, 
<filename class="directory">argouml/www/documentation/printablehtml/<replaceable>book</replaceable></filename>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
New files are copied into the checked out copy of www
on top of the previous files there replacing them.
</para>
	      <para>
All the files are copied from
<filename class="directory">argouml/build/documentation/defaulthtml/<replaceable>book</replaceable></filename> to
<filename class="directory">argouml/www/documentation/defaulthtml/<replaceable>book</replaceable></filename>. 
The same for <filename class="directory">printablehtml</filename> and 
<filename class="directory">pdf</filename>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
No longer used files in 
<filename class="directory">argouml/www/documentation</filename>
are removed from CVS and new files are added.
</para>
	      <para><command>cvs -n update</command></para>
	      <para>Watch for "Missing" and "Unknown" files.</para>
	      <para>
The missing files are scheduled to be removed by:
<command>cvs remove <replaceable>each of the missing files</replaceable></command>
</para>
	      <para>
The "Unknown" files are scheduled to be added by:
<command>cvs add <replaceable>each of the added files</replaceable></command>
</para>
	      <para>
This removing of missing files and adding of unknown files may seem
backward but it is from the perspective of CVS.
The missing files are the ones that were present in the previous
version of the documentation and that does not have a replacement,
either because that chapter does not exist anymore or that the tool
generate filenames differently.
The Unknown files are files with filenames that for the same reason
appear from one version of the documentation to the next.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Commit the changes thus publishing it on the web site.
</para>
	      <para>
<command>cvs commit -m'New version of the documentation published'</command>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
The pdf book is uploaded to the download page.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>How developers work with documentation</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Documentation</primary>
	    <secondary>work with</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
Developers that work with the documentation or with the tools 
to generate the documentation (or anyone else interested in this)
can generate the documentation like described above and examine
the result in
<filename class="directory">argouml/build</filename>.
It is only the last part about checking in and upploading the result
under
<filename class="directory">argouml/www/documentation</filename>
that requires write access in the CVS and synchronisation with the
rest of the project.
</para>
	  <para>
In order to do this you need to check out the whole of the
<filename class="directory">argouml/documentation</filename> directory.
You also need the directory
<filename class="directory">argouml/lib</filename> and
<filename class="directory">argouml/tools</filename>
that contains the tools used: ANT, Fop, saxon, ...
</para>
	  <para>
The subdirectories of
<filename class="directory">argouml/documentation</filename>,
<filename class="directory">cookbook</filename>,
<filename class="directory">manual</filename>, and
<filename class="directory">quick-guide</filename>
each contain one of the four books.
The subdirectory
<filename class="directory">docbook-setup</filename>
contains two things. 
It contains the configuration files that control how the generation is done.
It contains the xsl rules for all the generation.
The subdirectory
<filename class="directory">images</filename>
contains all the required pictures for all the books.
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Troubleshooting the development build</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Troubleshooting</primary>
	  <secondary>development build</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<sect3>
	  <title>Compiling failed. Any suggestions?</title>
	  <para>
It might be that some other developer has made a misstake in checking
in things that contains error, or forgotten to check in some files
in a change.
Look at the last couple of hours on the
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/BrowseList?listName=dev">
developers mailing list</ulink>!
It is probably on fire.
</para>
	  <para>
Another reason for problems is an unclean local source tree.
This means that if you have updated different parts of your source 
tree at different times it might contains inconsistencies.
If you suspect this, first try fix it by doing
<command>build clean</command> and <command>cvs update -d</command>
before trying to build again.
If that doesn't work remove your checked out copy completely and 
get it all again through CVS.
</para>
	  <para>
Another reason might be that you have an 
<filename>build.properties</filename> or
<filename>argouml.build.properties</filename>
file that you have been working with earlier
and that is doing something. If in doubt, remove those files.
</para>
	  <para>
If nothing helps, ask the 
<ulink url="mailto:dev@argouml.tigris.org">developers mailing list</ulink>!
</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>Can't commit my changes?</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Troubleshooting</primary>
	    <secondary>commiting changes</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
You need to have a developer role in the ArgoUML project.
If you don't then you cannot do commit yourself.
Discuss what you have done and how best to test it on the
<ulink url="mailto:dev@argouml.tigris.org">developers mailing list</ulink>!
Eventually someone will commit it for you.
</para>
	  <para>
Furthermore the checkout of your copy need to be done with your
tigris id that has the Developer role.
If you for some reason have earlier checked out
a copy as guest and then made modifications, changed the CVSROOT
variable you still cannot commit changes done in the repository since the
checked out copy contains information on who checked out.
For this reason, it is best to apply for an Observer role in 
the project if you are going to work with the source at all.
The Observer role is probably granted within a couple of days
(we welcome everybody!) and then you can check out with your tigris id.
This means that when you eventually are granted a Developer role you
can continue working with the same checked out copy.
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>

 </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>The JUnit test cases</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>JUnit testing</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Unit testing of ArgoUML</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Testing ArgoUML</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
ArgoUML has a set of automatic test cases using JUnit-framework
for testing the insides of the code.
The purpose of these are to help in pin-pointing problems with
code changes already before even starting ArgoUML.
</para>
      <para>
The JUnit test cases are residing at two different places in the
source repository and run in two different ways.
They are never distributed with ArgoUML but merely a tool for
developers.
</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>New style JUnit test cases</title>
	<para>
By running the command
<command>build tests</command>
from <filename>src_new</filename>
these test cases are started, each in their own jvm.
</para>
	<para>
Each test case writes its result on the Ant log.
</para>
	<para>
The result is also generated into a set of files that can be found at
<filename>build/test/reports/junit/output/html/index.html</filename>.
</para>
	<para>
Testcases shall be located under
<filename>argouml/tests/org/argouml</filename>
and the filenames shall be like
<filename>Test<replaceable>*</replaceable>.java</filename>.
</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Old style JUnit test cases</title>
	<para>
This chapter describes the old way of doing JUnit test cases.
</para>
	<para>
The JUnit module is an ArgoUML module that is used to contain all 
Unit Test Cases.
The reason for it being a module is that the classes contained need
not be distributed with the ArgoUML distribution. 
They have their use in the hands of the developers of ArgoUML.
</para>
	<para>
The module is available from CVS under
<filename class="directory">modules/junit</filename>
and the used version of the JUnit framework is also available there
(under <filename class="directory">modules/junit/lib</filename>).
</para>
	<para>
This location will probably change in the future.
</para>
	<para>
The Java package structure under 
<filename class="directory">modules/junit/src</filename>
in the module is a complete copy of the ArgoUML Java package
structure.
Ideally every class
<classname>org.argouml.<replaceable>x.y</replaceable>.<replaceable>z</replaceable></classname>
stored in the file
<filename class="directory">src_new/org/argouml/<replaceable>x/y</replaceable>/<replaceable>z</replaceable>.java</filename>
should have a JUnit test case called
<classname>org.argouml.<replaceable>x.y</replaceable>.Test<replaceable>z</replaceable></classname>
stored in the file
<filename class="directory">modules/junit/src/org/argouml/<replaceable>x/y</replaceable>/Test<replaceable>z</replaceable>.java</filename>
containing all the Unit Test Cases for that class.
</para>

	<sect3 id="run_junit_testcases">
	  <title>How to run the old style test cases</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>JUnit testing</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
This is a simple description on how to run the JUnit Test Cases.
</para>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Check out all you need to build ArgoUML and the modules/junit
directory.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Build ArgoUML as a package in src_new as described in the
<xref endterm="Build_term" linkend="Build"></xref>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Change directory to
<filename class="directory">../modules/junit</filename>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Run ant with the argument run.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
ArgoUML starts up just with the splash screen and then the normal
window.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Observe that the Tools menu now is enabled (i.e. not greyed out).
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Under the Tools menu, select the item Test Panel....
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
The JUnit panel called Run Test Suite opens on top of ArgoUML.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Enter the word <classname>TestAll</classname> in the field 
"Enter the name of the Test class:" to run all tests.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Uncheck the "Reload classes every run" checkbox.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Press the "Run"-button and watch the "Progess"-bar turn all green
(hopefully).
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Verify that all the tests are Run and that there are 
no "Errors" and no "Failures".
</para>
	      <para>
If there are "Errors" or "Failures" they you can hopefully easily
pinpoint the problem.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	  <para>
If you only want to run one of your newly written test cases and not
all the test cases, give the class name of your test case instead of
"TestAll" like
<classname>org.argouml.<replaceable>x.y</replaceable>.Test<replaceable>z</replaceable></classname>.
</para>
	  <para>
This will probably change in the future simplifying it to the 
following even simpler description:
</para>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Check out all you need to build ArgoUML</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Build ArgoUML and run the JUnit test cases using
<command>build run-all-junit-tests</command>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Verify that all the tests are Run and that there are 
no "Errors" and no "Failures".
</para>
	      <para>
If there are "Errors" or "Failures" they you can hopefully easily
pinpoint the problem.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>How to write a test case</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Unit testing of ArgoUML</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Testing ArgoUML</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Testcases</primary>
	    <secondary>writing</secondary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
Now this will make all you java-enthusiasts go nuts!
We have both classnames and method names that need to have a special
syntax.
</para>
	  <para>
The name of the test case starts with "Test" (i.e. Capital T, then
small e, s and t). This is to help the TestAll class determine what is
a Test Case and what is not without loading them. 
If you write a test case that does not comply to this rule you still
can run the test case but it wont be run by TestAll.
This could prove useful sometimes but I (Linus) have yet to figure out
when.
</para>
	  <para>
The test case imports the JUnit framework: 
<blockquote>
	      <para>
import junit.framework.*;
</para>
	    </blockquote>
and it inherits <classname>TestCase</classname>.
</para>
	  <para>
Methods that are tests must have names that start with "test"
(i.e. all small t, e, s, t). This is a requirement of the JUnit
framework.
</para>
	  <para>
A lot of times it is useful just to run the compiler to verify that
the signatures are correct on the interfaces. Therefor Linus has
thought it is a good idea to add methods called
<methodname>compileTestStatics</methodname>,
<methodname>compileTestConstructors</methodname>, and
<methodname>compileTestMethods</methodname>
that was thought to include correct calls to all static methods,
all public constructors, and all other public methods that are not
otherwise tested.
These methods are never called.
They serve as a guarantee that the public interface of a class will
ever loose any of the functionality provided by its signature in an
uncontrolled way in just the same way as the test-methods serve as a
guarantee that no features will ever be lost.
</para>
	  <example>
	    <title>A complete example</title>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Testcases</primary>
	      <secondary>an example</secondary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
<programlisting>
package org.argouml.uml.ui;
import junit.framework.*;

public class TestUMLAction extends TestCase {
    public TestUMLAction(String name) {
	super(name);
    }

    // Testing all three constructors.
    public void testCreate1() {
	UMLAction to = new UMLAction(new String("hejsan"));
	assert("Disabled", to.shouldBeEnabled());
    }
    public void testCreate2() {
	UMLAction to = new UMLAction(new String("hejsan"), true);
	assert("Disabled", to.shouldBeEnabled());
    }
    public void testCreate3() {
	UMLAction to = new UMLAction(new String("hejsan"), true, UMLAction.NO_ICON);
	assert("Disabled", to.shouldBeEnabled());
    }
	

    // Functions never actually called. Provided in order to make
    // sure that the static interface has not changed.
    private void compileTestStatics() {
	boolean t1 = UMLAction.HAS_ICON;
	boolean t2 = UMLAction.NO_ICON;
	UMLAction.getShortcut(new String());
	UMLAction.getMnemonic(new String());
    }

    private void compileTestConstructors() {
	new UMLAction(new String());
	new UMLAction(new String(), true);
	new UMLAction(new String(), true, true);
    }

    private void compileTestMethods() {
	UMLAction to = new UMLAction(new String());
	to.markNeedsSave();
	to.updateEnabled(new Object());
	to.updateEnabled();
	to.shouldBeEnabled();
    }
}
</programlisting>
</para>
	  </example>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	  <title>The TestAll class</title>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Testing ArgoUML</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
The TestAll class goes through all directories under 
<filename class="directory">modules/junit/build/classes</filename>
and finds all class-files beginning with "Test".
They are all added to the test suite.
</para>
	  <para>
This means that the risk of forgetting to add a test case to the suite
is reduced and there is no need to maintain such a suite.
</para>
	  <para>
On the other hand this only works in the build environment.
If the jar-file is used somewhere else or the ArgoUML is started in
some other place with respect to
<filename class="directory">modules/junit/build/classes</filename>
then this will fail and TestAll will probably not detect any test
cases at all.
</para>
	  <para>
I hope and think that this will never be a problem since most of the
times the test cases are run by a person with all the source available
in just this way.
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="release_process">
      <title>Making a release</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Making a release</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
To simplify for the person that is actually doing the release work
and to make sure that everything is done in the exact same way 
every time and nothing is forgotten,
this list of what to do when releasing is maintained.
</para>
      <para>
It is provided with the hopes of being helpful.
If you, the release responsible, finds it unhelpful, please remove it!
</para>

      <para>
What needs to be done when one actually does a release:
</para>

      <para>
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Modify <filename>default.properties</filename> if necessary!</para>
	    <para>
The property to change is 
<methodname>argo.core.version</methodname>
where you will set the version number.
</para>
	    <para>
For release 0.9.8 it should look like this:
<programlisting>
#
# Argo version
#
argo.core.version=0.9.8
</programlisting>
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Tag the whole CVS repository with the freeze tag!</para>
	    <para>
Normally this tag is "VERSION_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable>_F",
e.g. VERSION_0_9_7_F.
The according command line CVS command is 
<command>cvs rtag VERSION_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable>_F argouml</command>.
In case you make a mistake doing that (you shouldn't really), 
you need to remove the tag you mistakenly put there and start over.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Make sure you have a clean copy of the source!</para>
	    <para>
This is done by checking out from the tag using the command
<command>cvs co -r VERSION_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable>_F argouml_modules</command>
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Build the release with <command>build dist-release</command>!</para>
	    <para>
The output should be the files
ArgoUML-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>-libs.tar.gz,
ArgoUML-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>-libs.zip,
ArgoUML-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>-src.tar.gz,
ArgoUML-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>-src.zip,
ArgoUML-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>.tar.gz, and
ArgoUML-<replaceable>VERSION</replaceable>.zip
in the top-level argouml directory.

</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Test the release!</para>
	    <para>
Either the tar or zip-file is tested by unpacking, starting and then
running through the test cases.
Currently there isn't any defined test cases.
</para>
	    <para>
All JUnit test cases are run by 
cd:ing to the <filename class="directory">modules/junit</filename> source directory,
running <command>build run</command>,
invoking JUnit tests from the Tools menu,
specifying the Test Case TestAll,
and running.
No problems shall be found.
</para>
	    <para>
If the tests did not pass See <xref linkend="release_process_test_failed"/>.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Tag the whole repository with the release tag!</para>
	    <para>
This tag is "VERSION_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable>",
e.g. VERSION_0_9_7.
The according command line CVS command is 
<command>cvs tag VERSION_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable></command>
when your are standing in the
<filename class="directory">argouml</filename>-directory.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Open the repository for commits towards the next version.
</para>
	    <para>
This is done by setting the <methodname>argo.core.version</methodname>
in <filename>default.properties</filename> to 
<replaceable>Number of next release</replaceable>
and commiting.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Upload the files onto the tigris website!</para>
	    <para>
Only a project owner can do that.
Please write the descriptions of the files like this:
<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>libraries</para>
		  <para>
libraries needed to compile
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>sources</para>
		  <para>
source code without libraries
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>complete set</para>
		  <para>
binary distribution, including all libraries
</para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Contact Jason Robbins to make the new Webstart version available!
</para>
	    <para>
Jason Robbins takes care of the signing and publishing of the
Webstart version.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Go through Issuezilla and check things.
</para>
	    <para>
Things to check are:
</para>
	    <orderedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
That there is a Version created in issuezilla for the newly created release.
</para>
		<para>
The purpose of this is to make it possible for everyone 
to report bugs on the new release.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
Make sure that the upcoming releases have 
target milestones created for them.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
Change the target milestones of all the non yet resolved issues to ---.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Other stuff.</para>
		<para>
This can also be a good time to change all 
RESOLVED/REMIND and RESOLVED/LATER.
Seach for them and Reopen them.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </orderedlist>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Make announcements!</para>
	    <para>
The announcement shall include a list of what has changed.
</para>
	    <para>
Write to the dev, users and announce lists.
Announcer should make sure that he/she is already subscribed to all lists.
</para>
	    <para>
Freshmeat: currently Thierry Lach does the freshmeat announcements
which require a login so just inform him.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
      <sect2 id="release_process_test_failed">
	<title>The release did not work</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Troubleshooting</primary>
	  <secondary>during the release work</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
This shouldn't happen! This really shouldn't happen!
</para>
	<para>
The reason that this has happened is that one of the developers 
has made a misstake.
You now must decide a way forward.
</para>
	<sect3 id="release_work_fix_problem_yourself">
	  <title>Fix the problem yourself.</title>
	  <para>
If the problem is obvious to you and you can fix it quickly, do so.
This is done by doing the following:
<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Make the release tag into a branch</para>
		<para>
<command>cvs rtag -b -r VERSION_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable>_F BRANCH_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable></command>
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Update you checked out copy to be on that branch</para>
		<para>
<command>cvs update -r BRANCH_<replaceable>X_Y_Z</replaceable></command>
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Fix the problem in your checked out copy</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Commit the problem in the branch</para>
		<para>
<command>cvs commit -m'Fix of problem blabla'</command>
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Continue the build process</para>
		<para>
This is done by restarting the <command>build dist-release</command>-command
and from that point on working in the branch instead of at the tag.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
Explain to the culprit what mistakes he has made and how to fix it.
</para>
		<para>
It is now his responsibility to make sure that the problem will not
appear in the next version.
He can do this either by merging in your fix or by fixing the problem
in some other way.
</para>
		<para>
At this point an in-detail description of how poor programming skills
the culprit has and how ugly his mother is, is probably in place but
please keep it constructive!
Remember, you might be misstaken when you guess who the responsible is.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>
Delay the release waiting for someone to fix the problem.
</title>
	  <para>
Create the branch as described in 
<xref linkend="release_work_fix_problem_yourself"/>.
Then tell the culprit and everyone on the developer list
what the problem is and that it is to be fixed in the
release branch a.s.a.p.
</para>
	  <para>
Monitor the changes made to the branch to verify that
noone commits anything else but the solutions to the
problems.
</para>
	  <para>
When you get notified that it is completed, 
update your checked out copy and continue the release work.
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>


</sect1>

</chapter>

  <chapter id="requirements">
    <chapterinfo>
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Linus</firstname>
	  <surname>Tolke</surname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
    </chapterinfo>
    <title>ArgoUML requirements</title>

    <para>
This chapter contains a description on how ArgoUML should work
and behave for the users.
</para>

    <para>
These things might not be implemented yet and the solutions
might not even be clear but it is a definition of the goal.
</para>
    <para>
The fact that it is not implemented or doesn't work as stated here
should be registered as a bug 
in the bug registering tool.
</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements for Look and feel</title>
      <para>
This describes how the ArgoUML look and feel shall behave.
</para>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
When multiple visual components are showing the same model element
they shall be updated in a consistent manner throught the application.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
As soon as the model element changes then all views shall update.
For text fields, this can be at every key stroke.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
There shall be no indication of an exception on the screen or in the
log if it has occured merely because of a user mistyping or not being
aware of UML syntax.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
All text fields shall have context sensitive help.
</para>
	    <para>
As follows:
<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
A tooltip that explains the data and format expected by the
particular field.
</para>
		  <para>
This can be omitted when there is a header stating the data of
the field and the format is obvious.
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Pressing F1 or choosing help from the menu shall display a popup
window explaining for data and format required by the current input
field. 
Input focus shall be left on the field during any user
interaction with the popup (dragging, scrolling or closing).
</para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
</para>

	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
 
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements for UML</title>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
ArgoUML shall be a correct implementation of the UML 1.3 model.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
ArgoUML shall implement everything in the UML 1.3 model.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements on java and jvm</title>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Choice of JRE</para>
	    <para>
It shall be possible to run ArgoUML with any Java2 compliant JRE.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Download and start</para>
	    <para>
It shall be possible to install ArgoUML locally on the machine
and use without Internet connection.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Console output</para>
	    <para>
Logging or tracing information shall not be written to the console
or to any file unless explicitly turned on by the user.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements set up for the benefit of the development of ArgoUML</title>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Logging</para>
	    <para>
The code shall contain entries logging important information
for the purpose of helping Developers of ArgoUML in finding problems
in ArgoUML itself.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>


<chapter id="components">
    <title>ArgoUML Design, The Big Picture</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ArgoUML</primary>
      <secondary>Design</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
Currently this is more of a base for discussion and
ambition but hopefully this will mature and 
prove useful.
</para>
    <para>
The code within ArgoUML is separated in components 
that each have a responsibility.
</para>
    <para>
<xref linkend="inside_components"></xref>
explains each component in details.
This chapter just gives an overall picture.
</para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>layer</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
The components are organized in layers.
The purpose of the layers is to keep a clear view
of what components provide services to others
and to allow us to know how much is involved
when testing each component.
</para>
    <para>
TODO: Insert UML diagram describing the relation between components and layers.
</para>
    <para>
This chapter contains 
a list of all components and what layer they are in
and the definition of the responsibility of each component.
</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Definition of component</title>
      <para>
All ArgoUML code is organized in components.
</para>
      <para>
Each component has:
<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>A name</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>A single directory/java package where it resides</para>
	    <para>
Subparts of the component can reside in subdirectories of this directory.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</para>
      <para>
Each component has a single Facade object that is used by
all other components when using this component.
The Facade object is called
<classname><replaceable>ComponentName</replaceable>Facade</classname>
and is located in the component package.
</para>
      <para>
Each component can also have one or several plug-in interfaces.
That is Facade objects where modules or plug-ins can connect themselves
to modify or augment the behavior of that component.
</para>
      <para>
The plug-in interfaces are also all located in the component package
and called
<classname><replaceable>ComponentName</replaceable>Plugin<replaceable>Plug-inType</replaceable></classname>.
Example: 
<classname>ModelPluginDiagram</classname>, 
<classname>ModelPluginType</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
If the component uses a callback-technique
the callback is always made to an interface.
The interface is also in component package and it is called
<classname><replaceable>ComponentName</replaceable><replaceable>Plug-inType</replaceable>Interface</classname>.
Example:
<classname>ModelDiagramInterface</classname>,
<classname>ModelTypeInterface</classname>.
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Definition of layer</title>

      <para>
Layers are used to organize and 
clairify the relationships between the different components
within ArgoUML.
</para>

      <para>
ArgoUML is built from the bottom and up.
Components on a higher level are relying on components
on a lower level and never the other way around.
A component cannot even rely on a component in the same layer.
</para>

      <para>
This means that when testing a component,
it can always be tested with just that component and
components on lower levels.
</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="layer0">
      <title>Layer 0 - Description of components</title>
      <para>
Layer 0 contains some infrastructure components that
just are there for every other layer to use.
</para>
      <para>
They are all insignificant enough not to be mentioned when
listing dependencies.
</para>
      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Logging</para>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Logging</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
Calls can be spread all over that would go through some rule set
and then end up on file, on the output or not at all.
</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Internationalization</para>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Internationalization</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>I18n</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
This is the set of files that is a repository of localized strings.
Every other module uses these strings in all communcations with
the user.
</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>JRE with utils</para>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>JRE</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
Every other component can use the classes available with the JRE.
</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    <para>
TODO: Insert UML diagram listing all layer 0 components.
</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="layer1">
      <title>Layer 1 - Description of components</title>
      <para>
Layer 1 is the lowest layer.
The components in this layer does not rely on any other part
(except layer 0)
of ArgoUML to do their work.
They can all be tested in full individually 
i.e. independant of any other component.
</para>
      <para>
<itemizedlist>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>The Model</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Model</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
The Model contains a modifyable view of the UML model
and the diagrams.
</para>
	    <para>
The Model presents several different views
and access methods for the information.
Among other things, the information can be saved,
loaded, examined, and observed.
</para>
	    <para>
The Model is described in detail in 
<xref linkend="model"></xref>.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>To do items</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>To do items</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the To do items. They can be created, deleted and saved.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>The GUI Framework</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>GUI Framework</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the framework with menus, tabs, and panes
available for the other
components to fill with actions and contents.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Help system</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Help system</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
Not yet implemented.
</para>
	    <para>
This is the component that the other components can call
to present some help for the user.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
</para>
    <para>
TODO: Insert UML diagram listing all layer 1 components with relations
to layer 0 components.
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="layer2">
      <title>Layer 2 - Description of components</title>
      <para>
These components rely on components of layer 1 in order to their
work.
</para>

      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Diagrams</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Diagrams</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the diagram view of the model.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Property panels</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Property panels</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the prop panel view of the model.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Navigator pane</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Navigator pane</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the navigator pane view of the model.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Module loader</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Module loader</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Pluggable interface</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the load mechanism for loading all Layer 3 and 
other modules into ArgoUML.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</para>
    <para>
TODO: Insert UML diagram listing all layer 2 components with relations
to layer 0 and 1 components.
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="layer3">
      <title>Layer 3 - Description of components</title>
      <para>
These components are primarily connected through the 
pluggable interfaces meaning that they can be
individually disabled using the module loader.
</para>

      <para>
	<itemizedlist>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Code generation, Reverse engineering - Java</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Code generation</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Reverse engineering</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Java</primary>
	      <secondary>reverse engineering</secondary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the ArgoUML connection to the java language.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Code generation, Reverse engineering - Other languages</para>
	    <para>
Languages are plugged into 
the notation,
the import, 
and code generation.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Critics and checklists</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>Critics</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>checklists</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the critics.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>OCL</para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>OCL</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <para>
This is the editing of the OCL strings.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
</para>
    <para>
TODO: Insert UML diagram listing all layer 3 components with relations
to layer 0, 1 or 2 components.
</para>
    </sect1>

<!-- Has to be rewritten to fit the new concepts.
(If it at all will fit, I am not sure. Linus December 2002.)
    <sect1>
      <title>ArgoUML Initialization</title>
      <sect2>
	<title>Which sources are involved?</title>
	<para>
Relative to the directory org/argouml, they are mainly:
</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
application/Main.java,
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
kernel/Project.java + xml/argo/ArgoParser.java,
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
ui/{ProjectBrowser.java,*Pane.java},
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
cognitive/{Designer.java,ui/ToDoPane.java}.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>What is loaded/initialized?</title>
	<para>
It all begins in org.argouml.application.Main: set up
main application frame (org.argouml.ui.ProjectBrowser), the
project (org.argouml.kernel.Project), numerous classes, and
finally as a background thread: cognitive support
(org.argouml.cognitive.Designer) and some more classes.
</para>
	<para>
The ProjectBrowser initializes the menu, toolbar, status bar
and the four main areas:
navigation pane (org.argouml.ui.NavigatorPane),
editor pane (org.argouml.ui.MultiEditorPane),
to do pane (org.argouml.cognitive.ui.ToDoPane), and
details pane (org.argouml.ui.DetailsPane). Then, the actual
project is set to either a read from file project
(see ArgoParser.SINGLETON.readProject(URL) and
ArgoParser.SINGLETON.getProject() in org.argouml.xml.argo.ArgoParser)
or a newly generated project (see Project.makeEmptyProject()).
</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
-->
<!--
Has to be rewritten.
    <sect1>
      <title>Which Objects live during a typical session?</title>
      <para>
(Project, Designer, Globals, NavPane, ToDoPane, ...)
</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>What is their task?</title>
      <para>
(visual component, model, controller, ...)
</para>
    </sect1>
-->

<!--
    <sect1 id="bigger_components">
    <title>The bigger picture, ArgoUML and supporting libraries</title>
<indexterm><primary>Libraries</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Components</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata format="GIF" fileref="images/cookbook/big.gif"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Well, ArgoUML is obviously the main thing.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>GEF stands for <emphasis>Graph Editing Framework</emphasis>. It is the package which controls most of the graphical aspects of ArgoUML.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>NSUML stands for <emphasis>Novosoft UML</emphasis>. This library gives ArgoUML all the components which are required to deal with UML objects and their relationships with each other. Normally you can recognize everything out of the NSUML packages very easily because the classes start with a capital M.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
-->

<!-- Move to chapter 5.
    <sect1 id="nsuml">
      <title>NS-UML</title>
      <sect2>
	<title>Tip for understanding NS-UML (from Jeremy Bennett)</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>NSUML</primary>
	  <secondary>understanding</secondary>
	</indexterm>
      <para>
I found that building a javadoc for the NSUML source was quite helpful.
There are some comments in key places, and it allows you to see what
operations are available.
</para>
      <para>
Its not part of their standard distribution, so you have to generate
it yourself. Jeremy Bennet has written the following script to do it:
</para>
      <para>
makedoc.sh:
<programlisting>
#!/bin/sh

# A script to drive Javadoc for all this

###############################################################################
# The source trees for ordinary source and generated source and where we put it
# all.
NSUML_HOME=$HOME/nsuml0_4_19/nsuml
SRCDIR=${NSUML_HOME}/src
GENDIR=${NSUML_HOME}/gen
DESTDIR=${NSUML_HOME}/docs/javadocs

# Run the javadoc command
javadoc -d $DESTDIR -sourcepath $GENDIR:$SRCDIR @${NSUML_HOME}/package_list
</programlisting>
Where package_list is:
<programlisting>
ru.novosoft.uml
ru.novosoft.uml.behavior.activity_graphs
ru.novosoft.uml.behavior.collaborations
ru.novosoft.uml.behavior.common_behavior
ru.novosoft.uml.behavior.state_machines
ru.novosoft.uml.behavior.use_cases
ru.novosoft.uml.foundation.core
ru.novosoft.uml.foundation.data_types
ru.novosoft.uml.foundation.extension_mechanisms
ru.novosoft.uml.model_management
ru.novosoft.uml.undo
ru.novosoft.uml.xmi
</programlisting>
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Tip for understanding NS-UML (from Ryan Ismert)</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>NSUML</primary>
	  <secondary>understanding</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
The file docs/guide/NS_Uml_Api.html that comes in the NSUML source is
very helpful.
</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
-->

<!-- This is taken care of.
<sect1 id="small">
<title>The smaller components, inside ArgoUML</title>
<para>
ArgoUML itself breaks down into several components. The graphic does not reflect the true package names, neither the true dependencies of the packages.
<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata format="GIF" fileref="images/cookbook/small.gif"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>User Interface</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Diagrams (see <xref linkend="diagrams"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>GEF</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Model</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Saving/Loading</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Notation (see <xref linkend="notation"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Code Generation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Reverse Engineering (see <xref linkend="java"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ocl</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Help System (see <xref linkend="help"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Internationalization (see <xref linkend="internationalization"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Critics and other cognitive tools (see <xref linkend="critics"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Plugin-Module API (see <xref linkend="plugins"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Logging (see <xref linkend="logging"/>)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
-->

<!-- This will be totally different.
    <sect1>
      <title>Collaboration table between components</title>
      <para>
Here is a table that lists all components within ArgoUML against each other
so that you easily can find where that specific collaboration is described
(if at all) in this cookbook.
-->
<!--
For the document maintainer:
Please stick to the component names as they are written 
in the entry tags in the header row for links within this document.
They all start with comp-.
Every component has a section describing it at componentname.
Every component has a purpose at componentname-purpose.
Every interface has a description at componentname-to-componentname
(origin-to-destination). Example comp-critics-to-comp-model.
-->
<!--
</para>
      <table>
	<title>Collaboration table</title>
	<tgroup cols="12">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry id="comp-ui">User Interface</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-diagrams">Diagram</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-gef">GEF</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-model">Model</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-saveload">Saving and Loading</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-notation">Notation</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-codegenreveng">Code Generation and Reverse Engineering</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-ocl">OCL-constraints</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-critics">Cognitive</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-help">Help system</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-internationalization">I18n</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-logging">Logging</entry>
	      <entry id="comp-plugins">Plug in and Module API</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>User Interface</entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Diagram</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>GEF</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Model</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-model-to-comp-logging"/></entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Saving and Loading</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Notation</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-notation-to-comp-codegenreveng"/></entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Code Generation and Reverse Engineering</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>OCL-constraints</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Cognitive</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-critics-to-comp-diagrams"/></entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-critics-to-comp-model"/></entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-critics-to-comp-saveload"/></entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>No</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-critics-to-comp-help"/></entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-critics-to-comp-internationalization"/></entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-critics-to-comp-logging"/></entry>
	      <entry><xref linkend="comp-critics-to-comp-plugins"/></entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Help system</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Internationalization</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Logging</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Plug in and Module API</entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry>       </entry>
	      <entry> - </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
-->
<!--

Empty chapter that would be written for every component.

In this template XXX need to be replaced by the generic name for the
component, XXDESCXX, some beautiful version of the name and YYY with 
something else.

    <sect1 id="XXX">
      <title>XXDESCXX</title>
      <para id="comp-XXX-purpose">
Purpose - to provide YYY
</para>
      <para>
This module contains the following main class types:
</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
YYY
</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <sect2>
	<title>Collaborations for XXDESCXX</title>
	<para>
YYY
</para>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-diagrams">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Diagrams</title>
	  <para>
YYY
</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-model">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses the Model</title>
	  <para>
YYY
</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-saveload">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Saving/Loading</title>
	  <para>Not at all!</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-notation">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Notation</title>
	  <para>Not at all!</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-codegenreveng">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Code Generation and Reverse Engineering</title>
	  <para>Not at all!</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-critics">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses the Cognitive stuff</title>
	  <para>Not at all!</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-help">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Help System</title>
	  <para>
YYY
</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-internationalization">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Internationalization</title>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-plugins">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Plugin-Module API</title>
	  <para>
Currently not!
</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3 id="comp-XXX-to-comp-logging">
	  <title>XXDESCXX uses Logging</title>
	  <para>
YYY
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Main classes</title>
	<para>
XXDESCXX are currently located in:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
YYY
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="howdoi_YYY">
	<title>How do I YYY...?</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>...YYY?</para>
	    <para>
YYY
</para>
	    </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>




-->

</chapter>


<chapter id="inside_components">
<title>Inside the components</title>
    <warning>
      <para>
This chapter is currently under rework with new component organization.
</para>
    </warning>
<para>...</para>

    <sect1 id="model">
      <title>Model</title>
      <para id="comp-model-purpose">
Purpose - to provide the data structures that keeps track of the model
and the diagrams. 
This comes with a complete set of methods to modify the model
and register interest in changes to the model.
</para>
      <para>
The Model is located in <classname>org.argouml.model</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Model is a Layer 1 component. See <xref linkend="layer1"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
This is implemented using NSUML to implement the UML model.
</para>
      <para>
ArgoUML uses several factories and helperclasses to manipulate the NSUML
model. 
The NSUML model itself does not define enough 'business' logic
to be directly used and the factories and helperclasses provide a
centralized place for accessing this 'business' logic.
Per section of chapter 2 of the UML 1.3 specification there is one factory
and one helper. They are placed in their own package. The package name
convention is:
<classname>org.argouml.model.uml.SECTIONNAME</classname> 
where sectionname is one of the following:
<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>foundation</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>foundation.core</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>foundation.extensionmechanisms</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>foundation.datatypes</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>behavioralelements</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>behavioralelements.commonbehaviour</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>behavioralelements.statemachines</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>behavioralelements.usecases</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>behavioralelements.collaborations</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>behavioralelements.activitygraphs</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>modelmanagement</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</para>
      <para>
Each package has at least a helper and a factory in it. 
The factories contain all methods that deal with 
creating and building modelelements.
The helpers contain all utility methods needed to manipulate
the modelelements.
</para>
      <para>
Both helpers and factories are singletons. 
The static method to access them is
<methodname>getFactory</methodname> for the factory
and <methodname>getHelper</methodname> for the helper.
</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>Factories</title>
	<para>
The factories contain at least for each modelelement a create method.
Example: <methodname>createClass</methodname>
resides in <classname>CoreFactory</classname> in the package
<classname>org.argouml.model.uml.foundation.core</classname>.
Besides that, there are several buildmethods to build classes.
The build methods have a signature like
<methodsynopsis>
	    <modifier>public</modifier>
	    <type><replaceable>MODELELEMENT</replaceable></type>
	    <methodname>build<replaceable>MODELELEMENTNAME</replaceable></methodname>
	    <methodparam>
	      <parameter><replaceable>params</replaceable></parameter>
	    </methodparam>
	  </methodsynopsis>.
</para>
	<para>
Each build method verifies the wellformednessrules
as defined in the UML spec 1.3. 
The reason for this is that NS-UML does not enforce 
the wellformedness rules even though non-wellformed UML can lead to
non-wellformed XMI which leads to saving/loading issues and 
all kinds of illegal states of argouml.
</para>
	<para>
If you want to create an element you shall use the create methods
in the factories.
You are strongly advised to use a build method or, if there is
none that suits your needs, to build one thereby reusing the allready
existing build methods and utility methods in the helpers. 
One reason for this is that the eventlisteners for
the newly create modelelement are setup correctly.
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Helpers</title>
	<para>
The helpers contain all utility methods for manipulating modelelements. 
For example, they contain methods to get all modelelements 
of a certain class out of the model 
(see <methodname>getAllModelelementsOfKind</methodname> in 
<classname>ModelmanagementHelper</classname>).
</para>
	<para>
To find a utility method you need to know where it is.
As a rule of thumb, a utility method for some modelelement 
is defined in the helper that corresponds with the section
in the UML specification.
For example, all utility methods for manipulating classes 
are defined in <classname>CoreHelper</classname>.
</para>
	<para>
There are a few exceptions to this rule, mainly if 
the utility method deals with two modelelements 
that correspond to different sections in the UML
specification.
Then you have to look in both corresponding helpers and you
will probably find what you are searching for.
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Collaborations for Model</title>
	<para>
The Model does not use much of the other parts of ArgoUML.
It is provided for use of others.
</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="howdoi_model">
	<title>How do I...?</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>...create a new create method?</para>
	    <para>
Create it in the correct factory.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>...create a new utility method?</para>
	    <para>
Create it in the correct helper.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>


<sect1 id="critics">
      <title>Critics and other cognitive tools</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Critics</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Check lists</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Wizards</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para id="comp-critics-purpose">
Purpose - to provide cognitive help for the User.
This help is based on the current model that the User works with.
</para>
      <para>
The Critics are located in <classname>org.argouml.cognitive</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Critics is a Layer 3 component. See <xref linkend="layer3"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
The Critics component depend on the Model that it works against to take
all decisions
and the To Do Items used to present the information.
</para>
      <para>
This component contains the following main class types:
</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Critics provide help to find artifacts in
the model that do not obey simple design "rules" or 
"best practises".
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Checklists provide help for the user to suggest and
keep track of considerations that the user should make
for each design element.
Checklists are currently (0.9.5 and 0.9.6) turned off.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
ToDoItems provide a way for the Critics to communicate
its knowledge to the User and let the User start Wizards.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Wizards are step by step instructions that fixes problems
found by the Critics.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect2>
	<title>Main classes</title>
<para>Here is an illustration of the main classes implementing critics</para>
<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata format="GIF" fileref="images/cookbook/critics.gif"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
<para>Critics are currently located in:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>org.argouml.cognitive.critics</para>
	    <para>
These are basic critics, which are very general in nature. For example
ArgoUML keeps nagging when Modelelements overlap, which makes the
Diagram hard to read.
</para>
	    <para>
This package also contain the base classes for the handling.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>org.argouml.uml.cognitive.critics</para>
	    <para>
These are Critics which are directly related to UML issues (well, more
or less). For example, it will nag when a class has two many
operations, because that makes it hard to maintain the particular
class.
</para>
	    <para>
This package also contains Wizards used by these Critiques.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>org.argouml.pattern.cognitive.critics</para>
<para>These are critics related to patterns. Currently they deal only with the Singleton pattern</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>org.argouml.language.java.cognitive.critics</para>
<para>These are critics which deal with java specific issues. Currently this is only a warning agains modelling multiple inheritance.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
      <para>
Base classes for Wizards is <classname>org.argouml.kernel.Wizard</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
Checklists are located in the package org.argouml.cognitive.checklist.
</para>
      <para>
Helper classes for To Do Items, To Do Pane, Wizards and the Knowledge Types
is located in the package org.argouml.cognitive.ui.
</para>
      </sect2>

<sect2 id="howdoi_critics">
<title>How do I ...?</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>...create a new critique?</para>
	      <para>
Currently the only way to add a new critique is to write a class that
implements it so that is described here.
There have however been ideas on a possibility to build critics in
some other way in the future, as a set of rules instead of java code.
</para>
	      <para>
Create a new critic class, of the form 
<classname>Cr<replaceable>XxxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable></classname>, 
extending <classname>CrUML</classname>.
Typically your new class will go in the package
<classname>org.argouml.uml.cognitive.critics</classname>,
but it could go in one of the other
<classname>cognitive.critics</classname> packages.
</para>
	      <para>
Write a constructor, which takes no argouments and calls the following
methods of <classname>CrUML</classname>:
</para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
<command>setResource("Cr<replaceable>XxxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable>");</command>
to set up the locale specific text for 
the critic headline (the one liner that appears in the to-do pane)
and
the critic description (the detailed explanation that appears in 
the to-do tab of the details pane).
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
<command>addSupportedDecision(CrUML.dec<replaceable>AAAA</replaceable>);</command>
where <replaceable>AAAA</replaceable> is the design issue category
this critic falls into
(examples include STORAGE, PATTERN METHODS).
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
<command>setPriority(ToDoItem.<replaceable>BBB</replaceable>_PRIORITY);</command>
where <replaceable>BBB</replaceable> is one of
<constant>LOW</constant>, <constant>MEDIUM</constant> or 
<constant>HIGH</constant>, to set the priority for the critic 
in the to-do pane.
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
<command>addTrigger("<replaceable>UML MetaClass</replaceable>");</command>
where <replaceable>UML MetaClass</replaceable> is a UML MetaClass,
with initial lower capital, e.g. "associationEnd".
The intention is that critics should only trigger for elements (or
children) of particular UML metaclasses.
I (Jeremy Bennett february 2002) believe this code is not yet working
so you can probably leave it out.
You can have multiple calls to this method for different metaclasses.
</para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	      <para>
After this add a method 
<command>public boolean predicate2(Object dm, Designer dsgr);</command>.
This is the decision routine for the critic.
<parameter>dm</parameter> is the UML entity (an NSUML object)
that is being checked.
The second argument, <parameter>dsgr</parameter> is for future
development and can be ignored.
The <classname>Critic</classname> class conveniently defines
two boolean constants 
<constant>NO_PROBLEM</constant> and 
<constant>PROBLEM_FOUND</constant> to be returned
according to whether the object is OK, or triggers the critic.
</para>
	      <para>
<parameter>dm</parameter> may be any UML object, 
so the first action is to see if it is an
artifact of interest and if not return 
<constant>NO_PROBLEM</constant>.
</para>
	      <para>
The remaining code should examine <parameter>dm</parameter> and
return <constant>NO_PROBLEM</constant> or
<constant>PROBLEM_FOUND</constant> as appropriate.
</para>
	      <para>
Having written the code you need to add the text for the headline and
description to the cognitive resource bundles. 
These are in the package 
<classname>org.argouml.i18n</classname>, 
in the file
<filename>UMLCognitiveResourceBundle.java</filename>.
You need to add two keys for the head and description,
which will be named respectively
<constant>Cr<replaceable>XxxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable>_head</constant>
and
<constant>Cr<replaceable>XxxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable>_desc</constant>.
There are plenty of examples to look at there.
The other files 
(<filename>UMLCognitiveResourceBundle_en_GB.java</filename>,
<filename>UMLCognitiveResourceBundle_es.java</filename>, ...
for
British English,
Spanish, ...
respectively)
are the responsibility of the corresponding language team.
Notify the language teams that there is work to be done.
</para>
	      <para>
In method <methodname>Init</methodname>
of the class <classname>org.argouml.uml.cognitive.critics.Init</classname>, 
add two statements:
<programlisting>
  public static Critic <replaceable>crXxxxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable> = new <replaceable>CrXxxxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable>();
...
  Agency.register(<replaceable>crXxxxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable>, <replaceable>DesignMaterialCls</replaceable>);
</programlisting>
If you want to add a critic to a design material 
which is not already declared (for example the Extend class), 
you will have to add a third statement to the 
<methodname>Init</methodname> method as well, which is:
<programlisting>
  java.lang.Class <replaceable>XxxYyyyZzCls</replaceable> = <replaceable>MXxxYyyyZzImpl</replaceable>.class;
</programlisting>
where <replaceable>MXxxYyyyZzImpl</replaceable>.class should be part of the NovoSoft UML package.
</para>
	      <para>
Finally you should get a new section added to the user manual reference
section on critics.
The purpose of this is to collect all the details and rationale around
this critic to complement the short text in the description.
It should go in the ref_critics.xml file and have an id tag
named critics.<replaceable>CrXxxYyyyZzzz</replaceable>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...write the test in a critique?</para>
	      <para>
The critiques tests are essentially a combination of conditions 
that are to be fulfilled.
The conditions are often simple tests on simple model elements.
</para>
	      <para>
The class
<classname>org.argouml.cognitive.critics.CriticUtils</classname>
contains static routines that are commonly needed when writing
<methodname>predicate2</methodname>
(for example to test if a class has a constructor).
If you find you are writing code that may be of wider use than just
your critic, you should add it to
<classname>CriticUtils</classname>
rather than putting it in your critic.
</para>
	      <para>
For commented examples to copy, look at
<classname>org.argouml.pattern.cognitive.critics.CrConsiderSingleton</classname>,
<classname>org.argouml.pattern.cognitive.critics.CrSingletonViolated</classname> and
<classname>org.argouml.uml.cognitive.critics.CrConstructorNeeded</classname>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
<listitem><para>...fix a critique?</para>
<para>Locate the critique and insert some logging code. You should make sure that you understand all the implications of changes, therefore it is a good idea to see what makes the critic nag in the first place. But rest assured: some of the critics haven't been updated to reflect the latest changes in ArgoUML, so this is a procedure which is well worth digging into, since it gives you also some exposure to related NSUML elements.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>...change the text of a critique?</para>
<para>
The texts of the critics should be in the according localization files
and resource bundles. Be careful: in some critics the text is still in
the critic, but if you change that, you will notice that it doesn't
have any effect.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para> 
</sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>org.argouml.cognitive.critics.* class diagram</title> 
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/screenshots/argocogcritics.png"/> 
	    </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </sect2>
</sect1>


    <sect1 id="diagrams">
      <title>Diagrams</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Diagrams</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
Purpose - to generate a graphical view of the diagrams in the model with
tools.
The contents of the diagrams and model is modifyable.
</para>
      <para>
The Diagrams will be located in <classname>org.argouml.???</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Diagrams is a Layer 2 component. <xref linkend="layer2"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
The Diagrams are depending on the Model and the GUI framework.
</para>

      <sect2 id="howdoi_diagrams">
	<title>How do I add a new element to a diagram?</title>

	<para>
To add a new element to a diagram, two main things have to be done.
</para>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Create a new property panel class that will be displayed in
the property tab windown on the details pane.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Create new Fig classes to represent the element on the
diagram and add them to the graph model and renderer.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	<para>
Throughout we shall use the example of adding the UML Extend
relationship to a use case diagram. This allows two Use Cases to be
joined by a dotted arrow labelled
<literal>&laquo;extend&raquo;</literal> to show that one extends the
behaviour of the other.
</para>

	<para>
The classes involved in this particular example have all been well
commented and have full Javadoc descriptions, to help when examining
the code. 
You will need to read the description here in conjunction
with looking at the code.
</para>

      </sect2>
<!-- TODO: Property panels are not part of diagrams. -->
      <sect2>
	<title>Adding the property panel</title>

	  <para>
Property Panels are found as class PropPanelXXX.java, where XXX is the
UML metaclass. They are in sub-packages of org.argouml.uml.ui
corresponding to the XXX NSUML packages, which in turn corresponds to
their section in the chapter 2 of the UML 1.3 spec. This packaging is
essential for their lookup through Java reflection.
</para>

	  <para>
So for our example we create a new class
<literal>PropPanelExtend</literal> in package
<literal>org.argouml.uml.ui.behavior.use_cases</literal>.
</para>

	  <para>
Any associated classes that do not fall into the NSUML classification
are provided in org.argouml.uml.ui.
</para>

	  <para>
Typically the constructor for the new class invokes the parent
constructor, and then builds the fields required on the property
tab. The parent constructor may need an icon. If you need a new icon,
it should be placed in <literal>org/argouml/Images</literal> and a
call to <literal>ResourceLoader.lookupIconResource()</literal> made
(note this is a method of a GEF class). This is usually added to
<literal>PropPanelModelElement</literal>. For our example we have had
to add <literal>Extend.gif</literal>.
</para>

	  <para>
Finally the property panel must be added to the list of property
panels in the <literal>run()</literal> method of the
<literal>TabProps</literal> class, with a new call of
<literal>_panels.put()</literal>. If you don't do this, navigation
listeners won't know about it!
</para>

	  <para>
The property panel is created as a grid with a predefined number of
columns (2 if there are only a few fields, 3 if there are a lot). Into
each row of each column is placed a caption and a corresponding
field.
</para>

	  <para>
Adding a caption or field is through one of a small number of utility
methods which require you to specify which column and which row and
also a <literal>weighty</literal> parameter to specify the amount of
padding to be added when fields are stretched to fit a
column. Vertical padding is distributed in proportion to
<literal>weighty</literal> amongst all fields in the column that have
non-zero <literal>weighty</literal> values.
</para>

	  <tip>
	    <para>
You should always ensure at least one field or caption in each column
has a non-zero value for <literal>weighty</literal>. If you wish
everything fixed size and floated to the top, make the value for the
final caption in the column non-zero.
</para>
	  </tip>

	  <para>
Every field is built from Java Swing components. However these are
extended by ArgoUML to help in the provision of action methods for
fields in the property tab. Several fields involve lists, and these
require in addition list models to compute the members of the
list.
</para>

	  <para>
The fields that you might add to a property panel include.
</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Simple editable text. For example the Name
field. Supported through the <literal>UMLTextField</literal>
class.
</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
A drop down box of options that can be selected, with an icon to the
right allowing navigation to the property panel for the currently
selected item. For example the Stereotype field. Supported in general
by the <literal>UMLComboBox</literal> class and more speficically by
its subclass for stereotypes,
<literal>UMLStereotypeComboBox</literal>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
A non-editable text box, with a pop-up menu that allows opening,
addition, deletion, moving up and moving down of entries. For example
the Generalizations field. Supported by the <literal>UMLList</literal>
class. The list model is usually provided by a sub-class of
<literal>UMLModelElementListModel</literal>. There there is a varient
<literal>UMLModelElementListLinkModel</literal> which adds a link
option to the pop-up menu, allowing connection to existing model
elements (used for the Extension Points field for
example).
</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
A set of check boxes for modifiers. Supported by the
<literal>PropPanelModifiers</literal> class.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  <para>Examples of these in more detail now follow.</para>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Adding a simple list field</title>

	    <para>
For example We need to add a field to the use case property panel for
the extends relationships that derive from this use case.
</para>

	    <para>
This field consists of a label and a scrollable pane
(<literal>JScrollPane</literal>) containing the list
(<literal>JList</literal>), possibly empty, or extends relationships
from this use case.
</para>

	    <para>
Rather than a straight <literal>JList</literal>, we use its child,
<literal>UMLList</literal>, which implements the
<literal>MouseListener</literal> and NSUML
<literal>ElementListener</literal> interfaces.
</para>

	    <para>
The constructor for <literal>UMLList</literal> requires two arguments,
a list model and a flag to indicate whether the list is navigable,
i.e. responds to the mouse.
</para>

	    <para>
The list model should be a subclass of
<literal>UMLModelElementListModel</literal>, a subclass of the Swing
<literal>AbstractListModel</literal> that implements the NSUML
<literal>ElementListener</literal> interface.
</para>

	  <sect4>
	    <title>The list model</title>

	      <para>
In out example we create UMLExtendListModel. Its constructor should
take three arguments:
</para>

	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
The container, where this list is being built. I.e. the
<literal>PropPanelUseCase</literal> (from which we can then derive the
NSUML <literal>MUseCase</literal>, which is the <quote>target</quote>
of the extends relationship).
</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
A string naming an NSUML event that should force a refresh of the list
model. A null value will cause all events to trigger a refresh. The
best way to identify the event you want to use is to look at the NSUML
source for the container object (<literal>MUseCaseImpl</literal> in
our example) for calls to <literal>fireXXX()</literal>. The first
argument is the name of the event (in our case
<literal>extend</literal>). There is no definitive list, but from the
NSUML source, these are all the names of events that are used:
</para>

		  <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem><para>action</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>actionSequence</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>activator</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>activityGraph</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>actualArgument</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>addition</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>aggregation</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>alias</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>annotatedElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>argument</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>association</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>associationEnd</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>associationEndRole</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>associationRole</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>attribute</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>attributeLink</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>availableContents</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>availableFeature</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>availableQualifier</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>base</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>baseClass</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>baseElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>behavior</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>behavioralFeature</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>binding</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>body</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>bound</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>callAction</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>changeability</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>changeExpression</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>child</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>classifier</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>classifierInState</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>classifierRole</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>classifierRole1</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>client</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>clientDependency</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>collaboration</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>collaboration1</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>comment</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>communicationConnection</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>communicationLink</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>componentInstance</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>concurrency</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>condition</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>connection</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>constrainedElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>constrainedElement2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>constrainingElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>constraint</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>container</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>contents</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>context</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>createAction</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>defaultElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>defaultValue</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>deferrableEvent</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>deploymentLocation</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>discriminator</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>dispatchAction</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>doActivity</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>dynamicArguments</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>dynamicMultiplicity</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>effect</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>elementImport</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>elementImport2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>elementResidence</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>entry</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>event</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>exit</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>expression</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>extend</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>extend2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>extendedElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>extender</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>extenderID</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>extension</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>extensionPoint</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>feature</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>generalization</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>guard</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>icon</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>implementationLocation</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>include</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>include2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>incoming</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>initialValue</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>instance</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>instantiation</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>inState</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>interaction</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>internalTransition</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isAbstarct</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isAbstract</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isActive</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isAsynchronous</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isConcurent</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isDynamic</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isInstantiable</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isLeaf</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isNavigable</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isQuery</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isRoot</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isSpecification</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>isSynch</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>kind</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>link</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>linkEnd</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>location</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>mapping</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>message</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>message1</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>message2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>message3</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>message4</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>method</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>modelElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>modelElement2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>multiplicity</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>name</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>namespace</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>nodeInstance</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>objectFlowState</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>occurrence</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>operation</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>ordering</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>outgoing</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>ownedElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>owner</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>ownerScope</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>package</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>parameter</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>parent</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>participant</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>partition</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>partition1</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>powertype</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>powertypeRange</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>predecessor</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>presentation</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>qualifiedValue</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>qualifier</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>raisedSignal</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>receiver</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>reception</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>recurrence</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>referenceState</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>representedClassifier</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>representedOperation</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>requiredTag</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>resident</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>residentElement</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>script</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>sendAction</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>sender</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>signal</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>slot</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>source</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>sourceFlow</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>specialization</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>specification</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>state</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>state1</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>state2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>state3</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>stateMachine</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>stereotype</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>stereotypeConstraint</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>stimulus</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>stimulus1</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>stimulus2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>stimulus3</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>structuralFeature</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>subject</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>submachine</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>submachineState</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>subvertex</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>supplier</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>supplierDependency</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>tag</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>taggedValue</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>target</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>targetFlow</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>targetScope</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>templateParameter</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>templateParameter2</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>templateParameter3</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>top</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>transition</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>trigger</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>type</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>useCase</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>value</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>visibility</para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para>when</para></listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
A flag to indicate that a label <quote>none</quote>
should be used when the list is empty.
</para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>

	      <para>
Quite usually it is sufficient to just invoke the constructor of
the parent class.
</para>

	      <para>
This list model should then be provided with a number of methods. The
following are mandatory, since they are declared abstract in the
parent.
</para>

	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>protected int recalcModelElementSize()</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Recomputes the number of elements in the list (zero if empty).
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
                
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>protected MModelElement getModelElementAt(int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Returns the element at the given index in the list, 
or null if there isn't one.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>

	      <para>
The following are sometimes provided as an override of the
parent, although for many uses the default is fine.
</para>

	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void open(int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Perform the action associated with the <quote>open</quote> pop-up menu
on the element at the given index. The default provided in the parent
just navigates to that element.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public boolean buildPopup(JPopupMenu popup, int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Build a pop-up menu for the list and return whether it should be
displayed. Any actions will be associated with the item at the given
index in the list.
This is build using <literal>UMLListMenuItem</literal>, which can
record the index, rather than plain <literal>JListItem</literal>. 
The default provides open, add, delete, move up and move down, with
add disabled if there are already as many elements as the upper bound
(if any) for the list, open and delete disabled if there are no
elements and move up and move down disabled if they cannot be invoked
on the given element.
The default implementation always returns true.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>

	      <para>
The following should be declared as needed to support particular
pop-up functions.
</para>

	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>public void add(int index)</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Perform the actions associated with the <quote>add</quote> pop-up menu
on the element at the given index.
There is no default provided, so this must be given if the
<quote>add</quote> operation is supported.
The <literal>addAtUtil()</literal> method (see below) may prove
helpful.
</para>

		    <para>
In this routine you may create a new NSUML entity.
There seem to be three ways to do this, in order of preference 1) use
a utility from the <literal>MMUtil</literal> class, 2) use the NSUML
Factory class to create what you want 3) use new on a
<literal>MXXXImpl</literal> class.
Whilst 1) is best, most of the <literal>MMUtil</literal> routines are
not yet general enough.
</para>

		    <para>
Be sure to set it up (don't forget e.g namespace etc).
Remember also to change anything that references the newly created
entity.
</para>

		    <warning>
		      <para>
The NSUML routines generally set up the <quote>other</quote> end of a
relationship automatically if you set up one end.
If you try to do both (on a NxM relationship) you will probably end up
doing it twice.
If you do encounter this, the rule of thumb is to explicitly set the
ordered end (if you do it the other way round, NSUML will assume you
mean the "other" end to be at the end of its ordered
list).
</para>
		    </warning>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>public void delete(int index)</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Perform the actions associated with the <quote>delete</quote> pop-up
menu on the element at the given index.
There is no default provided, so this must be given if the
<quote>delete</quote> operation is supported.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>public void moveUp(int index)</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Perform the actions associated with the <quote>move up</quote> pop-up
menu on the element at the given index. 
There is no default provided, so this must be given if the <quote>move
up</quote> operation is supported.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void moveDown(int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Perform the actions associated with the <quote>move down</quote>
pop-up menu on the element at the given index.
There is no default provided, so this must be given if the <quote>move
down</quote> operation is supported.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>

	      <para>
The following normally use the default method, but may be
declared to override methods in the parent
</para>

	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>public void resetSize()</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Called when an external event may have changed the size of the
list.
The default just sets a flag, which will ensure recalcModelElementSize
(see above) is invoked as needed.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public Object formatElement(MModelElement element)</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Return an object (invariably a String) that represents an element. 
The default provided in the parent defers this to the container, which
in turn defers it to the current profile. 
This is usually perfectly satisfactory.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>public void targetChanged()</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Called when the number of elements in the displayed list (including
<quote>none</quote>) may have changed.
Default invokes the necessary Swing operations to advise of a change
in list size.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void targetReasserted()</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Called when the navigation history has been changed (and navigation
buttons may need changing).
Not clear why anything is needed, but default recomputes the list
size, and invokes the necessary Swing operations.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void roleAdded(final MElementEvent event)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
part of the NSUML EventListener interface.
Called when an add event happens, i.e. some NSUML object has been
added.
The default provided looks to see if the event is the role name we
declared, or we are listening to all events, and if so looks to see if
it relates to an element in our list. 
If so Swing is notified that the element has been
added.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void roleRemoved(final MElementEvent event)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
part of the NSUML EventListener interface.
Called when a remove event happens, i.e. some NSUML object has been
removed.
The default provided looks to see if the event is the role name we
declared, or we are listening to all events, and if so looks to see if
it relates to an element in our list. 
If so Swing is notified that the element has been removed.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void recovered(final MElementEvent p1)</literal>
</term> 

		  <term>
<literal>public void listRoleItemSet(final MElementEvent p1)</literal>
</term> 

		  <term>
<literal>public void removed(final MElementEvent p1)</literal>
</term> 

		  <term>
<literal>public void propertySet(final MElementEvent p1)</literal>
</term> 

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
these are all required as part of the NSUML EventListener interface,
which is not well documented.
In each case the default implementation recomputes the size, and
advises Swing that the entire list has changed. 
Needs more investigation.
</para>
</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void navigateTo(MModelElement modelElement)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
a request to navigate to the specified object as part of the
NavigationListener interface.

The default in the parent just invokes navigateTo() on the container
(ultimately PropPanel).
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>

	      <para>
The following utility routines are also provided in the parent.
They are not normally overridden.
</para>

	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>public int getUpperBound()</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
get any upper bound (-1 is used if there is none).
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public void setUpperBound(int newBound)</literal>
</term> 

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
set the upper bound (-1 is used if there is none).
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public final String getProperty()</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
returns the NSUML event name being monitored (null if all are being
monitored).
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>protected final int getModelElementSize()</literal>
</term> 

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
returns the number of elements in the list.
Invokes <literal>recalcModelElementSize()</literal> (see above) if
necessary.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>final Object getTarget()</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
returns the NSUML object associated with the container (some child of
<literal>PropPanel</literal> usually) that holds this list
model.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>final UMLUserInterfaceContainer getContainer()</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
returns the the container (some child of <literal>PropPanel</literal>
usually) that holds this list model.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term><literal>public int getSize()</literal></term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
returns the size of the list.
Including if there are no elements in the model, but the list has a
default text when empty.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>public Object getElementAt(int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
returns the element at the given index in the list.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>static protected Collection 
addAtUtil(Collection oldCollection, MModelElement newItem, int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
helps in writing the <quote>add</quote> function. newItem is added at
the specified index in the given oldCollection.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>static protected java.util.List 
moveUpUtil(Collection oldCollection, int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
helps in writing the <quote>move up</quote> function.
Swaps the elements at offsets index and index-1.
Not clear why it doesn't return a Collection.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>static protected java.util.List
moveDownUtil(Collection oldCollection, int index)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
helps in writing the <quote>move down</quote> function.
Swaps the elements at offsets index and index-1.
Not clear why it doesn't return a Collection.
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>
<literal>static protected MModelElement
elementAtUtil(Collection collection, int index, Class requiredClass)</literal>
</term>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
helps in writing the <literal>getElementAt()</literal>.
Finds the element at a specific index.
The last argument is ignored!
</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
	  </sect4>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Building the field</title>

	    <para>
By convention the background of the list is set to the same as the
background of the PropPanel and the foreground to Color.blue.
</para>

	    <para>
The list is then added to a <literal>JScrollPane</literal>.  
Although ArgoUML has historically not used scrollbars
(<literal>JScrollPane.VERTICAL_SCROLLBAR_NEVER</literal> and
<literal>JScrollPane.HORIZONTAL_SCROLLBAR_NEVER</literal>), it is more
helpful to permit at least a vertical scrollbar where needed
(<literal>JScrollPane.VERTICAL_SCROLLBAR_AS_NEEDED</literal> and
<literal>JScrollPane.HORIZONTAL_SCROLLBAR_AS_NEEDED</literal>).
</para>

	    <para>
Finally the inherited method <literal>addCaption()</literal> is used
to add the label for the field and <literal>addField()</literal> to
add the associated scrollpane.
</para>

	    <para>
The second argument of each of these identifies the index of the
caption/field pair in the vertical column of the grid for this
property panel. The third argument identifies the column index. The
final argument is a vertical weighting to expand the field if there is
room in the property tab. This is usually set to the same non-zero
value for all fields and corresponding captions that can have multiple
entries, so they expand equally. If none of the fields should expand,
the caption only of the last field in each column should be given a
non-zero value.
</para>

	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Adding Property Tab Toolbar Buttons</title>

	    <para>
These are added by creating new instances of
<literal>PropPanelButton</literal> (you don't need to assign them to
anything&mdash;just creating will do).
This has six arguments.
</para>

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
The container, i.e this property panel (usually just use
<literal>this</literal>).
</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
The panel for the buttons.
Use <literal>buttonPanel</literal> which is inherited from
<literal>PropPanel</literal>.
</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
The icon.
Lots of these are already defined in <literal>PropPanel</literal>.
</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
The advisory text for the button.
Use <literal>localize(string)</literal> to ensure international
portability.
</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
The name of the method to invoke when this button is used. 
Some of the standard ones (e.g for navigation) are provided, but you
will need to write any specials.
</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
The name of the method (if any) to invoke to see if this button should
be enabled.
Use <literal>null</literal> if the button should always be
enabled.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

	    <para>
In our example, the extend property panel has a <quote>add extension
point</quote> button, with a method
<literal>newExtensionPoint</literal> that we provide to create a new
use case.
</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Support for stereotypes</title>

	    <para>
The PropPanel should override the following (note the spelling of the
method name).
</para>

	    <para>
<literal>protected boolean 
isAcceptibleBaseMetaClass(String baseClass)</literal>. 
Returns <literal>true</literal> if the given base class is a class of
the target in the <literal>PropPanel</literal>.
</para>

	    <para>
This is used to determine what stereotypes may be shown for this
property panel.
</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Other sorts of fields</title>

	    <para>
Another sort of field that may be useful is the ComboBox.
This is useful to allow users to select from a pre-defined list of
alongside a navigation arrow to go to the selected entry.
</para>

	    <para>
For example this is used to provide drop-down lists for the base and
extension use cases of an Extend relationship in
PropPanelExtend.
</para>

	    <para>
The model behind the drop down is created by using
<literal>UMLCombBoxModel</literal>:
<literal>UMLCombBoxModel(container, predicate, event, getter, setter,
allowVoid, baseClass, useModel)</literal>.
</para>

	    <para>
The container is the <literal>PropPanel</literal> where we are setting
up this ComboBox, the predicate is the name of a public method in that
PropPanel that, given a model element, determines if it should be in
the drop down, the event is the NSUML <literal>MElementEvent</literal>
name we are looking for (see earlier for the list),
<literal>getter</literal> is the name of a public method in the
PropPanel that yields the current entry in the comboBox (of type
<literal>baseClass</literal>), <literal>setter</literal> (with a
single argument of type <literal>baseClass</literal>) sets that entry,
<literal>allowVoid</literal> if <literal>true</literal> will allow an
empty entry for the box, <literal>baseClass</literal> is the NSUML
metaclass from which all entries must descend,
<literal>useModel</literal> is <literal>true</literal> to consider all
the elements in the standard profile model for inclusion (so the Java
types, standard stereotypes etc.).
</para>

	    <para>
For our <literal>PropPanelExtend</literal>, we provide a predicate
routine the call for the <quote>base</quote> field is:
</para>

	    <para>
<literal>UMLComboBoxModel(this, "isAcceptableUseCase", "base",
"getBase", "setBase", true, MUseCase.class, true);</literal>
</para>

	    <para>
and we define the methods <literal>isAcceptableUseCase</literal>,
<literal>getBase</literal> and <literal>setBase</literal> in
<literal>PropPanelExtend</literal>.
</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>How UMLTextField works</title>
	  <para>
This information is provided by Jaap Branderhorst (September 2002).
</para>

	  <para>
<classname>UMLTextField</classname> implements several kinds of 
event listeners:
<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><interfacename>MMelementListener</interfacename></para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><interfacename>DocumentListener</interfacename></para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><interfacename>FocusListener</interfacename></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
Furthermore it is a <classname>UMLUserInterfaceComponent</classname>.
</para>

	  <para>
Since it is an <classname>UMLUserInterfaceComponent</classname>
it must implement <methodname>targetChanged</methodname> and
<methodname>targetReasserted</methodname>.
<methodname>TargetChanged</methodname> is called everytime the 
<classname>UMLTextField</classname> is selected. 
<methodname>targetReasserted</methodname> is of no interest for 
<classname>UMLTextField</classname>.
It plays a role in keeping history but since history 
is not really implemented at the moment in ArgoUML 
it is of no interest.
<methodname>targetChanged</methodname> does two things:
<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
It calls the <methodname>targetChanged</methodname> method 
of the <classname>UMLTextProperty</classname> this 
<classname>UMLTextfield</classname> is showing.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
It calls the <methodname>update</methodname> method.
The <methodname>update</methodname> method is described further on.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>

	  <para>
Besides <classname>UMLUserInterfaceComponent</classname>
there are several other interfaces of interest. 
One of them is <interfacename>MMElementListener</interfacename>.
</para>

	  <para>
Every time a <interfacename>MModelElement</interfacename> is
changed this will fire an <classname>MEvent</classname>
to <classname>UMLChangeDispatch</classname>.
<classname>UMLChangeDispatch</classname> will dispatch 
these events to all containers implementing
<interfacename>UMLUserInterfaceComponents</interfacename>
interested in this event, including <classname>UMLTextField</classname>.
It will also dispatch the event to all childs of an interested container
implementing
<interfacename>UMLUserInterfaceComponent</interfacename>.
By this it is only necessary to register a 
<classname>PropPanel</classname> which holds an 
<classname>UMLTextField</classname> at 
<classname>UMLChangeDispatch</classname> to
dispatch the event to the <classname>UMLTextField</classname> too.
<interfacename>MMelementListener</interfacename>
knows several methods of which only one is of interest to
<classname>UMLTextField</classname>s:
<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>propertySet</para>
		<para>
Called everytime a property in a 
<classname>MModelElement</classname> is set. 
This method calls 
<methodname>update</methodname> too if the 
<classname>UMLTextProperty</classname> really is affected.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>

	  <para>
Furthermore <classname>UMLTextField</classname> implements
<interfacename>DocumentListener</interfacename>. 
This is very typical for <classname>UMLTextField</classname>.
At the moment it is not possible to change the style of
the text in the <classname>UMLTextField</classname>.
Therefore the method <methodname>changedUpdate</methodname> does not
have a body.
This method is only called when a <classname>DocumentEvent</classname>
occurs that changes the style/layout of the text.
The methods <methodname>insertUpdate</methodname>
and <methodname>removeUpdate</methodname> are respectively called when a
character is added to the document 
<classname>UMLTextField</classname> contains or removed. 
Since both methods are called when there is true userinput 
and when the contents of the document are changed programmaticaly,
the methods distinguish between them.
<methodname>InsertUpdate</methodname> and 
<methodname>removeUpdate</methodname>
are both handled via the protected method 
<methodname>handleEvent</methodname>.
<methodname>HandleEvent</methodname> updates the property in 
<classname>UMLTextProperty</classname> if it is really changed.
If the update comes via userinput, it is checked if it is valid input. 
If it is not, a <classname>JOptionPane</classname> is shown with '
a warning and the change is not commited into the model.
If it is not via userinput, the input is not checked and the
property is set. If the property is set, the update method is called.
</para>

	  <para>
The implementation of <interfacename>FocusListener</interfacename>
makes sure that the checking of userinput only happens when focus is lost.
Otherwise, it would not be possible to enter 'intermediate' values 
that are not legal. 
For instance, say the value class is not legal. 
Without the implementation of <interfacename>FocusListener</interfacename>,
it would not be possible to enter classdiagram since
handleEvent would popup a warning messagebox.
</para>

	  <para>
The method <methodname>update</methodname> updates both the actual
<classname>JTextfield</classname> as the diagram as soon
as some property is set. 
The updating of the diagram is done by calling the
<methodname>damage</methodname> method of the figs that
represent the property on the diagram.
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>How to add a new Fig</title>

	  <para>
The new item must be added to the toolbar. Both the graph model and
diagram renderer for the diagram will need modifying for any new fig
object.
</para>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Adding to the toolbar</title>

	    <para>
Find the diagram object in
<literal>uml/diagram/XXXX/ui/UMLYYYYDiagram.java</literal>, where
<literal>XXXX</literal> is the diagram type (lower case) and
<literal>YYYY</literal> the diagram type (bumpy caps). For example
<literal>uml/diagram/use_case/ui/UMLUseCaseDiagram.java</literal>. 
This will be a subclass of UMLDiagram (in
<literal>uml/diagram/ui/UMLDiagram.java</literal>).
</para>

	    <para>
Each toolbar action is declared as a protected static field of class
<literal>Action</literal>, initiated as a 
<literal>new CmdCreateNode</literal> (for nodal UML elements) or a
<literal>new CmdSetMode</literal> (for behaviour, or creation of line
UML elements). These classes are part of the GEF library.
</para>

	    <para>
The common ones (select, broom, graphic annotations) are inherited
from UMLDiagram, the diagram specific ones in the class itself. For
example in UMLUseCaseDiagram.java we have the following for creating
Use Case nodes.
</para>

	    <para><programlisting>
protected static Action _actionUseCase =
    new CmdCreateNode(MUseCaseImpl.class, "UseCase");
</programlisting>
</para>

	    <para>
The first argument is the class of the node to create from NSUML, the
second a textual tool tip.
</para>

	    <para>For creating associations we have:</para>

	    <para><programlisting>
protected static Action _actionAssoc =
      new CmdSetMode(ModeCreatePolyEdge.class,
	   	     "edgeClass", MAssociationImpl.class,
		     "Association");
</programlisting>
</para>

	    <para>
The first argument is a GEF class that defines the type of behaviour
wanted (in this case creating a poly-edge). The second and third
arguments are a named parameter used by
<literal>ModeCreatePolyEdge</literal> ("edgeClass") and its value
(<literal>MAssociationImpl.class</literal>). The final argument is a
tooltip.
</para>

	    <para>
The toolbar is actually created by defining a method,
<literal>initToolBar()</literal> which adds the tools in turn to the
toolbar (a protected member named <literal>_toolBar</literal>).
</para>

	    <para>
The default constructor for the diagram is declared private, since it
must not be called directly. The desired constructor takes a namespace
as an argument, and sets up a graph model
(<literal>UseCaseDiagramGraphModel</literal>), layer perspective and
renderer (<literal>UseCaseDigramRenderer</literal>) for nodes and
edges.
</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Changing the graph model</title>

	    <para>
The graph model is the bridge between the UML meta-model
representation of the design and the graph model of GEF. They are
found in the parent directory of the corresponding diagram class, and
have the general name <literal>YYYYDiagramGraphModel.java</literal>,
where <literal>YYYY</literal> is the diagram name in bumpy caps. For
example the use case diagram graph model is in
<literal>uml/diagram/use_case/UseCaseDiagramGraphModel.java</literal>
</para>

	    <para>
The graph model is defined as a child of the GEF class
<literal>MutableGraphSupport</literal>, and should implement
<literal>MutableGraphModel</literal> (GEF),
<literal>VetoableChangeListener</literal> (Java) and
<literal>MElementListener</literal> (NSUML).
</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Changing the renderer</title>

	    <para>
The renderer is responsible for creating graphic figs as required on
the diagram. It is found in the same directory of the corresponding
diagram class, and has the general name
<literal>YYYYDiagramRenderer.java</literal>, where
<literal>YYYY</literal> is the diagram name in bumpy caps. For example
the use case diagram graph model is in
<literal>uml/diagram/use_case/ui/UseCaseDiagramRenderer.java</literal>
</para>

	    <para>
This provides two routines, <literal>getFigNodeFor()</literal>, which
provides a fig object to represent a given NSUML node object and
<literal>getFigEdgeFor()</literal>, which provides a fig object to
represent a given NSUML edge object.
</para>

	    <para>
In our example, we must extend <literal>getFigEdgeFor()</literal> so
it can handle NSUML MExtend objects (producing a
<literal>FigExtend</literal>).
</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Creating a new Fig</title>

	    <para>
New objects that are to appear on a diagram will require new Fig
classes to represent them. In our example we have created
FigExtend. They are placed in the same directory as the diagram that
uses them.
</para>

	    <para>
The implementation must provide constructors for both a generic fig,
and one representing a specific NSUML object. It should provide a
setFig() method to set a particular figure as the representation. It
should provide a method canEdit() to indicate whether the Fig can be
edited. It should provide an event handler modelChanged() to cope with
advice that the model has changed.
</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="java">
      <title>Code generations and Reverse Engineering - Java</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Reverse Engineering</primary>
	<secondary>Java</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Code generation</primary>
	<secondary>Java</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Round-trip Engineering</primary>
	<secondary>Java</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Java</primary>
	<secondary>Reverse Engineering</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Java</primary>
	<secondary>Code generation</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Java</primary>
	<secondary>Round-trip Engineering</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Purpose - two purposes:
to allow the model to be converted into java code and updated either
in java or in the model;
to allow some java code to be coverted into a model.
</para>
      <para>
The java things are located in 
<classname>org.argouml.language.java</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Java component is a Layer 3 component. See <xref linkend="layer3"></xref>.
</para> 

<sect2 id="howdoi_reverse">
<title>How do I ...?</title>
<para>...</para></sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Which sources are involved?</title>
	<para>
The package org.argouml.uml.reveng is supposed to hold those classes
that are common to all RE packages. At the moment this is the Import
class which is mainly responsible to recognize directories, get their
content and parse every known source file in them. These are only java
files at them moment, but there might be other languages like C++ in
the future. With this concept you could mix several languages within
a project. The DiagramInterface is used to visualize generated NSUML
metamodel objects then.
</para>
	<para>
The package org.argouml.uml.reveng.java holds the Java specific parts
of the current RE code. C++ RE might go to org.argouml.uml.reveng.cc,
or so...
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>How is the grammar of the target language implemented?</title>
	<para>
It's a Antlr (<ulink url="http://www.antlr.org">http://www.antlr.org</ulink>)
grammar, based on the Antlr Java parser
example. The main difference is the missing AST (Abstract Syntax Tree)
generation and treeparser. So the original example generates a AST
(a treelike data structure) and then traverses this tree, while the
ArgoUML code parses the source file and generates NSUML objects
directly from the sources. This was done to avoid the memory usage
of an AST and the frequent GC while parsing many source files.
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Which model/diagram elements are generated?</title>
	<para>
The *context classes hold the current context for a package, class
etc. When the required information for a object is available, the
corresponding NSUML object is created and passed to the DiagramInterface
to visualize it.
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Which layout algorithm is used?</title>
	<para>
The classes in org.argouml.uml.diagram.static_structure.layout.* hold
the Classdiagram layout code. No layout for other diagram types yet.
It's based on a ranking scheme for classes and interfaces. The rank of
a class/interface depends on the total number of (direct or indirect)
superclasses. So if class B extends A (with rank(A)=0), then rank(B)=1.
If C extends B, then rank(C)=2 since it has 2 superclasses A,B. An
implemented interface is treated similar to a extended class. The
objects are placed in rows then, that depend on their rank.
rank(0)=1st row. rank(1) =2nd row (below the 1st one) etc. Example:
</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/examples/example1.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>
In the next diagramm, a link goes to a object that is not in the row
above:
</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/examples/example2.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>
In this case, insert virtual objects which are linked to the actual
target and link to them:
</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/examples/example3.gif" format="GIF"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>
The object are sorted within their row then to minimize crossing links
then. Compute the average value of the vertical positions of all linked
object in the row above. Example: we have 2 ranks 0 and 1 with 3
classes each:
</para>
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
A B C : rank 0
</para>
	  <para>
D E F : rank 1
</para>
	</blockquote>
	<para>
We give the superclasses an index in their rank (assuming that they are
already sorted):
</para>
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
A:0, B:1, C:2
</para>
	</blockquote>
	<para>
D, E, F have the following links (A, B, C could be interfaces, so I allow
links to multiple superclasses here):
</para>
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
D -> C
</para>
	  <para>
E -> A and C
</para>
	  <para>
F -> A and B
</para>
	</blockquote>
	<para>
Compute the average value of the indexes:
</para>
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
D = 2 (C has index 2 / 1 link)
</para>
	  <para>
E = 0 + 2 / 2 = 1 (A=0, C=2 divide by 2 links)
</para>
	  <para>
F = 0 + 1 / 2 = 0.5 (A=0, B=1, 2 links)
</para>
	</blockquote>
	<para>
Then sort the subclasses by that value:
</para>
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
F(is 0.5), E(is 1), D(is 2)
</para>
	</blockquote>
	<para>
So the placement is:
</para>
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
A B C
</para>
	  <para>
(here are the links, but I can't hardly paint them as ASCIIs)
</para>
	  <para>
F E D
</para>
	</blockquote>
</sect2>



</sect1>

    <sect1 id="guiframework">
      <title>The GUI Framework</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>GUI Framework</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Details Panel</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Purpose - Provide an infrastructure with menus, tabs and panes available
for the other components to fill with actions and contents.
</para>
      <para>
No domain-specific information is located in this component.
</para>
      <para>
The GUI Framework is located in <classname>org.argouml.???</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The GUI Framework is a Layer 1 component. See <xref linkend="layer1"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
This is implemented directly on top of the Swing and Java2.
</para>

      <sect2 id="howdoi_detailspanel">
	<title>How do I ...?</title>
	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...add a tab in the Details Panel?</para>
	      <para>
Create your <classname>TabXXX</classname> class in 
<classname>org.argouml.uml.ui</classname> by
copying from another <filename>TabYYY.java</filename>
(e.g. <classname>TabSrc</classname>, <classname>TabStyle</classname>).
Then register your <classname>TabXXX</classname> in
<filename>org/argouml/argo.ini</filename>
by adding a line giving the compass point to place the tab.
Like - 
<programlisting>
south: 	TabXXX
</programlisting>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...remove a tab from the Details Panel?</para>
	      <para>
Remove the line for the tab from 
<filename>org/argouml/argo.ini</filename>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>


<sect1 id="help">
      <title>Help System</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Help system</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Purpose - to provide the menu actions that starts the help and other
documentation.
To provide infrastructure that makes context sensitive help possible.
</para>
      <para>
The Help System is not yet implemented.
</para>
      <para>
The Help System will be located in <classname>org.argouml.help</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Help System is a Layer 1 component. See <xref linkend="layer1"></xref>.
<!--
TODO: It however violates the layer concept by providing menu items that fit
into the GUI Framework.
-->
</para>
      <para>
Javahelp or some other help function will probably be used.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="internationalization">
<title>Internationalization</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Internationalization</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>i18n</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Localization</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>l10n</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>ResourceBundles</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Purpose - to provide the infrastructure that the other components can
use to translate strings;
to provide the infrastructure that makes it possible to plug in
new languages;
to administer the default (English U.S.) language;
to administer all supported languages.
</para>
      <para>
The Internationalization is located in <classname>org.argouml.i18n</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Internationalization is a Layer 0 component. 
See <xref linkend="layer0"></xref>.
</para>

      <para>
The internationalization is currently changing from ListResourceBundles
to Property files. This chapter is not updated to fit the change.
Please read carefully.
</para>
      <para>
In ArgoUML internationalization (sometimes called i18n) is done using
the ListResourceBundle-classes and parts of it is handled by the 
GEF infrastructure.
</para>
      <para>
There are several sets of Bundle files for different domains within ArgoUML.
Each domain has a name and is handled by a file.
This is set up in <classname>org.argouml.application.Main</classname>.
</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>Organising translators</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Language</primary>
	  <secondary>teams</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Translators</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
The problems with internationalization are not so much the technical
problems as to how it works but more so the problems are with
getting, keeping and coordinating the correct compentences to do
the job.
This comes from the fact that by necessity the different
persons working with internationalization have different native languages
and that complicates the communications.
</para>
	<para>
To handle this problem for GNU applications 
there is a community set up around gettext with one language team
per language working with all gettext applications.
There are also tools to help the translator do his job
delivered with gettext that are the same for all the applications.
In each of these language teams discussions are held that ensure a
consistant use of words over all these applications.
</para>
	<para>
It is for me (Linus Tolke, May 2002) unclear if and how such a
community exists for Open Source Java tools and ArgoUML cannot
simply benefit from the gettext communities since we don't use
gettext and cannot use the same tools.
</para>
	<para>
To get things done, we organise our own Language Teams with ArgoUML.
Each language teams are actually just one or several persons that
know that language and is eager to work with translating ArgoUML.
</para>
	<para>
The language team has the following responsibilities:
<orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
All localized strings and resources shall be tranlated into the language.
</para>
	      <para>
This is a constant work with keeping up with the changes that
will be made to the ArgoUML code since ArgoUML 
is under fast development.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
The terminology used shall be correct.
</para>
	      <para>
This requires work in keeping up with the current litterature in the
domain of ArgoUML.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
Help with the improvements on ArgoUML by pin-pointing where ArgoUML
needs to be modified to allow for localization.
</para>
	      <para>
As ArgoUML is originally built without localization we still have a
big backlog of stuff in the GUI that is not localizable just by
modifying the resource bundles. 
Each such thing is a Defect and shall be corrected.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
See that the used libraries also provides their part in that language.
</para>
	      <para>
This is mostly GEF since GEF is central both when it comes to 
the fact that it has localized strings of its own but also
because it handles parts of the localization.
</para>
	      <para>
This means discussing with the teams developing the underlaying package
as to how best to provide the localization for those parts. 
Either by providing localization for that team to include in the
package or by having ArgoUML overriding that package in that respect.
</para>
	    </listitem>

	  </orderedlist>
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Ambitions for localization</title>
	<para>
Let me (Linus Tolke, May 2002) try to define the levels of
ambition for us to try to make it possible to discuss where
we are going.
</para>
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>No translation</para>
	    <para>
This is the lowest level of ambition that is a "do nothing"-level.
This goes for all languages where we have not done anything like
Swahili, Polish, South African English, ...
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Tool translation</para>
	    <para>
This is the basic level of ambition that each Language Team should
aim for.
It means that in ArgoUML all strings are localized so that ArgoUML
is giving a complete appearance of being a tool for that language.
</para>
	    <para>
Setting this level of ambition for a language
(or creating a team for the language) is pointless
if there is no window system available for the language in questions.
I mean, if neither the people working with 
Windows, Linux (KDE or Gnome) or java has collected enough interest
to do a translation of the basic infrastructure there is no point
in doing so for ArgoUML.
(My Windows 2k has 80 supported languages so I would think that this
is a no-issue.)
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>User environment translation</para>
	    <para>
This is the next level of ambition that can be set out by a 
Language Team that works really well and has plenty of translating
resources left.
</para>
	    <para>
It means that not only the ArgoUML tool should be translated but also
everything around it that the user sees 
i.e. the User Manual, the Quick Guide, the FAQ, 
the Users' part of the ArgoUML Web site.
</para>
	    <para>
Setting this level of ambition for a language is pointless
if the problem domain does not exist in that language.
I mean, if the professionals that use UML or other 
Software Engineering tools, in their every day work don't use 
their native language to discuss UML concepts,
then there is no use in translating these concepts to their language,
they will not use the translation because they are more
comfortable with the English concepts.
Note that the UML Specification does only exist in English.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Development environment translation</para>
	    <para>
Here I mean that everything that the developer of ArgoUML sees
shall be translated.
</para>
	    <para>
This begins with this Cookbook, then the Developers' part of the
ArgoUML web site and 
also includes the javadoc comments in the code of ArgoUML and
design documentation of included packages such as GEF, NSUML...
</para>
	    <para>
For translating the javadoc there exists no good tools.
</para>
	    <para>
This is pointless unless we have identified an extremely large
developer base willing to take on big parts of of the ArgoUML
development that is
speaking one specific language and where most of them does not
know English.
</para>
	    <para>
If any Language Team would consider this, 
probably after several years of extremely good work on the 
User environment translation ambition level
it is a decision not only concerning that language team but the whole
ArgoUML development community.
</para>
	    <para>
Maybe I (Linus Tolke) has gone a little over the top now in trying 
to define things far off the side of the planet.
It is probably just me but I find a weird pleasure in encouraging people
to strive for unreachable goals.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </sect2>
<sect2 id="howdoi_internationalization">
<title>How do I ...?</title>
	<para>
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...verify that all translations are up to date?</para>
	      <para>
Run the JUnit test cases.
See <xref linkend="run_junit_testcases"/>.
This will verify that all tags are in synch between different
translations.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...start a new Language Team?</para>
	      <para>
The Language Teams are loosely defined by
the web page of language teams on the Tigris site.
As soon as the language code and names (at least one) are in place
the teams is created.
</para>
	      <para>
From that point it is the Language Teams responsibility to 
do a good job.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...find the languages internationalization code for the language you 
will add: en, es, en_GB,...
</para>
	      <para>
The one you are currently using is shown in the log when ArgoUML starts.
Search for lines looking like:
<computeroutput>
Language: sh
Country: unknown
</computeroutput>
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...start the work?</para>
	      <para>
Look at the files in
<filename class="directory">org/argouml/i18n</filename>,
under <filename class="directory">argouml/src_new</filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
Translate all the texts in each of these classes of files.
</para>
	      <para>
This is a lot of extremely qualified work including searching well-known
litterature on UML and Software Engineering in order to get the correct
terms for the domain.
Discuss with other UML and Software Engineering professionals with the
same native language to get it right.
</para>
	      <para>
Create the files with the translations and store them in
<filename class="directory">argouml/src_new/org/argouml/i18n</filename>.
They will have the names:
<filename>UMLResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>,
<filename>UMLCognitiveResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>,
<filename>ActionResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>,
<filename>SettingsResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>,
<filename>MenuResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>,
<filename>DiagramResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>,
<filename>TreeResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>, and
<filename>NotationResourceBundle_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.java</filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
Add the language to the JUnit list of tested languages and run the JUnit tests.
</para>
	      <para>
The purpose of this is for you to get the simple JUnit tests to work for
your language also.
</para>
	      <para>
This is in the file
<filename>argouml/modules/junit/src/org/argouml/util/CheckResourceBundle.java</filename>.
Search for the supportedLanguages-array.
</para>
	      <para>
Now you have completed the first iteration of the Tool translation
ambition.
The work will probably be more maintenance-like from here on.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...join an existing Language Team</para>
	      <para>
Discuss with the Language Team on where the team is in its work
and what you can do.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...add or modify code with localized things?</para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Write your code using the same way of handling strings as the surrounding code.
</para>
		  <para>
This means that strings are denoted by "labels" or "tags" and then
the resolution of the "tag" is in a 
<filename><replaceable>Domain</replaceable>ResourceBundle.java</filename>-file.
</para>
		  <para>
The name for the domain is most often specified in a variable like
<programlisting>
    protected static final String BUNDLE = <replaceable>Domain</replaceable>;
</programlisting>
or
<programlistingco>
    protected static final String RESOURCE_BUNDLE = <replaceable>Domain</replaceable>;
</programlistingco>
in a base class to what you are doing and there is 
a convenience method in the class
<classname>org.argouml.application.api.Argo</classname>
so normal strings are written
<programlisting>
import org.argouml.application.api.*;
...
    String localized = Argo.localize(BUNDLE, <replaceable>tag</replaceable>);
</programlisting>
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Add your "tag" and resolution in English in the non-localized 
<filename><replaceable>Domain</replaceable>ResourceBundle.java</filename>-file.
</para>
		  <para>
How do I choose the tag?
Jean-Hugues de Raigniac has made a small investigation as to how this
is done in the java world and found that there is no real consensus on
how to do this.
He suggests a hierarchical choice of tags like this:
<programlisting>
   {"docpane.label.since", "Since"},
   {"docpane.label.deprecated", "Deprecated"},
   {"docpane.label.see", "See"},

   {"stylepane.label.bounds", "Bounds"},
   {"stylepane.label.fill", "Fill"},
   {"stylepane.label.no-fill", "No Fill"},
</programlisting>
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Contact all the language-teams so that they can update their files.
</para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	      <para>
Notice that if you somewhere change the meaning of a specific
localized thing it would be a good idea to use a new "tag" for the
new meaning.
This will make it easier for the translation team to
spot the modification.
</para>
	      <para>
There eledgedly are tools in the java world to spot this kind of changes.
Until we have the tools and processes in place to handle them
it is better to rely on this simpler mechanism to guarantee correctness.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
</para>
      </sect2>
</sect1>

&cookbooklogging;


    <sect1 id="jre">
      <title>JRE with utils</title>
      <para>
Purpose - to provide the infrastructure to run everything.
</para>
      <para>
The JRE is a Layer 0 component. See <xref linkend="layer1"></xref>.
It is not distributed with ArgoUML but considered to be 
a precondition in the same respect as the user's host.
</para>
      <para>
This is a Java3 JRE so swing and awt can be used together with
reflection.
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="todoitems">
      <title>To do items</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>To do items</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Purpose - To keep track of the To do items.
Items are generated and removed automatically by the critics.
They could also be created by other means.
</para>
      <para>
The To do items are located in
<classname>org.argouml.?</classname>
</para>
      <para>
The To do items is a Layer 1 component. See <xref linkend="layer1"></xref>.
</para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="propertypanels">
      <title>Property panels</title>
      <para>
Purpose - to provide a form view of the diagrams and objects in the model.
The contents of the model is modifyable.
</para>
      <para>
The Property panels will be located in
<classname>org.argouml.?</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Property panels is a Layer 2 component. See <xref linkend="layer2"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
Currently the PropPanels for the diagrams is in
<classname>org.argouml.uml.diagram.ui</classname>
and the property panels for the other object are in
<classname>org.argouml.uml.ui.<replaceable>NS-UML path</replaceable></classname>.
</para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="navigatorpane">
      <title>Navigator pane</title>
      <para>
Purpose - to provide a tree view of the diagrams and objects in the model.
</para>
      <para>
The Navigator pane will be located in
<classname>org.argouml.?</classname>
</para>
      <para>
The Navigator pane is a Layer 2 component. See <xref linkend="layer2"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
Currently the Navigator pane is mixed with the GUI framework
and actions in
<classname>org.argouml.ui</classname>.
Parts of it (Go rules) are mixed with Diagrams and Property panels 
under
<classname>org.argouml.uml.diagram.ui</classname> and
<classname>org.argouml.uml.diagram.<replaceable>diagram</replaceable>.ui</classname>.
</para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="moduleloader">
      <title>Module loader</title>
      <para>
Purpose - to provide the mechanisms to load (and unload) the Layer 3
and auxiliary modules.
</para>
      <para>
The Module loader will be located in
<classname>org.argouml.?</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The Module loader is a Layer 2 component. See <xref linkend="layer2"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
Currently the module loader is located in
<classname>org.argouml.application.modules.ModuleLoader</classname>
with interfaces in
<classname>org.aroguml.application.api</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
This just handles the enabling and disabling of every module.
It is then the modules responsibility to connect and register to
the component or components it is going to work with using that
components Facade or Plugin interface.
</para>
      <para>
For details see <xref linkend="modules_and_plugins"></xref>.
</para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="ocl">
      <title>OCL</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>OCL</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Constraints</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Purpose - To allow for editing of strings in the OCL language.
</para>
      <para>
The OCL is located in
<classname>org.argouml.ocl</classname>.
</para>
      <para>
The OCL is a Layer 3 component. See <xref linkend="layer3"></xref>.
</para>
      <para>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Dresden OCL Toolkit</primary>
	</indexterm>
Currently this component is more or less only 
Dresden OCL Toolkit
and adaptation.
</para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>

  <chapter id="general">
    <title>General information</title>

      <para>
This section is not yet updated to discuss layers.
</para>
      <para>
This section explains some general concepts which come in handy, when 
programming in ArgoUML.
</para>

    <sect1 id="howdoi_general">
	<title>How do I ...?</title>
	<para>
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...get the according NS-UML element for a given
<classname>Fig<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></classname> class?
</para>
	      <para>
Each <classname>Fig<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></classname>
implements the method <methodname>getOwner()</methodname>
which returns the appropriate owner element which is
responsible for this Fig element.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...get the according Fig element for a given 
<classname>MModelElement</classname>?
</para>
	      <para>
for this one needs to iterate through all fig elements and invoke
<methodname>getOwner</methodname>.
Compare the result with the given <classname>MModelElement</classname>.
Beware that there might be more than one Fig Element per 
<classname>MModelElement</classname>.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
</para> 
    </sect1>

&cookbookmodules;

    <sect1>
      <title>How are modules organised in in the java code</title>
    <para>
This section is not yet updated to discuss layers.
</para>
      <para>
The previous section describes how modules and plugins are 
connected on the java level totally independant of how they
are actually linked into ArgoUML.
</para>
      <para>
Within the ArgoUML project some parts of the code are for
different reasons developed and kept separate from the main
ArgoUML source code.
These parts can be modules or plugins on the java level but
on the source code level they are called modules.
This section describes how they are organised and how you 
create such source-code modules.
</para>

      <sect2 id="howdoi_source_code_modules">
	<title>How do I ...?</title>
	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...create a new source-code module.
</para>
	      <para>
Suggestion, copy from the 
<filename class="directory">junit</filename>
module as described here.
</para>
	      <para>
Make a copy of
<filename class="directory">argouml/modules/junit</filename>
into 
<filename class="directory">argouml/modules/<replaceable>yourname</replaceable></filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
Remove <filename class="libraryfile">junit.jar</filename>
from
<filename class="directory">argouml/modules/<replaceable>yourname</replaceable>/lib</filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
Add any jar you need to 
<filename class="directory">argouml/modules/<replaceable>yourname</replaceable>/lib</filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
Edit
<filename class="directory">argouml/modules/<replaceable>yourname</replaceable>/module.properties</filename>
</para>
	      <para>
Edit references to
<filename class="libraryfile">junit.jar</filename> in
<filename>argouml/modules/<replaceable>yourname</replaceable>/build.xml</filename>
to any new jars you need.
</para>
	      <para>
Edit <filename>argouml/modules/yourname/src/org/manifest.mf</filename>.
</para>
	      <para>
Reorganize the source files as necessary.
Something like org.argouml.<replaceable>yourname</replaceable>
as the package root.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...get Argo to use a plugin?
</para>
<para>
    Once you've created a jar file with a plugin in it,
    you need to make sure that Argo can find the jar
    to be able to execute it.
</para>
<para>
    If you are using a "standard" ArgoUML source structure,
    then you should be able to execute <command>build install</command>
    or <command>ant install</command>
    in the source directory of the plugin.
    This will copy the jar file to the proper directory in the
    main ArgoUML build target.
    You can test your plugin by running <command>build run</command>
    in the <filename class="directory">src_new</filename> directory.
</para>
<para>
    If you need to install the jar "the hard way",
    try the following steps.
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         Start up ArgoUML.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         Go to the menu <command>Edit->Settings</command>
	 and look at the <command>Environment</command> tab.
	 Find the entry labelled <literal>${argo.ext.dir}</literal>.
         Create that directory if it does not already exist.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         Copy the plugin jar
	 and any other jars required by it
	 into that directory.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         Start up ArgoUML again,
	 and you should see the plugin's startup banner
	 (if it has one, of course).
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

</chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>CVS repository contents</title>
    <para>
This chapter describes what parts of the CVS repository is used for
what purpose.
This is a rather terse collection.
Further details on specific part can sometimes be found elsewhere in
this document.
</para>
    <para>
This chapter is organised as the CVS repository itself and 
everything is in alfabetical order.
</para>
    <para>
<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">build</filename></para>
	  <para>Directory where the built things end up.</para>
	  <para>
There is actually no real need to keep this in CVS.
It is there just as a place holder.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">conf</filename></para>
	  <para>Not used. Empty.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">documentation</filename></para>
	  <para>Directory where the source of the documentation is.</para>
	  <para>
<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">cookbook</filename></para>
		<para>XML-source code for this cookbook.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">docbook-setup</filename></para>
		<para>
XML Tools and configuration files used for the formatting of
the documentation from the XML-source to HTML and PDF.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">images</filename></para>
		<para>Pictures for all documents are collected here.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">javahelp</filename></para>
		<para>Not used. Empty.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">manual</filename></para>
		<para>XML-source code for the User Manual.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">quick-guide</filename></para>
		<para>XML-source code for the Quick Guide.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">extra</filename></para>
	  <para>Not used. Empty.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">lib</filename></para>
	  <para>A set of jar files.</para>
	  <para>
This directory contains the jar files of products used
by the ArgoUML
(such as log4j, nsuml).
</para>
	  <para>
These are distributed with argouml and have licenses that allow this.
For clarity the README files and licenses and other distribution
details of each used jar will also be stored in this directory.
(Quick summary: BSD License, Apache License are LGPL are OK, GPL is not.)
Don't forget to arrange for the modules version and license information
to appear when starting ArgoUML and in the About box.
</para>
          <para>
Take care also to make version of these librairies explicit,
so as to allow people building from sources to figure out
exact dependencies. Easiest way is to rename the files to
include versioning informations, the same way as shared
libraries in Unix world: foo-x.y.z.jar, bar-x.y.z.jar,
etc...
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">modules</filename></para>
	  <para>Contains source level modules of ArgoUML.</para>
	  <para>
Source level modules are modules that can be compiled and deployed
independantly (after) the rest of ArgoUML.
Each module is located in its own subdirectory.
This is the list as it looks now (beginning of March 2002).
</para>
	  <para>
<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">jscheme</filename></para>
		<para>
Module that allows to extend ArgoUML using scheme.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">junit</filename></para>
		<para>
Module that is used during the development and contains all
junit test cases as well as the junit infrastructure needed to run
these tests.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">menutest</filename></para>
		<para>
Test module that tests the plugin interface for the menus.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><filename class="directory">php</filename></para>
		<para>
Language generating, Notation and reverse engineering for PHP.
</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">src</filename></para>
	  <para>
Source code.
</para>
	  <para>
This will contain one directory for each component within
ArgoUML.
They will all compile and be tested with controlled dependencies
to other components.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">src_new</filename></para>
	  <para>
All source code for ArgoUML including pictures of icons.
</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">tests</filename></para>
	  <para>
All source code for JUnit tests of everything that is in the src_new
directory.
</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">tools</filename></para>
	  <para>
All tools used during the build process.
</para>
	  <para>
Tools also have the readme files, licenses and other distribution files
stored in this directory in much the same way as the libraries in
<filename class="directory">lib</filename>.
However the requirement on the license is different.
The tools are never distributed with argouml but merely used in the
development of argouml so it is enough to have a license that does not
allow distribution.
(Quick summary: BSD License, Apache license, LGPL, GPL, Freeware are OK.)
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><filename class="directory">www</filename></para>
	  <para>
This is all the static contents of the web site. 
See <xref linkend="how_the_web_site_works"/>.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>
  </chapter>


  <chapter id="documentation_what_goes_where">
    <chapterinfo>
      <abstract>
	<para>
This chapter contains written down ideas on what goes into what
part of the documentation. These ideas are formulated by Linus Tolke.
</para>
      </abstract>
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Linus</firstname>
	  <surname>Tolke</surname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
    </chapterinfo>
    <title>Organisation of ArgoUML documentation</title>
    <para>
There are seven significantly different bits of documentation in the 
ArgoUML project.
By documentation I mean some information of the product that is 
developed alongside the product and that has a persistant value.
</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>The code, variablenames, class names</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The javadoc</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The cookbook</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The web site in CVS</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The manual and quick-guide</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Help texts within the running ArgoUML</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The FAQ</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
These different bits have all different purpose and audience and 
the purpose of this chapter is to try to define that.
</para>
    <table>
      <title>Bits of documentation</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>Bit</entry>
	    <entry>Audience</entry>
	    <entry>Main purpose</entry>
	    <entry>Contains</entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <!-- Bit -->
	    <entry>The code</entry>

	    <!-- Audience -->
	    <entry>
<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Other developers that will maintain and improve on the code.
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
The compiler.
</para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
</entry>

	    <!-- Purpose -->
	    <entry>
Implement ArgoUML in a maintainable and understandable way.
</entry>

	    <!-- Contains -->
	    <entry>
See <xref linkend="standards"/> for more information.
</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <!-- Bit -->
	    <entry>The javadoc</entry>

	    <!-- Audience -->
	    <entry>
Developers writing code that communicates or in other ways interact
with this class.
</entry>

	    <!-- Purpose -->
	    <entry>
Make it easy to see what the functions of every class are and how
to use them.
</entry>

	    <!-- Contains -->
	    <entry>
Description of the functions of all classes, 
all public and protected methods, variables, and constants.
</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <!-- Bit -->
	    <entry>The cookbook</entry>

	    <!-- Audience -->
	    <entry>
Developers writing code, maintaining the documentation or the web site.
</entry>

	    <!-- Purpose -->
	    <entry>
Make it easy to learn how ArgoUML works and how to extend it.
Be a collection of knowledge around how everything is set up.
Be a store of the agreed solution around fundamental design decisions
i.e. design decisions that are so big that it is meaningless to
store them in the javadoc.
Be a collection of knowledge around how and why the project makes
certain decisions.
</entry>

	    <!-- Contains -->
	    <entry>
Instructions on how to add new functions and behaviour.
Instructions on how to do the chores around maintenance 
(build a release, publish a release, 
build the documentation part of the release,
test ArgoUML, test the documentation, ...).
Agreed project rules like what level of quality is aimed for and
description of processes that achieves that level.
</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <!-- Bit -->
	    <entry>The web site in CVS</entry>

	    <!-- Audience -->
	    <entry>
Everyone, i.e. developers in the project, users of the product,
people searching for UML tools for the purpose of trying, testing,
evaluating, and using the tools.
</entry>

	    <!-- Purpose -->
	    <entry>
Be an entry point for the other parts of the documentation.
Be the main download area for the ArgoUML product.
Be the central point of the ArgoUML user community.
Be the central point of the ArgoUML development project.
</entry>

	    <!-- Contains -->
	    <entry>
References to all the other parts of the documentation.
Current project information like the contents of the upcoming releases
and the plan for the nearest future.
Easy access illustration for users to be.
Some illustrations that does not work well in the other 
parts of the documentation. 
This is done as a complement to the other parts. 
Examples, tours.
</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <!-- Bit -->
	    <entry>The manual and quick-guide</entry>

	    <!-- Audience -->
	    <entry>
Users of ArgoUML.
Persons that want to evaluate ArgoUML for the purpose of starting to use it.
Persons that are training to use UML and ArgoUML.
</entry>

	    <!-- Purpose -->
	    <entry>
Describe how ArgoUML is installed and used.
Describe how UML is used with ArgoUML.
</entry>

	    <!-- Contains -->
	    <entry>
Complete installation instructions for all supported installation schemes.
Complete description on how to use ArgoUML in your project.
Complete reference on how to use ArgoUML.
</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <!-- Bit -->
	    <entry>Help texts within the running ArgoUML</entry>

	    <!-- Audience -->
	    <entry>
Users of ArgoUML.
</entry>

	    <!-- Purpose -->
	    <entry>
Give a quick help with a specific feature or button.
Give short explanations of all commands and actions.
</entry>

	    <!-- Contains -->
	    <entry>
A complete set of quick help and explanations.
</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <!-- Bit -->
	    <entry>The FAQ</entry>

	    <!-- Audience -->
	    <entry>
Users of ArgoUML.
Members of the users mailing list.
</entry>

	    <!-- Purpose -->
	    <entry>
Cope for shortcomings in ArgoUML, the help text, 
the Manual and quick-guide and the web site.
</entry>

	    <!-- Contains -->
	    <entry>
A list of issues that are not addressed in the other part of the documentation.
It is written in questions-answers-format and the contents is governed by
the issues discussed recently in the user community.
</entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </chapter>


<chapter id="cvs">
    <title>How to work with CVS</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>CVS</primary>
      <secondary>standards</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>CVS</primary>
      <secondary>how to work with</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Standards</primary>
      <secondary>CVS</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <sect1 id="groundrules">
      <title>Ground rules</title>
      <para>
When you have done all the work, and all the testing and
are about to commit something please do:
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Compile argouml 
(<command>build run</command> or <command>build package</command>).
</para>
	    <para>
This goes for all changes, even changes in comments.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
If you changes include removing files make a clean compile.
(<command>build clean</command> followed by
<command>build run</command> or <command>build package</command>).
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
If you changes include removing public or protected operations and
attributes make a clean compile
(<command>build clean</command> followed by
<command>build run</command> or <command>build package</command>).
</para>
	    <para>
The build mechanism does not yet have reliable 
dependancy checker enabled so this is the best way to make sure.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
If your changes include adding abstract operations make a clean compile
(<command>build clean</command> followed by
<command>build run</command> or <command>build package</command>).
</para>
	    <para>
The build mechanism does not yet have reliable 
dependancy checker enabled so this is the best way to make sure.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
If you have changed anything that has the potential of affecting
something in a totally different part of the code like internal
data structure, handling of exceptions, 
run all JUnit test cases
and start the tool and do some more testing.
</para>
	    <para>
If in doubt, run all JUnit test cases.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Do a <command>cvs update</command> in src_new to make sure that 
you do not forget to commit any file and to make sure that noone 
else has commited anything in the mean time.
</para>
	    <para>
Remember that if you do not commit all the files from src_new
that <command>cvs update</command> found (marked A, R, and M)
in the same commit then you would better remove those file
from the checked out copy, update to get the original version
from the repository and start over with the compilation.
</para>
	    <para>
If someone else have updated a file 
(<command>cvs update </command> shown U, or no longer pertinent)
please compile again.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Commit all files that are included in a change at the same time.
</para>
	    <para>
This reduces the chance of anyone getting an inconsistant set of files
by updating in the middle of your commit.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Commit often.
</para>
	    <para>
Remember that the repository is also a backup copy of your work.
</para>
	    <para>
If your change is so big and involves so many files that you would
like to commit it for backup reasons but it doesn't compile or
doesn't work or for some other reason should not confuse the main 
branch in cvs, create a branch to work in.
Then when your work is complete, you merge the branch into 
the main branch.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
      <para>
<emphasis>Rationale:</emphasis>
These ground rules is for the purpose of not stopping or hindering
the work for anyone.
Remember that there might be several developers working with
different agendas and different efficiency (slower or faster)
and the commits is the melting point of this.
</para>
      <para>
<emphasis>Perspective:</emphasis>
If this will take you an extra two minutes before every commit
remember that if you commit something that will not work this
will take everyone else (guess 10 persons) the extra time of
looking at the compilation error or see the tool crash (1 minute),
wonder why (1 minute),
search for the error in his own changes (3 minutes),
search for the error somewhere else (1 minute),
glance at the mailing list to see if someone else has noticed this 
and send a mail (1 minute),
wait for some response (1 hour wait),
update (1 minute),
compile (1 minute).
This amounts to 10 hours wait and 1,5 hours extra work for
all developers in the project.
</para>

    </sect1>

<sect1 id="branches">
<title>Creating and using branches</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>CVS</primary>
	<secondary>branches</secondary>
      </indexterm>
<para>We use the following standards in ArgoUML:
<itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Released versions get the tag <emphasis>VERSION_X_X_X</emphasis></para></listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
Developers working on code, with an unspecified due date are requested
to put the code into a branch if it is deemed useful that the code can
be shared. Developer branches follow the scheme:
<emphasis>work_<replaceable>explanation</replaceable>_<replaceable>owner</replaceable></emphasis>, where
            <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>work is a literal</para></listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
<replaceable>explanation</replaceable> is something like javahelp,
propertypanel, cppcodegeneration
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
<replaceable>owner</replaceable> is a self explaining code for the
owner of the branch, 
e.g. tlach (Thierry Lach) or mklink (Markus Klink).
</para>
		</listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
</para>
          </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
      <para>Merging branches together is causing some work. So please use them sparingly and announce your intentions before on the mailing list.
</para>
      <sect2 id="howdoi_cvs">
	<title>How do I ...?</title>
	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...commit stuff?
</para>
	      <para>
You have made, the change, tested it and are satisfied with it.
</para>
	      <para>
Do a <command>cvs update -d</command> and see that only the files 
you have changed are marked as modified.
If files are updated or patched by this command, 
please recompile and test again.
</para>
	      <para>
Do a <command>cvs diff</command> on each of the files and verify that
only the lines you have changed are modified.
</para>
	      <para>
Do a single <command>cvs commit</command> for all the files included
in the change.
This reduces the risk that someone else updates in the middle of your 
work and also reduces the amount of notifications of commits sent out.
Include changes to documentation and JUnit tests if applicable.
</para>
	      <para>
Don't forget to update the corresponding issue (if any) in Issuezilla 
i.e. set it to RESOLVED/FIXED.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...get my update or patch into CVS if I don't have CVS write rights?
</para>
	      <para>
Contact any of the active developers on the list and send them your
updates. They're very nice about it the first few times.
</para>
	      <para>
Supposing that you have checked out CVS as guest, then after you have
mailed a diff or file to an active developer, and he has entered it in CVS
your checked out copy contains the change but is not in sync and
the next <command>cvs update</command> will result in an merge error.
The simplest way to solve this is to do remove all files modified by you
before doing the <command>cvs update</command>. 
The <command>cvs update</command> will restore all the files from the 
CVS repository and you can start with the next update.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...get a list of the currently active working branches?</para>
	      <para>
You can't from CVS. You need to follow the announcements of created
and discontinued branches on the mailing list to know what branches are
interesting.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
...create a branch for my work on <replaceable>xxxyyy</replaceable> 
and start work on that branch?</para>
	      <para>
This assumes that you have a checked out copy of argouml
	      </para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>Change directory to the directory where argouml is checked out.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Enter the argouml directory:
<command>cd argouml</command> or <command>chdir argouml</command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Create your branch: 
<command>cvs tag -b <replaceable>work_xxxyyy_myname</replaceable></command>
		  </para>
		  <para>
<replaceable>myname</replaceable> is is a self explaining code for you
(your Tigris login).
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Change your checked out copy to be on the branch:
<command>cvs update -r <replaceable>work_xxxyyy_myname</replaceable></command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>Do your work!</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Check in your changes in the branch:
<command>cvs commit -m'<replaceable>Blablabla</replaceable>' <optional>file</optional></command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>Continue working and checking in!</para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...move my work from my working branch into the release?</para>
	      <para>
This is done when your work with the feature xxxyyy is finished and you have
decided/received clearance to enter it in the main branch.
	      </para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Change directory to the directory where argouml is checked out.
		  </para>
		  <para>
If you are just working on one feature at a time this is the place where you
have a checked out copy on the branch in question. If not, this could be any
checked out copy of the source that does not contain any uncommited changes.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Enter the argouml directory:
<command>cd argouml</command> or <command>chdir argouml</command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Move the checked out copy that you are working on to the main branch:
<command>cvs update -A</command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Merge the changes from the branch into you checked out copy:
<command>cvs update -j <replaceable>work_xxxyyy_myname</replaceable></command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Compile and run all your tests again.
		  </para>
		  <para>
This is to verify that the merge was all right, noone else had done any changes
that in the meantime that has in any way modified the work made in the branch.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Commit your changes in the main branch:
<command>cvs commit -m'<replaceable>xxxyyy entered in the main branch</replaceable></command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Discontinue your branch!
		  </para>
		  <para>
From this point on it is important that you do not reuse your branch for 
any work. Only check it out for the purpose of examining how things were
in the branch. Make sure that all other developers that have been looking
at your branch also knows that it is discontinued.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>...look at someone else's work in a branch?</para>
	      <para>
You need the name of the branch, i.e. the 
<replaceable>work_xxxyyy_hisname</replaceable>.
	      </para>
	      <para>
There are two alternatives:
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Check out argouml or part of it on that branch:
<command>cvs co -r <replaceable>work_xxxyyy_hisname</replaceable> argouml</command>
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
Update your copy of argouml to be on that branch:
<command>cvs update -r <replaceable>work_xxxyyy_hisname</replaceable></command>
		    </para>
		    <para>
Make sure that your copy does not have any uncommited code or else your
your uncommited code will be present in your checked out copy on the branch.
This could, on the other hand, be useful if you want to test if your uncommited
code works also with the additions on that branch.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </sect2>

</sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Other CVS comments</title>
      <para>
This is included in the cookbook because it seems that there are
persons within the project that don't have the in-depth knowledge
of CVS nor the interest or need to acquire it.
For that reason some simple questions are answered here 
for use of CVS in the project.
</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Why do I get double lines?
Why do I get ^M at the end of each line?
Why do I get the whole checked out file on a single line?
</para>
	  <para>
CVS is line oriented.
It stores in the repository the concept of a new line
after each line.
It is the CVS clients (the program you have installed on you machine) 
responsibility to convert the conceptual new line to the correct new
line character on your system.
<note>
	      <para>
This is only so for normal files (not marked with -kb in cvs).
</para>
	    </note>
</para>
	  <para>
If files are moved from one system to another or for that matter
checked out on one system and used and edited on another (NFS, SMB, ...)
this is not done correctly.
There could also be CVS clients out there, not doing this correctly. 
</para>
	  <para>
Systems known to the author (Linus Tolke) 
are Unix uses LF, DOS/Windows uses CR-LF,
Mac uses CR.
</para>
	  <para>
Most of the time this really doesn't matter because the editors and
java compiler on all systems is very forgiving.
</para>
	  <para>
There are however some cases when this is cumbersome.
</para>
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>When an editor (or developer) decides to "fix-it".</para>
	      <para>
This means that the editor (or the developer) goes through the file and
removes ^M on every line or something else that touches every line 
in the file.
</para>
	      <para>
This is a problem because the subsequent commit will also touch every
line in the file making that file unmergeable.
This means that every developer that had it modified in a branch or in
a checked out copy will have no help from cvs when doing his merging.
</para>
	      <para>
Remember that you never know what other developers are working with.
</para>
	      <para>
This is fixed by not doing any such fixes and doing a 
<command>cvs diff</command> before
each check in so that your editor has not done this for you.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>When cvs clients and file systems are not in sync</para>
	      <para>
This could result in one of several things. 
Either each line get an extra empty line when commited,
or the whole file turns out to be on the same line.
</para>
	      <para>
This is the case on several files in the repository at the moment
(August 2002, Linus) and can be cumbersome for the developers.
</para>
	      <para>
These cases should be fixed because the files are no longer
readable.
For the first case, removing every other line (the empty ones)
can in some cases be done without cvs having problems with
merging later on.
For the second case, with a single long line, this will be very
problematic so even though it might cause problems for other
developers it is better do this as soon as possible.
</para>
	      <para>
When this is fixed, let the fix be the only thing done in that commit.
</para>
	      <para>
To avoid this in the future, always do a 
<command>cvs diff</command> before doing your
change to make sure that only the lines that you have actually
modified will be changed by cvs and not the whole file.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	  <para>
Files that are binary that shall be stored in cvs shall be marked
as binary.
They are marked with the admin flag -kb.
This means that the line ending conversion mechanism will not be applied
on those files and they will be exactly the same on all systems.
This is good for jars, gifs, and other such files.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>


  <chapter id="standards">
    <title>Standards for coding in ArgoUML</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Coding</primary>
      <secondary>Standards</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Standards</primary>
      <secondary>Coding</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
The coding style for ArgoUML is the following
</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Each file starts with some header info: 
file, 
version info, 
copyright notice,
classes in this file (if more than one),
original author (if you want).
Like this:
<programlisting>
// &dollar;Id&dollar;
// Copyright (c) 2002 The Regents of the University of California. All
// ...

// Classes: blabla, blabla (all classes of interest in this file)
// Original Author: who ever
</programlisting>
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
All instance variables are private and their names begin with an underscore.
If the variable should be accessible then add public or protected
accessor methods with the same name as the variable without the
underscore with "get" or "set" prepended.
For example:
<varname>_lineWidth</varname>, 
<methodname>setLineWidth()</methodname>, and 
<methodname>getLineWidth()</methodname>.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
In general, write short code.
If a method will fit comfortably on one line, then put it on one line.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Use javadoc for each class, instance variable, and method. 
In general do not put comments in the body of a method. 
If you are doing something complex enough to need a comment, consider
breaking it out into its own private commented method.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Indicate places of future modifications with 
<programlisting>
// TODO: reason
</programlisting>
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Name all classes with an initial uppercase letter, and all variables
and methods with a lowercase one. 
I use the <varname>allTogetherWithCaps</varname> naming style.
Name static variables with an underscore and an inital capital letter,
e.g., <varname>_PossibleLanguages</varname>.
Name constants with all upper case and underscores, e.g., 
<constant>GRIP_MARGIN</constant>.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
To emphasize clusters of classes we are using what we call the binomial
naming style (I am sure others have thought of this also): 
The root class of the cluster has a short name (e.g., Layer), 
other members of the cluster use that name as a prefix (e.g., LayerGrid).
This makes many of the class name longer than they might be normally (e.g., Grid would be shorter).
But this provides a lot of context without
having to look at a class inheritance diagram.
It is also very nice when you have to look at an alphabetical list
of classes. I try to name class clusters so that they are not lexigraphically close others (e.g., the Net cluster
used to be named Model, but that lexigraphically overlapped the Mode cluster).
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Four spaces should be used as the unit of indentation.
Tabs must be set exactly every 8 spaces (not 4) and represent 2 indents.
</para>
	<para>
This is exactly as it is stated in the Sun Code Conventions.
It is here just for the emphasis.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
If possible use lines shorter than 80 charaters wide.
</para>
	<para>
This is exactly as it is stated in the Sun Code Conventions.
It is here just for the emphasis.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Open brace on same line (at end).
Both for if/while/for and for class and functions definitions.
</para>
	<para>
This is exactly as it is stated in the Sun Code Conventions.
It is here just for the emphasis.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
For everything else follow
<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">
Code Conventions for the Java Programming Language
</ulink>!
</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>



<chapter id="further_reading">
<title>Further Reading</title>
<sect1 id="robbins">
<title>Jason Robbins Dissertation</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Jason Robbins</primary>
	<secondary>Dissertation</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Cognitive Support Features for Software Development Tools
</para>
<para>
The dissertation of Jason Robbins is a <emphasis>MUST READ</emphasis> for everyone concerned about ArgoUML. Be careful though, since it is based on an old version of ArgoUML, but many of the concepts remain intact.
</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>Abstract</title>
	<para>
Software design is a cognitively challenging task. Most software
design tools provide support for editing, viewing, storing, sharing,
and transforming designs, but lack support for the essential and
difficult cognitive tasks facing designers. These cognitive tasks
include decision making, decision ordering, and task-specific design
understanding. To date, software design tools have not included
features that specifically address key cognitive needs of designers,
in part, because there has been no practical method for developing and
evaluating these features.
</para>
	<para>
This dissertation contributes a practical description of several
cognitive theories relevant to software design, a method for devising
cognitive support features based on these theories, a basket of
cognitive support features that are demonstrated in the context of a
usable software design tool called ArgoUML, and a reusable
infrastructure for building similar features into other design tools.
ArgoUML is an object-oriented design tool that includes several novel
features that address the identified cognitive needs of software
designers. Each feature is explained with respect to the cognitive
theories that inspired it and the set of features is evaluated with a
combination of heuristic and empirical techniques.
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Where to find it</title>
<para>LINK: <ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/docs/robbins_dissertation/">Robbins Dissertation</ulink>
</para>
      </sect2>
</sect1>
    <sect1 id="skinner">
      <title>Martin Skinners Dissertation</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Martin Skinner</primary>
	<secondary>Dissertation</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Enhancing a UML Modelling Tool with Context-Based Constraints for Components
</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>Abstract</title>
	<para lang="de">
Noch vor der Erstellung eines detaillierten Entwurfs hilft ein
Spezifiationmodell eines komponenten-basierten Systems dabei, Probleme
so frh im Entwicklungsproze wie mglich zu entdecken. Die Sprache
CCL ('Component Constraint Language') wurde bei CIS entwickelt und
erlaubt den Entwickler 'Contextbased Constraints' dem
Spezifikationsmodell hinzuzufgen. Dadurch entsteht ein Modell, das
ber die Beschreibung der statische Struktur des Systems
hinausgeht. Zur Zeit existiert allerdings kein Werkzeug, das das
Komponentenspezifikationsmodell in den Entwicklungsproze
integriert. Ziel dieser Diplomarbeit war der Entwurf eines solchen
Werkzeugs, um die Philosophie des Continuous Software Engineering
(CSE) zu untersttzten.

</para>
	<para>
Before starting a detailed design, a specification model of the
component-based system assists the software developer in early problem
detection as soon as possible in the development process. The
Component Constraint Language (CCL) developed at CIS enables the
developer to add context-based constraints (CoCons) to a component
specification model. This produces a model which goes beyond the
simple description of the system's static structure. At this time,
there is no tool to integrate the component specification model into
the development process. The goal of this master's thesis was to
design such a tool, thereby supporting the Continuous Software
Engineering (CSE) philosophy.
</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Where to find it</title>
	<para>
LINK: <ulink url="http://www.cocons.org/publications/CCL_plugin_for_ArgoUML.pdf">Martin Skinners dissertation</ulink>
</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

  <chapter id="processes">
    <title>Processes for the ArgoUML project</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Processes</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
This chapter contains processes used when working with the 
ArgoUML project.
</para>
    <para>
These processes are provided with the hope of being helpful for
the members of the project and if they feel too complicated,
ambitious or overworked, please raise the issue of simplifying
them on the 
<ulink url="mailto:dev@argouml.tigris.org">developers' mailing list</ulink>.
</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>The big picture for Issues</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
Here is the big picture of the life of an Issue.
</para>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/cookbook/IssueBigPicture.gif" format="GIF"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <sect2>
	<title>Priorities</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Priorities</primary>
	  <secondary>on Issues</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Issue</primary>
	  <secondary>Priority</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
The priorities are used in the following manner in ArgoUML:
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>P1 - Fatal error</para>
	      <para>
ArgoUML cannot start.
Crashes program, jvm or computer.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>P2 - Serious error</para>
	      <para>
Information lost.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>P3 - Not so serious error</para>
	      <para>
Functions not working.
Strange behavior.
Exceptions logged.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>P4 - Confusing behavior</para>
	      <para>
Incorrect help texts and documentation.
Inconsistant behavior.
UI not updated.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>P5 - Small problems</para>
	      <para>
Spelling errors.
Ugly icons.
Excessive logging.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Resolutions</title>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Resolution</primary>
	  <secondary>of Issues</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Issue</primary>
	  <secondary>Resolution</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
This is what the different resolutions mean and how they are used when
an issue is resolved in the ArgoUML project.
This is to be read as an addendum to the 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/project/www/docs/issue_lifecycle.html">
Tigris definition of the resolutions
</ulink>.
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>LATER and REMIND</para>
	      <para>
Not used.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>WORKSFORME</para>
	      <para>
This means that it works in a released version of ArgoUML.
State the version in the comment.
</para>
	      <para>
If the version stated by the reporter in the issue is not
the same as the version in the comment then this probably 
means that problem was fixed in some release without anyone
noticing that this problem was fixed.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="resolve_issue">
      <title>How to resolve an Issue</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Resolving</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
This can be performed by persons that has the Developer role 
in the project.
Persons without the Developer role can do most of the work but they
need a person with the the role to actually commit the work.
There might be special skills involved but it differs widely depending
on the nature of the Issue.
</para>
      <para>
Do the following:
</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem id="resolve_issue_start">
	  <para>
Pick any Issue that is NEW or REOPENED
that you from the description think that you are able to solve.
Best result if you also find some Issue that you really feel 
needs to be solved.
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/issues/buglist.cgi?component=argouml&amp;issue_status=NEW&amp;issue_status=REOPENED">The list of all of them</ulink>.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Look at your personal schedule and how much time you have during the
next couple of weeks and compare that to the amount of time you think
you will need to spend, solving the issue.
Compare this to the release plan to see what release your contribution
will fit in.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Accept the Issue (setting it to Status STARTED), 
setting Target Milestone to the release you have
chosen.
You should also assign the issue to yourself.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Make sure you have a checked out copy of ArgoUML or else check out 
a new one.
</para>
	  <para>
How this is done is described in
<xref linkend="buildingandtools"/>.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Change the code to solve the problem.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Compile and test your new code.
</para>
	  <para>
Optionally this could include developing a JUnit test case to
verify that the problem is solved.
You could also develop the JUnit test case before actually solving
the problem.
</para>
	  <para>
If your solution did not work as intended, continue changing it
until it does.
</para>
	  <para>
If you feel that your estimation of the complexity of the problem
and your own abilities and time available was incorrect,
then change the Target Milestone of the Issue to another one
that fits your new estimation.
This is just a change of plan.
</para>
	  <para>
If you, at this point, feel that your personal plans have changed
so that you won't have time to pursue the work,
change the Issue back to "NEW" with your experiences sofar
stated in the comment. Remember not to commit your changes.
This means that you are giving up and giving the Issue back to
anyone.
You should also assign it back to issues@argouml or if you know
someone else in the ArgoUML team that will continue the work,
assign it to him.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Commit your changes (and the JUnit test case if any) stating
the number of the Issue in the comment.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
"Resolve" the Issue with the resolution "FIXED".
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Sit back and feel the personal satisfaction of having completed a
something that will be part of the ArgoUML product.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
If you during this, have discovered other problems,
create new Issues stating those new problems
according to the rule for creating Issues.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="verify_resolved_fixed">
      <title>How to verify an Issue that is FIXED</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Verifying</secondary>
	<tertiary>Fixed</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Verifying</secondary>
	<tertiary>WORKSFORME</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Verifying</secondary>
	<tertiary>Works for me</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
This can be performed by anyone.
There might be special skills involved but it differs widely depending
on the nature of the Issue.
</para>
      <para>
Do the following:
</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem id="verify_resolved_fixed_start">
	  <para>
Pick any Issue that is RESOLVED/FIXED or WORKSFORME and that you have
not raised, nor solved.
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/issues/buglist.cgi?component=argouml&amp;issue_status=RESOLVED&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;resolution=WORKSFORME">The list of all RESOLVED/FIXED and RESOLVED/WORKSFORME issues</ulink>.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Run the specified release of ArgoUML as provided for downloads or 
through Java Web Start.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Test the problem in the issue and verify that the problem is no longer
there or the feature is provided.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Do one of the following:
</para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
If the problem is gone, the feature is present put the Issue in
Status VERIFIED.
</para>
	      <para>
If you are allowed to do this directly in Issuezilla or not
depends on your current role in the project.
If you are not, then get in contact with someone who is
and let him do the actual resetting of status.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
If the problem is still there, the feature does not work, put the
Issue in Status REOPENED with a description of what is still there, is
still missing.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
If you during this, have discovered other problems than the ones that
are stated in the Issue, create new Issues stating those new problems
according to the rule for creating Issues.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Do this as many times as you like until there are no Issues left.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="verify_resolved_invalid">
      <title>How to verify an Issue that is rejected</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Resolving</secondary>
	<tertiary>Rejected</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Resolving</secondary>
	<tertiary>Invalid</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Resolving</secondary>
	<tertiary>Wontfix</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Resolving</secondary>
	<tertiary>Duplicate</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
This can be performed by anyone.
There might be special skills involved but it differs widely depending
on the nature of the Issue.
</para>
      <para>
Do the following:
</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem id="verify_resolved_invalid_start">
	  <para>
Pick any issue that is RESOLVED/(INVALID, WONTFIX, or DUPLICATE) that
you have not raised nor solved.
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/issues/buglist.cgi?component=argouml&amp;issue_status=RESOLVED&amp;resolution=INVALID&amp;resolution=WONTFIX&amp;resolution=DUPLICATE">The list of all RESOLVED/INVALID, RESOLVED/WONTFIX and RESOLVED/DUPLICATED issues</ulink>.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Read through the description provided.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Do one of the following:
</para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
If you agree with the statement and feel that the Resolution is correct
put the Issue in Status VERIFIED.
</para>
	      <para>
If you are allowed to do this directly in Issuezilla or not
depends on your current role in the project.
If you are not, then get in contact with someone who is
and convince him to do the actual resetting of status.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
If you don't agree, put the Issue in status REOPENED and give a
description as to why you don't agree.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Do this as many times as you like until there are no Issues left.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="close_verified_issue">
      <title>How to Close an Issue</title>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Issues</primary>
	<secondary>Closing</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
This is performed by the person that originally raised the Issue
or by the QA responsible for that area.
This can also be done by someone who would raise the issue but
did not because it was already present in Issuesilla.
</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Pick any Issue that is Verified and that you have raised or that you
have found and refrained from raising because somebody else already
had written it. 
<ulink url="http://argouml.tigris.org/issues/buglist.cgi?component=argouml&amp;issue_status=VERIFIED">The list of all VERIFIED issues.</ulink>.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
See that you are satisfied with the solution.
This could involve reading through the resolution and 
starting the tool to verify it.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Do one of the following:
</para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
If you are satisfied, put the Issue in Status CLOSED.
</para>
	      <para>
If you are allowed to do this directly in Issuezilla or not
depends on your current role in the project.
If you are not, then get in contact with someone who is
and let him do the actual resetting of status.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
If you are not satisfied but the problem is solved as it is written in
the Issue, put the Issue in Status CLOSED and open a new Issue with
the rest of the problem.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
If you are not satisfied and the problem is not solved, put the Issue
in status REOPENED with a description on what you are not satisfied
with.
</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>How to relate issues to problems in subproducts</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>subproducts</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
ArgoUML uses some product internally and is to some respect very 
dependant on the well functioning of these products.
This is products like GEF, NS-UML, ocl, log4j, xerces, jre, ...
</para>
      <para>
Occasionally a bug found in ArgoUML is found to be a problem in one
of these subproducts and cannot or is extremely complicated to fix
within ArgoUML.
</para>
      <para>
If this happens this is the way to register that Issue in Issuezilla.
</para>
      <para>
This can be performed by anyone.
There might be special skills involved depending on the nature of the Issue.
</para>
      <para>
Do the following:
</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
During your examination of an issue you find that it is a problem
in one of the ArgoUML subproducts (GEF, NS-UML, ocl, jre, ...).
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Write a comment in the issue stating which one of the subprojects
that is the problem (and what the problem is).
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Post a bug in that subproducts bug reporting tool (or find the bug
already registered).
</para>
	  <para>
I am assuming that there is such a tool for all the subproducts.
If there isn't for the product in question, then explain the problem
to the responsible person for this product so that we are sure
that the problem is communicated.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Set the Issue in Issuezilla to RESOLVED/WONTFIX and
enter the reference from the subproducts bug reporting tool and
if possible the URL to the bug reporting tool or to the bug in question.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
The person responsible for the sourceing of the subtool in question
(Currently (December 2002) the subproduct responsible role 
is not explicitly pointed out 
but could be anyone that feels that something must be done.)
does the following for each new release of a subproduct.
</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
Looks at the new release of that subproduct to see
if any of the outstanding issues against that subproduct are in fact
fixed in the release.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
If any of the issues are fixed, then he weights together
the importance of the issues fixed,
the amount of work needed to fit the new version of the subproduct
instead of the old one,
the planned releases of the subproduct with other issues promised
to be fixed,
and
the current release plan of ArgoUML.
From this he decides wether it is time to do the update of 
the subproduct within ArgoUML or to wait.
</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
If he decides that it is time to update,
he adds the new version of the subproduct,
does all the needed work within ArgoUML,
tests and commits everything,
puts the issues indeed fixed in VERIFIED/WONTFIX,
and also closes the bugs registered in the subproducts bug reporting tool.
</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>

 <chapter>
  <title>Screen Grabs</title> 
    <para>
The following chapters are moved here from the User FAQ. They need rework.
</para>
    <para>
The current goal in this rework for this, the Screen Grabs chapter is to
join or move each section into the 
<xref linkend="inside_components"/>.
</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>How to make Screen Grabs</title> 
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Screen Grabs</primary>
	<secondary>How to make them</secondary>
      </indexterm>
  <para>There's nothing like show and tell when using software! Everyone likes screen grabs...here's how you can help out!</para> 
  <para>Make screen grabs as you go! And here's how...</para> 
      <sect2>
	<title>MS Windows</title>
  <para>You can use the PrintScreen key to copy the screen to the clipboard (as a bitmap), and then you can paste it into another application (such as MS Word, PowerPoint, etc. (maybe Paint, too)) using the Paste function (ctrl-v). MS Word may (depending on your version) allow you to save the document as an HTML page, which creates an html source file and gif files for all the embedded images (i.e. your pasted screen shot).</para> 
  <para>To capture a single window instead of the entire screen, use Alt-PrintScreen.</para> 
  <para>Image resolution is determined by screen size, for best results: 256 colors by 800X600 is good for a full screen capture.</para> 
  <para>Thanks to Derek for that little tip!</para> 
  <para>Do a search on any of your favorite freeware sites for more elaborate applications. Snagit from techsmith has been recommended</para> 
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Linux</title> 
  <para>There's a number of screen shots apps under Linux though they escape me now!</para> 
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
  <title>Argouml\application\api class diagram screen grab</title> 
 <mediaobject>
 <imageobject>
  <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/screenshots/argoapi.png"/> 
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
  <title>org\Argouml\application\configuration class diagram screen grab</title> 
 <mediaobject>
 <imageobject>
  <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/screenshots/argoconfig.png"/> 
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
  <title>org\Argouml\application\configuration class diagram screen grab</title> 
 <mediaobject>
 <imageobject>
  <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/screenshots/argocogchklist.png"/> 
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
  <title>src_new\org\Argouml\kernel class diagram screen grab</title> 
 <mediaobject>
 <imageobject>
  <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/screenshots/argokernel.png"/> 
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
  <title>src_new\org\Argouml\ocl class diagram screen grab</title> 
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/screenshots/argoocl.png"/> 
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Index</title>
    <para>
</para>
    <index>
    </index>
  </chapter>


</book>
