<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!--
// Copyright (c) 1996-2005 The Regents of the University of California. All
// Rights Reserved. Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this
// software and its documentation without fee, and without a written
// agreement is hereby granted, provided that the above copyright notice
// and this paragraph appear in all copies.  This software program and
// documentation are copyrighted by The Regents of the University of
// California. The software program and documentation are supplied "AS
// IS", without any accompanying services from The Regents. The Regents
// does not warrant that the operation of the program will be
// uninterrupted or error-free. The end-user understands that the program
// was developed for research purposes and is advised not to rely
// exclusively on the program for any reason.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
// UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BE LIABLE TO ANY PARTY FOR DIRECT, INDIRECT,
// SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, INCLUDING LOST PROFITS,
// ARISING OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE AND ITS DOCUMENTATION, EVEN IF
// THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
// SUCH DAMAGE. THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIMS ANY
// WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
// MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. THE SOFTWARE
// PROVIDED HEREUNDER IS ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, AND THE UNIVERSITY OF
// CALIFORNIA HAS NO OBLIGATIONS TO PROVIDE MAINTENANCE, SUPPORT,
// UPDATES, ENHANCEMENTS, OR MODIFICATIONS.
-->

<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <sect1 id="thanks">
    <title>Thanks</title>
    <para> We, the authors, would like to take the opportunity to thank everyone
      involved in the creation of this documentation, and especially the people
      behind setting up the DocBook environment. In particular thanks go out to
      Alejandro Ramirez, Phillipe Vanpeperstraete and Andreas Rueckert. Thank
      you! </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="project">
    <title>About the project</title>
    <para>
ArgoUML is an open source project, so it depends on people that
volunteer to work on it.
Especially in the area of development there is still
so much to do!
</para>
    <para>
This Cookbook is dedicated to everyone interested in taking
part in the ArgoUML project as such and should help to transfer the knowledge
from the old experts to them.
Please feel free to discuss the ArgoUML project and this Cookbook on
<ulink url="mailto:dev@argouml.tigris.org">dev mailing list</ulink>!
</para>
    <para>
The ArgoUML project is hosted at Tigris.
For best use of the Tigris platform,
the ArgoUML project is spread over several Tigris projects
with the argouml project as the top project.
Each Tigris project has its own
list of developers,
source repository,
issuezilla,
web site,
set of mailing lists, ...
but they are released together.
</para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="contributing">
    <title>How to contribute</title>
    <para> You can help, there are big tasks and small tasks waiting for you.
      </para>
    <para> Here is a suggestion on how you could become part of the ArgoUML Project.
      This could be perceived as a ladder to climb but remember that if so it is
      firstly a ladder of levels of commitment and time spent by you. You get no
      prize for climbing higher, you just get more responsibility in the project.
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>Use ArgoUML.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Report found bugs. </para>
          <para> There are bugs in ArgoUML. When you use ArgoUML you might
            encounter them where you least expect it. To help, make sure they are
            known about i.e. that there exists an issue in Issuezilla describing
            the problem. You need to be a registered user at Tigris to report bugs
            but notice that to add further comments to the issue you also need to
            have gotten a Role in the ArgoUML project. </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
Subscribe to some of the users' mailing lists.
</para>
          <para>
Discuss how you use ArgoUML in your project and how you promote
ArgoUML in your organization.
You can also help other users with their ArgoUML-related problems.
</para>

          <para>
There is one users' mailing list for each language project
(Spanish, Swedish, Chinese, ...)
for the users that prefer to discuss ArgoUML using that language.
These are not currently (May 2006) very active but the
main list, the English-speaking list at users@argouml.tigris.org-list, is.
</para>

          <para>
In some cases there are also users' mailing lists for the specific
subproject, for discussing these specific features or uses of them
(cpp, andromda, ...).
Prefer those if your discussion is for that area.
</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Apply for an Observer role.</para>
          <para>
This shows that you are committed to the project and also allows
you to comment on issues.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Familiarize yourself with the project and how we work. </para>
          <para> Suggestion on how to go about this:
            <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
              <listitem>
                <para> Read through most of the User manual and install and run
                  the latest version of ArgoUML. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Subscribe to the issues list.</para>
                <para> You will get updates on all issues so you can monitor what
                  we are doing in the project. (It could be a lot of mails. If it
                  turns out you don't like watching issues in this way, you
                  unsubscribe!) </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Subscribe to the cvs mailing list
of the project that you are interested in.
</para>
                <para>
You will get updates on all changes that are done to code,
                  documentation, and the web site. (It could be a lot of large
                  mails. If it turns out you don't like watching what is going on
                  in the project in this way you unsubscribe.) </para>
                <note>
                  <para>
Some of the argouml projects does not use cvs for the repository
but subversion
and, probably during 2006,
we will convert all the argouml project to subversion.
For subversion projects, the mailing list is called commits.
When the conversion is done, you will be moved from the cvs list to the
commits list automatically but the syntax of the mailings will change.
</para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Read the process part of the Developers Cookbook
at <xref linkend="processes"/>.
</para>
                <para> This will give you the idea of how the ArgoUML project
                  attempts to release with good quality and especially how we
                  use Issuezilla. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Get the Observer role granted.</para>

                <para>
You can apply for the Observer role in any or all of the argouml projects
if you like.
Choose the ones you are interested in.
</para>

                <para>
From this on you can comment on bugs yourself directly in Issuezilla.
</para>

                <para> You can also verify issues according to the verification
                  process (see <xref linkend="verify_resolved_fixed"/>).
</para>
                <para> This will help you understand the terminology used in the
                  project and also gives you an idea of the current quality of
                  ArgoUML and what needs to be done in the future. </para>
                <para> This is also a very low-commitment level task that could
                  be completed in a couple of minutes (depending on your choice
                  of issue). </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Read the rest of the Developers Cookbook.</para>
                <para> There is a lot of stuff discussed in here that is
                  interesting for your understanding of the project and the
                  code. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Check out the source from CVS and build.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist> </para>
          
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
Subscribe to some of the dev mailing lists.
</para>
          <para>
There is one dev mailing list for each project
with the purpose of discussing the specifics for that project.
Subscribe to as many of them as you'd like and take part.
</para>

          <para>
The purpose of this is to see what the developers are discussing
in the project.
</para>

          <para>
Monitor the discussions and as soon as you see something
discussed where you have an opinion, jump right in!
</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Familiarize yourself with the code.</para>
          <para>For this a good knowledge of Java is more or less a prerequisite.
            </para>
          <para> Suggestion on how to go about this:
            <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
              <listitem>
                <para>
Take active part in the discussions on the dev-list.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Solve issues registered in Issuezilla or fix other things that you
want to pursue.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Convince someone to commit your changes.
</para>
                <para>
Establish a relationship with one developer of the project you want
to work with.
That developer will check that your code reaches the quality level
that we strive for in the project and obeys the design.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para> Repeat. </para>
                <para>
This can go on until the developer helping you knows that
you have good knowledge of the project quality and
design and
the main problem for you two is that
sending,
waiting,
committing,
updating et.c.
is extra work.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Apply for a Developer role in the project where you want to contribute.
</para>
          <para>
This allows you to do commits on your own and you can now increase
the pace in which you are working while also increasing your
responsibilities in the project.
</para>
          <para>
This role is granted by the Project leader after he is convinced
that you have learned the enough about the project w.r.t.:
</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Understanding and accepting the goals.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Understanding where we are in the development process.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Understanding the terminology used in the project.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Understanding how we use CVS in the project.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Understanding the set of tools (ant, JUnit) and how to use them.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Focus your work in a specific area.</para>
          <para>
Everybody has different interests and the best contribution is
made when someone is allowed to pursue his own interests. Hopefully
ArgoUML provides you with interesting challenges to your taste.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Accept responsibility for a specific area.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
</para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>About this Cookbook</title>
    <para> This document, the Cookbook for Developers of ArgoUML, is provided
      with the hopes of being helpful for the developers of ArgoUML when it comes to
      learning and understanding how ArgoUML work in order to improve on its
      functions and features.
      It can also be of interest for persons that wish to analyze the ArgoUML
      project for whatever purpose that may be. </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>In this Cookbook, you will find...</title>
      <para>
Information on how to compile ArgoUML.
(<xref linkend="buildingandtools"/>)
</para>

      <para>
Information on how different features of ArgoUML are implemented and
how they are to be used.
(<xref linkend="subsystems"/> and
<xref linkend="inside_subsystems"/>)
</para>

      <para>
Information on how you should write extensions to ArgoUML.
(<xref linkend="extending"/>)
</para>

      <para>
Information that you, as a developer of ArgoUML,
need to know about how to contribute.
(<xref linkend="standards"/>,
<xref linkend="app.docstand"/> and
<xref linkend="processes"/>)
</para>
      
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>In this Cookbook, you will not find...</title>
      <para> You will not find information on how to install and use ArgoUML.
        </para>
      <para> You will not find information on what UML is and if or how you should use
        it in your project. </para>
      <para> You will not find information on how to convince your project to use
        ArgoUML as a modeling tool. </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="mailing_lists">
    <title>Mailing Lists</title> <indexterm><primary>Mailing
    lists</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>Developers' Mailing
    List</primary></indexterm>
    <para> All developers <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> subscribe to the mailing
      list for developers. Please find the details at: <ulink
        url="http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList">
      http://argouml.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectMailingListList</ulink>
      </para> <indexterm>
    <primary>CVS</primary>
    <secondary>Mailing list</secondary> </indexterm> <indexterm>
    <primary>Issues</primary>
    <secondary>Mailing list</secondary> </indexterm>
    <para> It is also recommended to join the CVS and Issues mailing lists. Both
      give you a good idea of what is going on. Developers should also work with
      Issuezilla registering or fixing problems found by themselves and others.
      </para>
  </sect1>
  
</chapter>

<!-- Local stuff for Emacs - please do not delete

Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-doctype: "cookbook.xml"
sgml-parent-document: ("cookbook.xml" "chapter" nil)
sgml-validate-command: "nsgmls -wxml -sv ../docbook-setup/xml.dcl \
cookbook.xml"
indent-tabs-mode: nil
End:

-->