<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="requirements">
    <chapterinfo>
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Linus</firstname>
	  <surname>Tolke</surname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
    </chapterinfo>
    <title>ArgoUML requirements</title>

    <para>
This chapter contains a description on how ArgoUML should work
and behave for the users.
</para>

    <para>
These things might not be implemented yet and the solutions
might not even be clear but it is a definition of the goal.
</para>
    <para>
The fact that it is not implemented or doesn't work as stated here
should be registered as a bug 
in the bug registering tool.
</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements for Look and feel</title>
      <para>
This describes how the ArgoUML look and feel shall behave.
</para>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
When multiple visual components are showing the same model element
they shall be updated in a consistent manner throughout the application.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
As soon as the model element changes then all views shall update.
For text fields, this can be at every key stroke.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
There shall be no indication of an exception on the screen or in the
log if it has occured merely because of a user mistyping or not being
aware of UML syntax.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
All text fields shall have context sensitive help.
</para>
	    <para>
As follows:
<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
A tooltip that explains the data and format expected by the
particular field.
</para>
		  <para>
This can be omitted when there is a header stating the data of
the field and the format is obvious.
</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
Pressing F1 or choosing help from the menu shall display a popup
window explaining for data and format required by the current input
field. 
Input focus shall be left on the field during any user
interaction with the popup (dragging, scrolling or closing).
</para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
</para>

	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
 
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements for UML</title>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
ArgoUML shall be a correct implementation of the UML 1.3 model.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
ArgoUML shall implement everything in the UML 1.3 model.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements on java and jvm</title>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Choice of JRE</para>
	    <para>
		We will support any JRE compatible with the Sun specification one version
		behind the most recent stable JRE from Sun.
		A stable JRE is considered to be one that has had a second non-beta release.
	    </para>
	    <para>
                This is to allow ArgoUML to gradually take on board new stable features of
                the Java language while still offering users some choice of JRE.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Download and start</para>
	    <para>
It shall be possible to install ArgoUML locally on the machine
and use without Internet connection.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Console output</para>
	    <para>
Logging or tracing information shall not be written to the console
or to any file unless explicitly turned on by the user.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Requirements set up for the benefit of the development of ArgoUML</title>
      <para>
<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Logging</para>
	    <para>
The code shall contain entries logging important information
for the purpose of helping Developers of ArgoUML in finding problems
in ArgoUML itself.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>


<!-- Local stuff for Emacs - please do not delete

Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-doctype: "cookbook.xml"
sgml-parent-document: ("cookbook.xml" "chapter" nil)
sgml-validate-command: "nsgmls -wxml -sv ../docbook-setup/xml.dcl \
  cookbook.xml"
End:

-->
