<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="standards">
    <title>Standards for coding in ArgoUML</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Coding</primary>
      <secondary>Standards</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Standards</primary>
      <secondary>Coding</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
The coding style for ArgoUML is the following
</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Each file starts with some header info: 
file, 
version info, 
copyright notice,
classes in this file (if more than one),
original author (if you want).
Like this:
<programlisting>
// &dollar;Id&dollar;
// Copyright (c) 2003 The Regents of the University of California. All
// ...

// Classes: blabla, blabla (all classes of interest in this file)
// Original Author: who ever
</programlisting>
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
All instance variables are private and their names begin with an underscore.
If the variable should be accessible then add public or protected
accessor methods with the same name as the variable without the
underscore with "get" or "set" prepended.
For example:
<varname>_lineWidth</varname>, 
<methodname>setLineWidth()</methodname>, and 
<methodname>getLineWidth()</methodname>.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
In general, write short code.
If a method will fit comfortably on one line, then put it on one line.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Use javadoc for each class, instance variable, and method. 
In general do not put comments in the body of a method. 
If you are doing something complex enough to need a comment, consider
breaking it out into its own private commented method.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Indicate places of future modifications with 
<programlisting>
// TODO: reason
</programlisting>
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Name all classes with an initial uppercase letter, and all variables
and methods with a lowercase one. 
I use the <varname>allTogetherWithCaps</varname> naming style.
Name static variables with an underscore and an inital capital letter,
e.g., <varname>_PossibleLanguages</varname>.
Name constants with all upper case and underscores, e.g., 
<constant>GRIP_MARGIN</constant>.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
To emphasize clusters of classes we are using what we call the binomial
naming style (I am sure others have thought of this also): 
The root class of the cluster has a short name (e.g., Layer), 
other members of the cluster use that name as a prefix (e.g., LayerGrid).
This makes many of the class name longer than they might be normally (e.g., Grid would be shorter).
But this provides a lot of context without
having to look at a class inheritance diagram.
It is also very nice when you have to look at an alphabetical list
of classes. I try to name class clusters so that they are not lexigraphically close others (e.g., the Net cluster
used to be named Model, but that lexigraphically overlapped the Mode cluster).
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Four spaces should be used as the unit of indentation.
Tabs must be set exactly every 8 spaces (not 4) and represent 2 indents.
</para>
	<para>
This is exactly as it is stated in the Sun Code Conventions.
It is here just for the emphasis.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
If possible use lines shorter than 80 charaters wide.
</para>
	<para>
This is exactly as it is stated in the Sun Code Conventions.
It is here just for the emphasis.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
Open brace on same line (at end).
Both for if/while/for and for class and functions definitions.
</para>
	<para>
This is exactly as it is stated in the Sun Code Conventions.
It is here just for the emphasis.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
For everything else follow
<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">
Code Conventions for the Java Programming Language
</ulink>!
</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>



<!-- Local stuff for Emacs - please do not delete

Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-doctype: "cookbook.xml"
sgml-parent-document: ("cookbook.xml" "chapter" nil)
sgml-validate-command: "nsgmls -wxml -sv ../docbook-setup/xml.dcl \
  cookbook.xml"
End:

-->
