<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!--
// Copyright (c) 1996-2006 The Regents of the University of California. All
// Rights Reserved. Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this
// software and its documentation without fee, and without a written
// agreement is hereby granted, provided that the above copyright notice
// and this paragraph appear in all copies.  This software program and
// documentation are copyrighted by The Regents of the University of
// California. The software program and documentation are supplied "AS
// IS", without any accompanying services from The Regents. The Regents
// does not warrant that the operation of the program will be
// uninterrupted or error-free. The end-user understands that the program
// was developed for research purposes and is advised not to rely
// exclusively on the program for any reason.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
// UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BE LIABLE TO ANY PARTY FOR DIRECT, INDIRECT,
// SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, INCLUDING LOST PROFITS,
// ARISING OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE AND ITS DOCUMENTATION, EVEN IF
// THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
// SUCH DAMAGE. THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIMS ANY
// WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
// MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. THE SOFTWARE
// PROVIDED HEREUNDER IS ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, AND THE UNIVERSITY OF
// CALIFORNIA HAS NO OBLIGATIONS TO PROVIDE MAINTENANCE, SUPPORT,
// UPDATES, ENHANCEMENTS, OR MODIFICATIONS.
-->

<sect1 id="internationalization">
  <title>Internationalization</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Internationalization</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>I18n</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Localization</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>L10n</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>ResourceBundles</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
Purpose - to provide the infrastructure that the other subsystems can
use to translate strings;
to provide the infrastructure that makes it possible to plug in
new languages;
to administer the default language;
to administer all supported languages.
</para>
  <para>
When ArgoUML starts it starts with the language given by the first
decisive language information of
<orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Command line argument
</para>
        <para>
The prepared Java Web Start alternatives also uses this to override
everything else.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
The users' saved configuration
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
The default locale for the users' computer
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
ArgoUML default language (Enlish U.S.)
</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

This is done independently of if ArgoUML has that language prepared
or not.

<example>
      <title>
Starting with nonexisting language.
</title>
      <para>
If ArgoUML is started with Swahili on the command line (that doesn't exist),
while the user has French (that does exist) configured,
ArgoUML will work in Swahili and all languages will show up in English U.S.
i.e. the default language because Swahili doesn't exist.
</para>
    </example>
</para>
  <para>
The Internationalization is located in <classname>org.argouml.i18n</classname>
in the class path.
In the checked out copy of ArgoUML it is located partly in
<filename>argouml/src_new/org/argouml/i18n</filename> 
- functionality, and non-localized default language (US English), 
and partly in
<filename>argouml-<replaceable>language</replaceable>/src/org/argouml/i18n</filename>
- all files for a specific language (one new tigris project for each language).
</para>
  <para>
For the time being, some languages are also placed in
<filename>argouml/src/i18n/<replaceable>language</replaceable>/src/org/argouml</filename>
</para>
  <para>
The Internationalization is an Infrastructure subsystem. 
See <xref linkend="infrastructure_subsystems"></xref>.
</para>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>PropertyResourceBundles</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
In ArgoUML internationalization (sometimes called i18n) is done using
the property files that are loaded into PropertyResourceBundles.
</para>
  <sect2>
    <title>Organizing translators</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Language teams</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Internationalization teams</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>i18n teams</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Translators</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
The problems with internationalization are not so much the technical
problems as to how it works but more so the problems are with
getting, keeping and coordinating the correct competences to do
the job.
This comes from the fact that by necessity the different
persons working with internationalization have different native languages
and that complicates the communications.
</para>
    <para>
To handle this problem for GNU applications 
there is a community set up around <quote>gettext</quote> with one language team
per language working with all <quote>gettext</quote> applications.
There are also tools to help the translator do his job
delivered with <quote>gettext</quote> that are the same for all the applications.
In each of these language teams discussions are held that ensure a
consistent use of words over all these applications.
</para>
    <para>
It is for me (Linus Tolke, May 2002) unclear if and how such a
community exists for Open Source Java tools and ArgoUML cannot
simply benefit from the <quote>gettext</quote> communities since we don't use
<quote>gettext</quote> and cannot use the same tools.
</para>
    <para>
To get things done, we organize our own Language Teams for ArgoUML.
Each language team is actually just one or several persons that
know that language and are eager to work with translating ArgoUML.
</para>
    <para>
The language team has the following responsibilities:
<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Constitute the foundation of the ArgoUML community for that language.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Tranlate all localized strings and resources.
</para>
          <para>
This is a constant work with keeping up with the changes that
will be made to the ArgoUML code and ArgoUML modules since ArgoUML 
is under fast development.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The terminology used shall be correct.
</para>
          <para>
This requires work in keeping up with the current literature in the
domain of ArgoUML.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Help with the improvements on ArgoUML by pin-pointing where ArgoUML
needs to be modified to allow for localization.
</para>
          <para>
As ArgoUML is originally built without localization there may still have
places in the GUI that is not localizable just by
modifying the resource bundles. 
Each such place is a Defect and shall be corrected.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
See that the used libraries also provide their part in that language.
</para>
          <para>
This is mostly GEF since GEF is central both when it comes to 
the fact that it has localized strings of its own but also
because it handles parts of the localization.
</para>
          <para>
This means discussing with the teams developing the underlying package
as to how best to provide the localization for those parts. 
Either by providing localization for that team to include in the
package or by having ArgoUML overriding that package in that respect.
</para>
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>
</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Ambitions for localization</title>
    <para>
An ArgoUML subproject is created for each Language Team.
</para>
    <para>
The subproject has the following that is used in
building a community:
</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A web site</para>
        <para>
Ideally the site should match the main ArgoUML site,
page by page, with a footer on every page with flags of all the languages
that that specific page exist in so that it is easy to travel between
languages.
Missing pages should be linked to the main ArgoUML counterpart.
</para>
        <para>
Alas there is no tool support on Tigris to help in this.
<!-- Issue 26 on www (http://www.tigris.org/issues/show_bug.cgi?id=26) -->
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Mailing lists</para>
        <para>
The users@argouml-<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.tigris.org
should be for user and
dev@argouml-<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.tigris.org
for persons discussing the building of the site or the translation.
Discussions on both lists should be carried out in the actual language.
</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="howdoi_internationalization">
    <title>How do I ...?</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>...fix an incorrect or missing translation?</para>
          <para>
This is the responsibility of the language team.
</para>
          <para>
If you are a member of the language team, commit the new translation.
</para>
          <para>
If you are not, send your corrections to the correct team by mail
or enter an issue in issuezilla.
Each language team might want to handle this differently.
Whatever way, it should is stated on the web site for that team.
The language team members are the ones with the Developer role in
the language project.
</para>
          <para>
If the language team does not do its work quickly enough
(or well enough in your opinion),
please volunteer to help them out by joining the team.
</para>
          <para>
If the language team does not respond, contact the project leader
of the ArgoUML project.
</para>
          <para>
For historic reasons there are currently (June 2005) teams without
projects of their own.
Projects will be created when something is to be done for these languages.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>...verify that all translations are up to date?</para>
          <para>
There is a simple tool you can use that is developed in the argouml-gen
project.
Currently (June 2005) this tool is run regularly
and a web page with the result published in the argouml-stats project.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>...start a new Language Team?</para>
          <para>
Contact the project leader of the ArgoUML project to discuss this.
He will create the project and make you the first member
of the project once he is convinced that
you have understood the responsibilities.
</para>
          <para>
The project are argouml subprojects so they are listed at the bottom of
the argouml web page.
</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
...find the languages internationalization code for the language 
your instance of ArgoUML is attempting to run with: en, es, en_GB,...
</para>
          <para>
The one you are currently using is shown in the Versions information
in the about box.
Help Menu => About ArgoUML Menuitem => Version tab
just after the Operating System information.
Search for the text looking like this:
<programlisting>
Language: sh
Country: KR
</programlisting>
This example means that you have your computer set to
Swahili as spoken in Korea (I think).
Notice that the <replaceable>Language:</replaceable> and
<replaceable>Country:</replaceable> are localized and could
appear in your language.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>...start the translation work?</para>
          <para>
This is only applicable for members of the language team.
</para>
          <para>
Make sure you are a Developer in the appropriate project.
</para>
          <para>
Look at the files in
<filename class="directory">org/argouml/i18n</filename>,
under <filename class="directory">argouml/src_new</filename>
(in the argouml project).
</para>
          <para>
Translate all the values in each of these files.
</para>
          <para>
This is a lot of extremely qualified work including searching well-known
literature on UML and Software Engineering in order to get the correct
terms for the domain.
Discuss with other UML and Software Engineering professionals with the
same native language to get it right.
</para>
          <para>
Create the files with the translations and store them in
<filename class="directory">argouml-<replaceable>language code</replaceable>/src/org/argouml/i18n</filename>.
They will have names like:
<filename>action_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.properties</filename>,
<filename>button_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.properties</filename>,
<filename>checkbox_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.properties</filename>,
<filename>combobox_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.properties</filename>, ...
</para>
          <para>
When this is done the first iteration of the Tool translation is completed.
The work will probably be more maintenance-like from here on.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>...join an existing Language Team</para>
          <para>
Join the dev mailing list in the correct project and
apply for an Observer role in the project.
</para>
          <para>
Discuss with the Language Team in question by mailing
on the dev list.
They will hopefully have work prepared for you and greet you with open arms.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>...add or modify code with localized things?</para>
          <para>
This is only applicable for developers working with the ArgoUML Java source
or some argouml module.
</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Everywhere the user would see a string in the GUI you should
localize a key.
</para>
              <para>
This means that instead of writing a string you write a call to a
localizer method with a "key" ("label" or "tag") as argument and
the localizer method finds
the resolution of the "key" is in one of the property files.
You select one of the files for you key and name the key accordingly.
</para>
              <para>
The key is a String.
The key has a special syntax like this:
<programlisting>
    word1.word2.word3
</programlisting>
where word1 is the same as the first part of the filename that 
the key resides in.
Example:
The key "action.about-argouml" resides in the files
<filename>action.properties</filename> and 
<filename>action_<replaceable>language code</replaceable>.properties</filename>.
</para>
              <para>
You will have to call the class
<classname>org.argouml.i18n.Translator</classname>
to convert them to wherever they are used.
</para>
              <para>
This is how a real example would look like:
<programlisting>
import org.argouml.i18n.Translator;
...
    String localized = Translator.localize(<replaceable>key</replaceable>);
</programlisting>
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Add your "key" and resolution in English (U.S.) in the non-localized 
properties file in
<filename>argouml/src_new/org/argouml/i18n</filename>
and test that the GUI looks good for the default language.
</para>
              <para>
Which property file ArgoUML will eventually use
depends on the localization settings
of the running ArgoUML instance.
While developing you should use en_US or some language
that does not have a translation so that you can work with 
the default language.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Contact all language-teams so that they can update their files.
</para>
              <para>
Currently (November 2003) there is a great confusion as to where
we stand on the different translations.
For this reason we can't say if any language team is up to date
with the changes and served by such a contact.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
If you have strings that are sentences where you have dynamic values
like a file name, a class name, or some property to enter at a certain place,
remember that all languages would not write it exactly like that.
Use <classname>MessageFormat</classname> to build every such sentence!
There is a convenience function for this 
in <classname>Translator</classname>
called <methodname>messageFormat</methodname>.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
          <para>
Notice that if you somewhere change the meaning of a specific
localized string it would be a good idea to use a new "key" for the
new meaning.
This will make it easier for the translation team to
spot the modification.
</para>
          <para>
There allegedly are tools in the java world to spot this kind of changes.
Until we have the tools and processes in place to handle them
it is better to rely on this simpler mechanism to guarantee correctness.
</para>
          <para>
Notice also that you shouldn't localize 
log entries,
comments,
exception names,
names of environment variables, and
tags and tokens used in save files.
This is because
the development project of ArgoUML is a one-language community (en_US) and
the users of ArgoUML would want to be able to run an ArgoUML localized
differently with 
otherwise the exact same settings,
loading and saving the same files, ...
Also a user, changing the language, should not have his files or
configuration corrupted by this change.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>


<!-- Local stuff for Emacs - please do not delete

Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-doctype: "cookbook.xml"
sgml-parent-document: ("cookbook.xml" "sect1" nil)
sgml-validate-command: "nsgmls -wxml -sv ../docbook-setup/xml.dcl \
  cookbook.xml"
indent-tabs-mode: nil
End:

-->
