<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!--
	// Copyright (c) 1996-2005 The Regents of the University of California. All
	// Rights Reserved. Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this
	// software and its documentation without fee, and without a written
	// agreement is hereby granted, provided that the above copyright notice
	// and this paragraph appear in all copies.  This software program and
	// documentation are copyrighted by The Regents of the University of
	// California. The software program and documentation are supplied "AS
	// IS", without any accompanying services from The Regents. The Regents
	// does not warrant that the operation of the program will be
	// uninterrupted or error-free. The end-user understands that the program
	// was developed for research purposes and is advised not to rely
	// exclusively on the program for any reason.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
	// UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BE LIABLE TO ANY PARTY FOR DIRECT, INDIRECT,
	// SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, INCLUDING LOST PROFITS,
	// ARISING OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE AND ITS DOCUMENTATION, EVEN IF
	// THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
	// SUCH DAMAGE. THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIMS ANY
	// WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
	// MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. THE SOFTWARE
	// PROVIDED HEREUNDER IS ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, AND THE UNIVERSITY OF
	// CALIFORNIA HAS NO OBLIGATIONS TO PROVIDE MAINTENANCE, SUPPORT,
	// UPDATES, ENHANCEMENTS, OR MODIFICATIONS.
-->
<preface>
	<title>Preface</title>
	<para>
		1 April 2001
	</para>
	<para>
		In the last decade of the last millenium, object-oriented (OO) technology finally completed it's 
		transformation from a laboratory curiousity in the 1960s to become <emphasis>the</emphasis> mainstream 
		software development paradigm. It has been a long, tough journey - that nearly ended in obscurity - 
		primarily because OO technology required a major shift in the thought processes of systems designers, 
		developers and others involved in the software development lifecycle.
	</para>
	<para>
		It wasn't until the introduction of OO-hybrid languages such as C++, Classic Ada and Object Pascal in  
		the eighties that the mainstream was introduced to and, given the opportunity to experiment with OO technology. 
		These languages combined support for OO programming with support for traditional procedural programming. 
		The lack of support of procedural programming in pure OO languages had hindered the adoption of OO technology 
		for many years. The journey that had begun with the introduction of <emphasis>objects</emphasis> in Simula in 
		the 1960s was now complete. OO technology was now accessible to the mainstream…well, OO programming was at least.
	</para>
	<para>
		Simulation is the basic premise that underpins OO technology. An OO system is designed and implemented 
		essentially as a simulation of the real world using software artifacts. This premise is as powerful 
		as it is simple. By designing and building software 
		systems in this manner, the same language and ideas 
		can be used in the analysis, design and implementation of OO systems. This allowed a system to be designed 
		and tested (or more correctly allowed a system to be simulated) without having to actually build the system first. 
		This feature coupled with the ability to design systems at a very high level empowered experienced OO 
		practitioners to design and successfully implement more complex systems than had previously been possible.
	</para>
	<para>
		The availabilty of various OO methodologies and the eventual adoption of the Unified Modelling Language 
		(UML) as the standard language for communicating OO concepts continued the advance of OO technology into 
		the mainstream. The popularity of the object-based Visual Basic language and the parallel development and 
		meteoric adoption of the fully object-oriented 
		Java programming language was the final catalyst that fuelled 
		the final stages of the rapid adoption of OO technologies by the mainstream.
	</para>
	<para>
		ArgoUML was conceived as a tool and environment for use in the analysis and design of object-oriented software 
		systems. In this sense it is similar to many of the commercial CASE tools that are sold as tools for modelling 
		software systems. ArgoUML has a number of very important distictions from many of these tools:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					ArgoUML includes a number of features that support the cognitive needs object-oriented software 
					designers and architects.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					ArgoUML supports open standards extensively - UML, XMI, SVG, OCL and others. In this respect, 
					ArgoUML is still ahead (even almost five years after it's initial introduction) of many commercial 
					tools.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					ArgoUML is a 100% Pure Java application. This allows ArgoUML to run on all platforms for which 
					a reliable port of the Java2 platform is available.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					ArgoUML is an open source product. The availability of the source permits ensures that a new 
					generation of software designers and researchers now have a proven framework from which they 
					can drive the development and evolution of CASE tools technologies.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
		In creating the ArgoUML development tool and environment, Jason Robbins and the rest of his research team at 
		UCL leveraged the benefits of UML as the most prevalent OO modelling language and Java as one of the most 
		productive OO development platforms to produce a solid tool for OO systems design and, further a testbed for
		the evolution of OO CASE tools development and research.
	</para>
	<para>
		Kunle Odutola
	</para>
</preface>