<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "docbookx/docbookx.dtd"> -->
<!-- 

	[ PLEASE DO NOT REMOVE THIS COMMENT BLOCK!! ]
	
	Maintained by Kunle Odutola for the ArgoUML Project
	http://www.argouml.org/
	Template version: 0.0.1
	Template last modified: May 4, 2001
	
-->
<chapter id="introduction">
	<chapterinfo>
		<!-- 
			===========================================================
		   		Authors 
			===========================================================	
		-->
		<!-- Repeat <author> block (and optional <address> and <email> elements) as needed for each "main" author -->	
		&author-kunle.odu;
		&address-kunle.odu;
	</chapterinfo>	
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<!--
		===========================================================
			 Chapter "INTRODUCTION" section 
		===========================================================
	-->
	<sect1>
		<title>Welcome to &argo;</title>
		<para>
			Welcome to &argo; from the &argo-project-link; team at &tigris-link;. &argo; is a powerful yet 
			easy-to-use interactive, graphical software design environment that supports the design, 
			development and documentation of object-oriented software applications. It leverages 
			the <emphasis>Write Once, Run Anywhere</emphasis> promise of the Java2 platform to allow 
			you to design great object-oriented software in your preferred Operating System environment.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you are familiar with a family of software applications called Computer Aided Software 
			Engineering (CASE) tools then you should find &argo; instantly familiar. 
			It is an interactive, graphical modelling CASE tool that is easy to install, learn, 
			use and customise for your own unique design environment. It is built on an extendible foundation 
			of open standards (or industry standards) to ensure interoperability with the rest of the industry. 
			You can share designs created with &argo; and collaborate with colleagues using other tools easily 
			because of it's support for open standards. 
		</para>
		<para>
			The typical users of &argo; include software designers &amp; architects, software developers, 
			business analysts, systems analysts and other professionals involved in the analysis, design and 
			development of software applications. It has a number of features (some unique) that enables 
			it to better support these users in the design of software systems:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Uses the open standard Unified Modelling Language (UML) as the language for 
						documenting and communicating object-oriented designs
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Supports open standards including XML Metadata Interchange format (XMI), Scalable Vector 
						Graphics format (SVG) and Portable Graphics Markup Language natively and as formats 
						for the communicating design information with external systems
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Is a 100% Java application to ensure that it is available for use on all the major OS platforms 
						plus any other OS an implementation of the Java2 platform exists
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Is an Open Source product that enables it's users to extend or customize it. Many users also 
						eventually become contributors to the future development of &argo; itself. On particularly 
						important group of users are researchers and research groups who often endow &argo; with 
						state-of-the-art features ahead of other CASE tools
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Incorporates a number of specific cognitive features to better support the design process:
						<itemizedlist mark="box">
							<listitem>
								<para>
									reflection-in-action
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									opportunistic design
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									comprehension and problem solving
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
				&argo; was originally a product of a research programme at UCL led by Jason E. Robbins.
		</para>
		<caution>
			<title>&argo; version 0.8.x or earlier</title>
			<para>
				This guide is designed for the 0.9.x versions of &argo;. Many of the comments may also 
				be applicable to earlier versions of the software but that has not been tested.
			</para>
		</caution>
	</sect1>
	<!--
		===========================================================
			 Chapter section template - copy for each major "topic" 
												  discussed in this chapter
		===========================================================
	-->
	<sect1>
		<title>About this guide...</title>
		<para>
			This guide - the &document-title;	- is provided to help you get up and running as quickly as 
			possible with &argo;. It provides step-by-step instructions for obtaining and installing 
			&argo;, performing common tasks, and outlines your options for contacting &argo-project-link; 
			team should you need further support or to contribute to &argo;'s development.
		</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>In this guide, you will find...</title>
			<para>
				The remainder of this chapter includes information about documentation conventions and what 
				you need to know to be able to use &argo; effectively. Here's what you can expect to find 
				in the remaining chapters in this guide:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Download and Installation instructions
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Basic tutorial/introduction to &argo; - step-by-step procedures on essentials
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Support option - mailing list, resources, contributions, source code/CVS etc..
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>In this guide, you will not find...</title>
			<para>
				This guide is not a complete user or reference manual for &argo;. The &argo-website; has 
				information about the status of other &argo; documentation including a user manual. 
			</para>
			<para>
				This guide does not attempt to teach you about UML, XMI, SVG or any other such standards 
				that &argo; implements or supports. Neither does it attempt to teach you about the Java 
				platform or your Operating System platform.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>What you should already know</title>
			<para>
				This guide assumes that you know how to use your computer. It also assumes that you have some 
				knowledge of object-oriented software design given your interest in &argo;. You should be familiar 
				with the process of installing software applications on your computer although full installation 
				instructions are 	given for &argo;. 
			</para>
			<para>
				Once &argo; is installed, it is assumed that you know how to point, click, and drag with 
				a mouse or another pointing device and that you can use a keyboard.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Documentation conventions</title>
			<para>
				Before reading this guide, please take a moment to ensure that you understand the conventions 
				followed in the guide. This will help you to use the guide more effectively.
			</para>
			<sect3>
				<title>Conventions related to the use of the mouse</title>
				<informaltable>
					<!-- <title>Conventions related to the use of the mouse</title> -->
					<tgroup cols="2" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
						<colspec align="left" colwidth="2.5in"/>
						<colspec align="left" colwidth="3.2in"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>When you see this...</entry>
								<entry>Do this...</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<command>Click</command>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Press the primary mouse button (usually the left mouse button).
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<command>Double-click</command>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Press the primary mouse button quickly twice.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<command>Right-click</command>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Press the secondary mouse button (usually the right mouse button).
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<menuchoice>
										<guimenu>Files</guimenu>
										<guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem>
									</menuchoice>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Click <emphasis>File</emphasis> on the top-level menu bar and, click the 
									<emphasis>New</emphasis> option in the displayed 'File' menu.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<menuchoice>
										<guimenu>Create</guimenu>
										<guisubmenu>Diagrams</guisubmenu>
										<guimenuitem>ClassDiagram</guimenuitem>
									</menuchoice>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Click <emphasis>Create</emphasis> on the top-level menu bar, click 
									<emphasis>Diagrams</emphasis> in the 'Create' menu that appears, click the 
									<emphasis>ClassDiagram</emphasis> option in the 'Diagrams' submenu that appears.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<command>Select text</command>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Click and drag to highlight text.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</sect3>
			<sect3>
				<title>Conventions related to the use of the keyboard</title>
				<informaltable>
					<!-- <title>Conventions related to the use of the keyboard</title> -->
					<tgroup cols="2" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
						<colspec align="left" colwidth="2.5in"/>
						<colspec align="left" colwidth="3.2in"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>When you see this...</entry>
								<entry>Do this...</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<keycap>Enter</keycap>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Press the Enter key on your keyboard.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<keycombo action="simul">
										<keycap>Control</keycap>
										<keycap>Shift</keycap>
									</keycombo>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Press the Control key and the Shift key at the same time.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<keycombo action="press">
										<keycap>Control</keycap>
										<keycap>C</keycap>
									</keycombo>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Press the Control key and while keeping it pressed, press the C key at the same time.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>If you need further help</title>
		<para>
			The website, mailing lists etc...
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
