<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<chapter id="running">
	<title>Running &argo;</title>
	<para>
    When &argo; starts, then it shows an empty class diagram
    on which you can add various objects. &argo; works according the following
    principles:
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Project and Model</title>
    <para>
      The save and open operations handle one <literal>project</literal> at a
      time. One <literal>project</literal> corresponds to a
      <literal>model</literal> plus diagram information. 
      The <literal>model</literal> might contain many
      objects (ModelElements) which might be present on a diagram, but this is not
      required. Hence, the <literal>model</literal> that is stored in &argo; is
      independent of the contents of the diagrams. But everything together is
      stored in a <literal>project</literal>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Objects</title>
    <para>
      Select objects by left-clicking on them.
      The functionality of &argo; can be activated in the menu, 
      in toolbars,
      or in pop-up menus when right-clicking above an object.
      Many of these functions work on the selected objects.
    </para>
    <para>
      All diagrams have toolbars at the top which are used 
      to create objects on the diagram.
    </para>
  </section>

	<section>
		<title>Overview of the window</title>
		<para>
      The top of the window contains a menu bar with commands available.
      In the <literal>File</literal> menu you can store the project or 
      open another project instead.
    </para>
		<para>
      The upper left part of the &argo; window shows a tree model 
      of diagrams and objects. 
      This view can be adapted to your needs 
      by filtering the objects that are shown, 
      and the structure in which they are shown.
    </para>
		<para>
      The upper right part of &argo; shows the current diagram (one at a time).
      You can drag and drop the objects in the diagrams,
      and you can use the quick-links 
      that appear when hovering over a selected object 
      to create new objects connected to the
      already present objects.
    </para>
		<para>
      The lower right part contains various details of the currently selected 
      object: You select the object in one of the upper
      levels and choose what details you want to examine using the
      tabs.
    </para>
		<para>
      The lower left part contains a list of all ToDo items for this
      model.
    </para>
	</section>

</chapter>
